<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Gigascience</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Gigascience</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">gigascience</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>GigaScience</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2047-217X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10441000</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37602759</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gigascience/giad057</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">giad057</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI00960</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI02254</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>KGML-xDTD: a knowledge graph&#x02013;based machine learning framework for drug treatment prediction and mechanism description</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9731-5153</contrib-id><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Chunyu</given-names></name><!--cqm5886@psu.edu--><aff>
<institution>Huck Institutes of Life Sciences, Pennsylvania State University</institution>, <addr-line>State College, PA 16801</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1473-9071</contrib-id><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Zhihan</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Computer Science, Northwestern University</institution>, <addr-line>Evanston, IL 60208</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Han</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Computer Science, Northwestern University</institution>, <addr-line>Evanston, IL 60208</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0640-954X</contrib-id><name><surname>Koslicki</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><!--dmk333@psu.edu--><aff>
<institution>Huck Institutes of Life Sciences, Pennsylvania State University</institution>, <addr-line>State College, PA 16801</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Department of Computer Science and Engineering, Pennsylvania State University</institution>, <addr-line>State College, PA 16801</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Department of Biology, Pennsylvania State University</institution>, <addr-line>State College, PA 16801</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence address. Chunyu Ma, Westgate building, Pennsylvania State University, University Park, PA 16802 USA. E-mail: <email>cqm5886@psu.edu</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2">Correspondence address. David Koslicki, Westgate building, Pennsylvania State University, University Park, PA 16802 USA. E-mail: <email>dmk333@psu.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-08-21"><day>21</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>21</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>giad057</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>05</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>04</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2023. Published by Oxford University Press GigaScience.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="giad057.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="abs1"><title>Background</title><p>Computational drug repurposing is a cost- and time-efficient approach that aims to identify new therapeutic targets or diseases (indications) of existing drugs/compounds. It is especially critical for emerging and/or orphan diseases due to its cheaper investment and shorter research cycle compared with traditional wet-lab drug discovery approaches. However, the underlying mechanisms of action (MOAs) between repurposed drugs and their target diseases remain largely unknown, which is still a main obstacle for computational drug repurposing methods to be widely adopted in clinical settings.</p></sec><sec id="abs2"><title>Results</title><p>In this work, we propose <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace>: a <bold>K</bold>nowledge <bold>G</bold>raph&#x02013;based <bold>M</bold>achine <bold>L</bold>earning framework for e<bold>x</bold>plainably predicting <bold>D</bold>rugs <bold>T</bold>reating <bold>D</bold>iseases. It is a 2-module framework that not only predicts the treatment probabilities between drugs/compounds and diseases but also biologically explains them via knowledge graph (KG) path-based, testable MOAs. We leverage knowledge-and-publication&#x02013;based information to extract biologically meaningful &#x0201c;demonstration paths&#x0201d; as the intermediate guidance in the Graph-based Reinforcement Learning (GRL) path-finding process. Comprehensive experiments and case study analyses show that the proposed framework can achieve state-of-the-art performance in both predictions of drug repurposing and recapitulation of human-curated drug MOA paths.</p></sec><sec id="abs3"><title>Conclusions</title><p>
<monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> is the first model framework that can offer KG path explanations for drug repurposing predictions by leveraging the combination of prediction outcomes and existing biological knowledge and publications. We believe it can effectively reduce &#x0201c;black-box&#x0201d; concerns and increase prediction confidence for drug repurposing based on predicted path-based explanations and further accelerate the process of drug discovery for emerging diseases.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="keywords"><kwd>drug repurposing</kwd><kwd>reinforcement learning</kwd><kwd>biomedical knowledge graph</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000002</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Science Foundation</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000001</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Traditional drug development is a time-consuming process (from initial chemical identification to clinical trials and finally to Food and Drug Administration [FDA] approval) that takes around 10 to 15&#x000a0;years and also comes along with billions-of-dollars investments and high failure rates [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Considering the rapid pace of novel disease evolution, it is urgent to find a more efficient and economical drug discovery method. Fortunately, it has been observed that a single drug can often be effective in treating multiple diseases. For example, thalidomide was originally used as an antianxiety medication [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] and was later found to have the anticancer potential for the treatment of cancers [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Hence, drug repurposing, also known as the identification of new uses for existing drugs/compounds, might bring us hope to address this urgent need with the advantage of a shorter research cycle, lower development cost, and more preexisting safety tests.</p><p>Existing drug repurposing approaches can roughly be categorized into experimental-based approaches (e.g., binding affinity assays [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], phenotypic screening [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]), clinical-based approaches (e.g., off-label drug use analysis [<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]), and computational-based approaches (e.g., chemical structure&#x02013;based [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and GWAS-based approaches [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]). Compared with the former 2 approaches, the computational approaches are more cost- and time-efficient, particularly when the goal is to prioritize a large number of target drugs/compounds for follow-up experimental investigation. Among all computational drug repurposing methods, the integration of multiple biomedical data sources into a so-called biomedical knowledge graph (BKG) for drug discovery has become popular in recent years [<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] due to the increasing availability of curated biomedical databases such as DrugBank [<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], ChEMBL [<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], and HMDB [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and the advancement of semantic web techniques [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. There are 3 types of existing BKGs: database-based BKGs, literature-based BKGs, and mixed BKGs. The database-based BKGs (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">Hetionet</italic> [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], <italic toggle="yes">BioKG</italic> [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], <italic toggle="yes">iBKH</italic> [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]) are constructed by integrating biomedical data and their relations stored in existing biological databases. The literature-based BKGs (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">GNBR</italic> [<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]) are built by leveraging Natural Language Processing (NLP) techniques to extract semantic information from a large amount of available biomedical literature and electronic health record (EHR) data, which are mostly disease specific [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19&#x02013;21</xref>]. The mixed BKGs (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">CKG</italic> [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], <italic toggle="yes">RTX-KG2</italic> [<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]) are generated by combining the knowledge sources from the above 2 methods.</p><p>Based on these BKGs, several machine learning methods have been proposed or implemented for drug repurposing prediction by treating it as a link prediction task in the BKGs. For example, Himmelstein et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] used the so-called degree-weighted path count (DWPC) to assess the prevalence of 1,206 metapaths and then classified drug&#x02013;disease treatment relations by fitting these DWPC features to a logistic regression model. Ioannidis et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] proposed a novel graph neural network model I-RGCN to learn the node and relation embeddings for the Covid-19 drug repurposing task. Zhang et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] recently predicted the possible drugs for Covid-19 with 5 existing popular knowledge graph completion methods (e.g., TransE [<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], RotatE [<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], DistMult [<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], ComplEx [<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], and STELP [<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]). Although some of these models have shown good performance in drug repurposing prediction on the small-scale BKGs, none have been scaled to massive BKGs with more than millions of nodes and edges and make a comprehensive comparison. More importantly, most of them lack the biological explanatory ability for their predictions, which limits their applicability in clinical research.</p><p>Currently, there are few computational models designed for drug repurposing <italic toggle="yes">explanations</italic>. A common and intuitive explanation based on a biomedical knowledge graph for drug repurposing leverages the semantic BKG-based paths between given drug&#x02013;disease pairs. Sosa et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] applied a graph embedding model UKGE [<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], which utilizes the weighted (the frequency of relation appeared in literature) relation edges in a literature-based KG <italic toggle="yes">GNBR</italic> to identify new indications of drugs for rare diseases and then explain the results via the highest-ranking paths based on confidence scores. However, this method is only applicable in the literature-based BKGs with the weighted edge information. Most BKGs using database-based knowledge do not contain such information. Sang et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] proposed GrEDeL that combines the TransE embedding method with a long short-term memory (LSTM) recurrent neural network (RNN) model to predict drug&#x02013;disease relation. By using the embeddings of BKG paths as model input for predictions, they can provide path-based explanations. However, they claimed that the effectiveness of the approach relies heavily on the NLP tool SemRep, which is reported to have high false positives in named entity recognition [<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Also, they did not fully evaluate how biologically reasonable their predicted path-based mechanisms of action (MOAs) are.</p><p>Besides the existing methods above, we view reinforcement learning (RL) as a promising solution for drug repurposing explanation. RL models solve the decision-making problem, in which an agent learns how to take appropriate actions to maximize cumulative rewards through interactions with the environment. RL has achieved widespread success in various domains, including games, recommendation systems, health care, transportation, and so on [<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Graph reinforcement learning (GRL), first proposed around in 2017, aims to solve graph mining tasks such as link prediction [<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], adversarial attacks [<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], and relational reasoning [<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Unlike its applications in other domains, one of the biggest challenges in GRL is finding an appropriate reward to guide the path searching in specific domains. To address the issue of finding biologically reasonable BKG-based paths for drug repurposing, it is crucial to incorporate biomedical domain knowledge to guide the path-finding process. Liu et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] developed an RL-based model &#x0201c;PoLo&#x0201d; that utilizes the biological meta-paths identified in Himmelstein et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] via the &#x0201c;DWPC&#x0201d; method to supervise path searching for drug repurposing. However, the &#x0201c;PoLo&#x0201d; model does not scale to a massive and complex BKG (e.g., CKG and RTX-KG2) due to its dependence on the &#x0201c;DWPC&#x0201d; method that is reported to be computationally inefficient [<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].</p><p>In this article, we describe <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace>: a <bold>K</bold>nowledge <bold>G</bold>raph&#x02013;based <bold>M</bold>achine <bold>L</bold>earning framework for e<bold>x</bold>plainably predicting <bold>D</bold>rugs <bold>T</bold>reating <bold>D</bold>iseases, which contains 2 modules for both drug repurposing prediction and MOA explanation. We propose to amplify the ability of the RL model in biologically meaningful path searching by utilizing the biologically meaningful &#x0201c;demonstration paths&#x0201d; and pretrained drug repurposing model probability as rewards. We incorporate this idea into the appropriate models (e.g., GraphSAGE [<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], random forest, and ADAC RL [<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] models) and then make them applicable to the explainable drug repurposing problem at massive data scale and complexity. By comparing with the existing popular drug repurposing models and evaluating the predicted paths with an expert-curated path-based drug MOA database <italic toggle="yes">DrugMechDB</italic> [<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], we show that the proposed model framework can achieve state-of-the-art performance in both predictions of drug repurposing and recapitulation of human-curated drug MOA paths provided by DrugMechDB. In further case studies, by comparing the model predictions with the real regulatory networks, we show that the proposed framework effectively identifies biologically reasonable BKG-based MOA paths for real-world applications.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Datasets</title><sec id="sec2-1-1"><title>Customized biomedical knowledge graph</title><p>To accommodate biomedical-reasonable predictions of drugs&#x02019; indications and their mechanisms of action, the ideal biomedical knowledge graph should integrate biomedical knowledge from comprehensive and diverse databases and publications, as well as accurately identify and merge different identifiers representing the same biological entity into one (e.g., &#x0201c;CHEBI:2367&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;CHEMBL455626&#x0201d; are 2 distinct identifiers separately presented in the ChEBI database [<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] and ChEMBL database [<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] but represent the same compound &#x0201c;abyssinone I&#x0201d;). Thus, we utilize the canonicalized version of the Reasoning Tool X Knowledge Graph 2 (<italic toggle="yes">RTX-KG2c</italic>) [<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], one of the largest open-source BKGs that integrates knowledge from extensive human-curated and publication-based databases and has been widely used in the Biomedical Data Translator Project [<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Compared to other commonly used open-source BKGs mentioned above, <italic toggle="yes">RTX-KG2c</italic> is a biolink model&#x02013;based standardized [<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] and regularly updated BKG that efficiently merges biologically and semantically equivalent nodes and edges via multiple curation steps. The version 2.7.3 of <italic toggle="yes">RTX-KG2c</italic> that we use contains around 6.4 million nodes and 39.3 million edges with knowledge from 70 public biomedical sources, where all biological concepts (e.g., &#x0201c;ibuprofen&#x0201d;) are represented as vertices and all concepts&#x02013;predicates&#x02013;concept (e.g., &#x0201c;ibuprofen&#x02013;increases activity of&#x02013;GP1BA gene&#x0201d;) are presented as edges. For drug repurposing purposes, we customized <italic toggle="yes">RTX-KG2c</italic> with 4 principles (see more details in <xref rid="sup11" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Section&#x000a0;S1</xref>): (i) excluding the nodes whose categories are irrelevant to drug repurposing explanation (e.g., &#x0201c;GeographicLocation&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Device&#x0201d;), (ii) filtering out the low-quality edges based on our criteria, (iii) removing the hierarchically redundant edges, and (iv) excluding all drug&#x02013;disease edges. After these processing steps, 3,659,165 nodes with 33 distinct categories (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>) and 18,291,237 edges with 74 distinct types (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>) are left in our customized biomedical knowledge graph, which is used for downstream model training.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1"><label>Figure 1:</label><caption><p>Number of nodes by category (A) and number of edges by predicate (B) in the customized BKG.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="giad057fig1" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-1-2"><title>Data sources for model training</title><p>To train the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> framework for drug repurposing prediction and its MOA explanation, we utilize 4 high-quality and NLP-derived training datasets:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>
<bold>MyChem Data</bold> [<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] is provided by the BioThings API collection [<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], which contains up-to-date annotations regarding indication and contraindication for chemicals collected from 11 reliable data resources (summarized in <xref rid="sup11" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Section&#x000a0;S2</xref>). We use drug&#x02013;disease pairs with the relation &#x0201c;indication&#x0201d; as true positives while those with &#x0201c;contraindication&#x0201d; as true negatives.</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>SemMedDB Data</bold> [<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] is provided by the Semantic MEDLINE Database (SemMedDB), which leverages NLP techniques to extract semantic triples with &#x0201c;treats&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;negatively treats&#x0201d; relations from PubMed abstracts. We use drug&#x02013;disease pairs with the relation &#x0201c;treats&#x0201d; as true positives and those with &#x0201c;negatively treats&#x0201d; as true negatives.</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>NDF-RT Data</bold> [<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] is provided by National Drug File&#x02013;Reference Terminology from the Veterans Health Administration (VHA), which contains FDA-approved information on drug interaction, indications, and contraindications. We use drug&#x02013;disease with therapeutics label &#x0201c;indications&#x0201d; as true positives and those with &#x0201c;contraindications&#x0201d; as true negatives.</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>RepoDB Data</bold> [<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] is a standard set of successful and failed drug&#x02013;disease pairs in clinical trials collected by the Blavatnik Institute at Harvard Medical School. We use drug&#x02013;disease with the status &#x0201c;approved&#x0201d; as true positives and those with &#x0201c;terminated&#x0201d; as true negatives.</p></list-item></list><p>We further filter drug&#x02013;disease pairs from SemMedDB Data due to publication bias and possible NLP mistakes by using both the co-occurrence frequency and the PubMed publication-based normalized Google distance (NGD) [<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] defined below:</p><disp-formula id="update108a8-132ac">
<label>(1)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0001" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
NGD(c1, c2) = \frac{max\lbrace log\mathcal {N}(c1), log\mathcal {N}(c2)\rbrace - log\mathcal {N}(c1, c2)}{logN - min\lbrace log\mathcal {N}(c1), log\mathcal {N}(c2)\rbrace }
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>where <italic toggle="yes">c</italic>1 and <italic toggle="yes">c</italic>2 are 2 biological concepts used in the customized BKG, <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0002" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\mathcal {N}(c1)$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0003" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\mathcal {N}(c2)$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> respectively represent the total number of unique PubMed IDs associated with <italic toggle="yes">c</italic>1 and <italic toggle="yes">c</italic>2, <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0004" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\mathcal {N}(c1, c2)$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> is the total number of unique PubMed IDs shared between <italic toggle="yes">c</italic>1 and <italic toggle="yes">c</italic>2, and <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> is the total number of pairs of Medical Subject Heading (MeSH) terms annotations in PubMed database. Only the SemMedDB drug&#x02013;disease pairs with at least 10 supporting publications and an NGD score of 0.6 or lower are left for the downstream model training.</p><p>These datasets are pooled together and then processed by (i) mapping the raw identifiers of drugs and diseases to the identifiers used in the customized BKG and (ii) removing duplicate drug&#x02013;disease pairs in both the true-positive set and the true-negative set. Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref> shows the drug&#x02013;disease pair count from each data source after data preprocessing.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1:</label><caption><p>Pair count of true-positive (indications) and true-negative (contraindications or no effect) data from 4 data sources after data preprocessing</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">True positive (treats)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">True negative (not treat)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MyChem</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,663</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26,795</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SemMedDB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,255</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDF-RT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,421</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,119</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RepoDB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,127</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">738</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shared</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,971</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">526</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21,437</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33,189</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1fn1"><p>Note that &#x0201c;shared&#x0201d; means those pairs are from 2 or more data sources.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-1-3"><title>DrugMechDB</title><p>DrugMechDB [<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], to our best knowledge, is the first human-curated path-based database for explaining the MOA from a drug to a disease in an indication, with 3,593 MOA paths for 3,327 unique drug&#x02013;disease pairs. These paths are extracted from free-text descriptions from DrugBank, Wikipedia, and other literature sources and then have been curated by subject matter experts and also follow the schema of the Biolink model. Hence, we can match them to nodes used in the RTX-KG2 BKG via the <italic toggle="yes">Node Synonymizer</italic> function [<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Since the maximum length of predicted MOA paths generated by the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> framework is fixed to 3 in this study due to memory and training time constraints, we consider those 3-hop BKG-based paths as &#x0201c;correct&#x0201d; if all 4 of their nodes show up in the complete DrugMechDB-based MOA paths. Thus, we find 472 unique drug&#x02013;disease pairs of which each has at least 1 such &#x0201c;correct&#x0201d; matched path in all possible 3-hop paths between drug and disease in the customized BKG. The large reduction in evaluation paths is likely due to incompleteness of the underlying knowledge graphs, imperfect bioentity matching, and possibility of disconnected drug and disease pairs in the customized BKG. However, these paths are used for additional, external validation data only. We use the matched paths as true-positive biologically meaningful paths for the evaluation of the model-predicted paths in the task of MOA prediction (introduced below).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Model framework</title><p>The model framework of <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> consists of 2 modules: a drug repurposing prediction (DRP) module that combines the advantages of GraphSAGE [<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and a random forest model, and an MOA prediction module that utilizes an adversarial actor&#x02013;critic RL model. We show the overview of the entire model framework in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. The implementation details of each module in <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> framework are presented in <xref rid="sup11" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Section&#x000a0;S3</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="fig2"><label>Figure 2:</label><caption><p>Illustration of the entire <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model framework: DRP module (left) and MOA prediction module (right).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="giad057fig2" position="float"/></fig><sec id="sec2-2-1"><title>Notations</title><p>Let <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0005" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\mathcal {G} = \lbrace \mathcal {V}, \mathcal {E}\rbrace$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> be a directed biomedical knowledge graph, where each node <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0006" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$v \in \mathcal {V}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> represents a biological entity (e.g., a specific drug, disease, gene, or pathway), and each edge <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0007" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$e \in \mathcal {E}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> represents a biomedical relationship (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">interacts-with</italic>; see more in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>). We use <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0008" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\mathcal {V}^{\mathrm{drug}}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> to represent all the drug nodes (the nodes with the categories of &#x0201c;Drug&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Small Molecule&#x0201d; in the customized BKG) and <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0009" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\mathcal {V}^{\mathrm{disease}}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> to represent all the disease nodes (the nodes with the categories of &#x0201c;Disease,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;PhenotypicFeature,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;BehavioralFeature,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;DiseaseOrPhenotypicFeature&#x0201d; in the customized BKG). For each notation, we use bold formatting to represent its embedding (e.g., <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0010" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\boldsymbol {v}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> represents the embedding of <italic toggle="yes">v</italic> ).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2-2"><title>DRP module</title><p>Drug repurposing aims to identify new indications of existing drugs/compounds. We solve it as a link prediction problem on the graph <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0011" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\mathcal {G}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>. Specifically, given any drug&#x02013;disease pair (<italic toggle="yes">v<sub>i</sub></italic>, <italic toggle="yes">v<sub>j</sub></italic>) where <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0012" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$v_i \in \mathcal {V}^{\mathrm{drug}}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0013" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$v_j \in \mathcal {V}^{\mathrm{disease}}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, we predict the probability that drug <italic toggle="yes">i</italic> can be used to treat disease <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>. We first use GraphSAGE to calculate the embedding for each node. Ideally, the node embeddings should contain 2 kinds of information: node attributes and node neighborhoods.</p><p>To capture the neighborhood information, we optimize GraphSAGE to encourage neighbor nodes to have similar embeddings and nonneighbor nodes to have distinct embeddings. Specifically, we perform random walks for each node to collect its neighborhood information and train the model to maximize a node&#x02019;s similarity with its neighbor nodes. For a node <italic toggle="yes">u</italic>, the loss is calculated as</p><disp-formula id="equ2">
<label>(2)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0014" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
L_{\mathcal {G}}(\boldsymbol {z}_u) = - \log (\sigma (\boldsymbol {z}_u^{\top }\boldsymbol {z}_v)) - k \cdot \mathbb {E}_{v_n \sim P_n(v)} \log (\sigma (\boldsymbol {z}_u^{\top }\boldsymbol {z}_{v_n}))
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>where <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0015" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\boldsymbol {z}_u, \boldsymbol {z}_v$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> are respectively the embeddings of nodes <italic toggle="yes">u, v</italic>, &#x003c3; is the sigmoid function; <italic toggle="yes">v</italic> is a node that co-occurs with <italic toggle="yes">u</italic> in fixed-length random walks; <italic toggle="yes">P<sub>n</sub></italic> represents negative sampling distribution; and <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> indicates the number of negative samples (nodes not in <italic toggle="yes">u</italic>&#x02019;s fixed-length neighborhood).</p><p>To capture the node attributes information, we utilize the PubMedBERT model [<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>], a pretrained language model designed for biomedical texts, to generate a node attribute embedding for each node based on the concatenation of the node&#x02019;s name and category. We further compress the embeddings to 100 dimensions with principal components analysis (PCA) to reduce memory usage and use them as the initial node feature for GraphSAGE. In this way, the final GraphSAGE embedding of each node should contain the information regarding both graph topology and node attributes. We concatenate the GraphSAGE embeddings of drug&#x02013;disease pairs and use them as input of a random forest model to classify each drug&#x02013;disease pair into one of the &#x0201c;not treat,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;treat,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;unknown&#x0201d; classes. We obtain &#x0201c;treat&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;not treat&#x0201d; drug&#x02013;disease pairs from 4 data sources (described in &#x0201c;Data sources for model training&#x0201d; section). We generate &#x0201c;unknown&#x0201d; drug&#x02013;disease pairs through negative sampling [<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], that is, replacing the drug or disease identifier in each &#x0201c;treat&#x0201d; drug&#x02013;disease pair with a random drug or disease identifier to generate a new pair that does not appear in both the &#x0201c;treat&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;not treat&#x0201d; classes. Specifically, for each unique &#x0201c;treat&#x0201d; drug&#x02013;disease pair, we respectively replace its drug identifier with 1 random drug identifier as well as replace its disease identifier with 1 random disease identifier to make the &#x0201c;unknown&#x0201d; drug&#x02013;disease pairs.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2-3"><title>MOA prediction module</title><p>When potential indications of a given drug are identified by the drug repurposing prediction module, a natural yet essential question is: can we biologically explain the predictions? We solve this by employing an RL model to predict the BKG-based MOA paths, which are the paths on the knowledge graph from drug nodes to disease nodes. These BKG-based MOA paths can semantically describe an abstract biological process of how a drug treats a disease.</p><sec id="sec2-2-3-1"><title>Demonstration paths</title><p>To encourage the RL agent to terminate the path searching at the expected diseases through a biologically reasonable path, we leverage so-called "demonstration paths", a set of biologically likely paths (e.g., drug1&#x02013;gene1&#x02013;protein3&#x02013;disease1) that explains the underlying reasons for why a drug can treat a disease. We extract 396,705 demonstration paths from the customized BKG using the known drug&#x02013;target interactions collected from 2 curated biomedical data sources: DrugBank (v5.1) and Molecular Data Provider (v1.2) (see &#x0201c;Data Availability&#x0201d; section), as well as the PubMed publication-based NGD (see Equation&#x000a0;<xref rid="update108a8-132ac" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>). We show more details regarding demonstration path extraction in <xref rid="sup11" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Section&#x000a0;S4</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2-3-2"><title>Adversarial actor&#x02013;critic reinforcement learning</title><p>We formulate the MOA prediction as a path-finding problem and adapt the adversarial actor&#x02013;critic reinforcement learning model [<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] to solve it. Reinforcement learning is defined as a Markov decision process (MDP) that contains:</p><p>
<bold>States</bold>: Each state <italic toggle="yes">s<sub>t</sub></italic> at time <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> is defined as <italic toggle="yes">s<sub>t</sub></italic> = (<italic toggle="yes">v<sub>drug</sub></italic>, <italic toggle="yes">v<sub>t</sub></italic>, (<italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic> &#x02212; 1</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">e<sub>t</sub></italic>), &#x02026;, (<italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic> &#x02212; <italic toggle="yes">K</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">e</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic> &#x02212; (<italic toggle="yes">K</italic> &#x02212; 1)</sub>)), where <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0016" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$v_{drug} \in \mathcal {V}^{\mathrm{drug}}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> is a given starting drug node; <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0017" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$v_{t} \in \mathcal {V}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> represents the node where the agent locates at time <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>; and the tuple (<italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic> &#x02212; <italic toggle="yes">K</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">e</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic> &#x02212; (<italic toggle="yes">K</italic> &#x02212; 1)</sub>) represents the previous <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>th node and (<italic toggle="yes">K</italic> &#x02212; 1)th predicate. For the initial state <italic toggle="yes">s</italic><sub>0</sub>, the previous nodes and predicates are substituted by a special dummy node and predicate. We concatenate the embedding of all nodes and predicates of <italic toggle="yes">s<sub>t</sub></italic> to get the state embedding <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0018" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\boldsymbol {s}_{t}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, where the node embeddings are node attribute embeddings generated with the PubMedBERT model (see &#x0201c;DRP module&#x0201d; section) and the predicate embeddings employ one-hot vectors.</p><p>
<bold>Actions</bold>: The action space <italic toggle="yes">A<sub>t</sub></italic> of each node <italic toggle="yes">v<sub>t</sub></italic> includes a self-loop action <italic toggle="yes">a<sub>self</sub></italic> and the actions to reach its outgoing neighbors in the graph <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0019" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\mathcal {G}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>. Due to memory limitation and extremely large out-degree of certain nodes in the knowledge graph, we prune the neighbor actions based on the PageRank scores if a node has more than 3,000 neighbors. Specifically, we let <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0020" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$A_{t}= (a_{self}, a_{1},\dots , a_{k},\dots , a_{n_{v_t}})$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0021" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$n_{v_t}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> is out-degree of node <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0022" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$v_t \in \mathcal {V}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>. For each action <italic toggle="yes">a<sub>t</sub></italic> = (<italic toggle="yes">e<sub>t</sub></italic>, <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic> + 1</sub>) &#x02208; <italic toggle="yes">A<sub>t</sub></italic> taken at time <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>, we concatenate its node and predicate embeddings to obtain action embedding <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0023" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\boldsymbol {a}_t$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>. We learn 2 embedding matrices <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0024" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\boldsymbol{E}^{N_\mathrm{n} \times \mathrm{d}}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0025" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\boldsymbol{E}^{N_\mathrm{p} \times \mathrm{d}}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, respectively, for nodes and predicates (note that each subnetwork uses separate embedding matrices), where <italic toggle="yes">d</italic> represents the embedding dimension, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub>n</sub> represents the number of nodes in the graph, and <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub>p</sub> represents the number of predicate categories in the graph.</p><p>
<bold>Rewards</bold>: During the path-searching process, the agent only receives a terminal reward <italic toggle="yes">R<sub>e, T</sub></italic> from the environment (i.e., there is no intermediate reward from environment: <italic toggle="yes">R<sub>e, t</sub></italic> = 0, &#x02200;<italic toggle="yes">t</italic> &#x0003c; <italic toggle="yes">T</italic>). Let <italic toggle="yes">v<sub>T</sub></italic> be the last node of the path, and <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0026" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\mathcal {N}_{drug}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> be the known diseases that drug <italic toggle="yes">v<sub>drug</sub></italic> can treat. The terminal reward <italic toggle="yes">R<sub>e, T</sub></italic> from environment is calculated with the drug repurposing model via</p><disp-formula>
<tex-math id="TM0027" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
{R_{e,T}=\left\lbrace \begin{array}{ll}1, &#x00026;\,\, \mbox{if}\ v_T \in \mathcal {N}_{drug}.\\
p_{treat}, &#x00026;\,\, \mbox{if}\ v_{T} \notin \mathcal {N}_{drug} ; v_{T} \in \mathcal {V}^{\mathrm{disease}}\ \mathrm{and}\ f(v_{drug}, v_{T})\ \rm{is\,\,predicted\,\,as\,\,''treat''}.\\
0, &#x00026;\,\, \mbox{if}\ v_{T} \notin \mathcal {N}_{drug} ; v_{T} \in \mathcal {V}^{\mathrm{disease}}\ \mathrm{and}\ f(v_{drug}, v_{T})\ \rm{is\,\,not\,\,predicted\,\,as\,\,''treat''}.\\
-1, &#x00026;\,\, \mbox{if}\ v_{T} \notin \mathcal {V}^{\mathrm{disease}}, \end{array} \right.}
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>where <italic toggle="yes">p<sub>treat</sub></italic> is the &#x0201c;treat&#x0201d; class probability predicted by the drug repurposing model <italic toggle="yes">f</italic>.</p><p>The adversarial actor&#x02013;critic RL model consists of 4 subnetworks that share the same model architecture MLP<sup><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sup> (note that <italic toggle="yes">i</italic> represents the id of each subnetwork described later, such as <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> for <italic toggle="yes">actor network, c</italic> for <italic toggle="yes">critic network</italic>, etc.) but with different parameters:</p><disp-formula id="update10cb0-1c013">
<label>(3)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0028" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
\mathrm{MLP}^{i}(X) = BA(BA(XW^i_{1}+b^i_{1})W^i_{2}+b^i_{2})W^i_{3}+b^i_{3}
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>where {<inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0029" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${W^i_{1}, W^i_{2}, W^i_{3}, b^i_{1}, b^i_{2}, b^i_{3}}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>} are the parameters and biases of linear transformations, and <italic toggle="yes">BA</italic> represents a batch normalization layer followed by an ELU activation function.</p><p>
<bold>Actor network</bold>: The actor network learns a path-finding policy &#x003c0;<sub>&#x003b8;</sub> (note that &#x003b8; represents all parameters of the actor network) to guide the agent to choose an action <italic toggle="yes">a<sub>t</sub></italic> from the action space <italic toggle="yes">A<sub>t</sub></italic> based on the current state <italic toggle="yes">s<sub>t</sub></italic>:</p><disp-formula id="update13672-1451d">
<label>(4)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0030" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
\pi _{\theta }(a_{t}|s_{t}, A_{t}) = \mathrm{softmax}(\boldsymbol {A}_{t} \odot \mathrm{MLP}^{a}(\boldsymbol {s}_t))
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>where <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0031" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\boldsymbol {A}_{t}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> is the embedding matrix of the action space <italic toggle="yes">A<sub>t</sub></italic>; &#x02299; represents the dot product. Here, &#x003c0;<sub>&#x003b8;</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">a<sub>t</sub></italic>|<italic toggle="yes">s<sub>t</sub></italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A<sub>t</sub></italic>) represents the probability of choosing action <italic toggle="yes">a<sub>t</sub></italic> at time <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> from the action space <italic toggle="yes">A<sub>t</sub></italic> given the state <italic toggle="yes">s<sub>t</sub></italic>.</p><p>
<bold>Critic network</bold>: The critic network [<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>] estimates the expected reward <italic toggle="yes">Q</italic><sub>&#x003d5;</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">s<sub>t</sub></italic>, <italic toggle="yes">a<sub>t</sub></italic>) (note that &#x003d5; represents all parameters of the critic network) if the agent takes the action <italic toggle="yes">a<sub>t</sub></italic> at the state <italic toggle="yes">s<sub>t</sub></italic> by</p><disp-formula id="equ5">
<label>(5)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0032" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
Q_{\phi }(s_{t},a_{t}) = \mathrm{MLP}^{c}(\boldsymbol {s}_t) \odot \boldsymbol {a}_{t}
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>
<bold>Path discriminator network</bold>: Since the RL agent only receives a terminal reward <italic toggle="yes">R<sub>e, T</sub></italic> from the environment indicating whether it reaches an expected target, to encourage the agent to find biologically reasonable paths and provide intermediate rewards, we further guide it with demonstration paths. This network is essentially a binary classifier that distinguishes whether a path segment (<italic toggle="yes">s<sub>t</sub></italic>, <italic toggle="yes">a<sub>t</sub></italic>) is from demonstration paths or generated by the actor network. We treat all the known demonstration path segments <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0033" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$(s_{t}^{D}, a_{t}^{D})$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> as positive samples and all actor-generated non-demonstration path segments <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0034" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$(s_{t}^{ND}, a_{t}^{ND})$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> as negative samples. The path discriminator network <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0035" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$D_{p}(s,a) = \mathrm{sigmoid}(\mathrm{MLP}^{p}(\boldsymbol {s} \oplus \boldsymbol {a}))$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0036" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\boldsymbol {s}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0037" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\boldsymbol {a}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> are respectively the embeddings of the state <italic toggle="yes">s</italic> and the action <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>; &#x02295; represents the concatenation operator and is optimized with</p><disp-formula id="equ6">
<label>(6)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0038" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
L_{p} = - \mathbb {E}_{(s,a) \sim P_{D}}[\log (D_{p}(s,a))] - \mathbb {E}_{(s,a) \sim P_{A}}[\log (1-D_{p}(s,a))]
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>where <italic toggle="yes">P<sub>D</sub></italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P<sub>A</sub></italic> respectively represent the demonstration path segment distribution and the actor-generated non-demonstration path segment distribution. Based on the probability <italic toggle="yes">D<sub>p</sub></italic>(<italic toggle="yes">s<sub>t</sub></italic>, <italic toggle="yes">a<sub>t</sub></italic>), the path discriminator&#x02013;based intermediate reward <italic toggle="yes">R<sub>p, t</sub></italic> is calculated as</p><disp-formula id="equ7">
<label>(7)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0039" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
R_{p,t} = \log (D_{p}(s_{t},a_{t})) - \log (1-D_{p}(s_{t},a_{t})).
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>
<bold>Meta-path discriminator network</bold>: Similar to the path discriminator, this network aims to judge whether the meta-path of the actor-generated paths is similar to that of demonstration paths. The meta-path is the path of node categories (e.g., [&#x0201c;Drug&#x0201d;&#x02192;&#x0201c;Gene&#x0201d;&#x02192;&#x0201c;BiologicalProcess&#x0201d;&#x02192;&#x0201c;Disease&#x0201d;]). Similarly, the meta-path discriminator <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0040" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$D_{m}(M) = \mathrm{sigmoid}(\mathrm{MLP}^{m}(\boldsymbol {M}))$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0041" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\boldsymbol {M}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> is the embedding of the meta-path <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> defined as the concatenation of learned category embeddings of all nodes that appear in the path, is also a binary classifier where the meta-paths of demonstration paths are treated as positive samples while others are negative samples. We optimize it with the following loss:</p><disp-formula id="equ8">
<label>(8)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0042" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
L_{m}= - \mathbb {E}_{M \sim P^M_{D}}[\log (D_{m}(M))] - \mathbb {E}_{M \sim P^M_{A}}[\log (1-D_{m}(M))]
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>where <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0043" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$P^M_{D}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0044" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$P^M_{A}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> respectively represent the demonstration meta-path distribution and the actor-generated non-demonstration meta-path distribution. The intermediate reward <italic toggle="yes">R<sub>m, t</sub></italic> generated by the meta-path discriminator is calculated by</p><disp-formula id="equ9">
<label>(9)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0045" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
R_{m,t} = \log (D_{m}(M)) - \log (1-D_{m}(M)).
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>The integrated intermediate reward <italic toggle="yes">R<sub>t</sub></italic> at time <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> is then calculated as</p><disp-formula id="equ10">
<label>(10)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0046" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
R_{t} = {\alpha }_{p}R_{p,t}+{\alpha }_{m}R_{m,t}+(1-{\alpha }_{p}-{\alpha }_{m}){\gamma }^{T-t}R_{e,T}
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>where &#x003b1;<sub><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></sub> &#x02208; [0, 1] and &#x003b1;<sub><italic toggle="yes">m</italic></sub> &#x02208; [0, 1 &#x02212; &#x003b1;<sub><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></sub>] are hyperparameters, &#x003b3; is the decay coefficient, and <italic toggle="yes">R<sub>e, T</sub></italic> is defined in the &#x0201c;Rewards&#x0201d; section&#x000a0;above.</p><p>To optimize the critic network, we minimize the temporal difference (TD) error [<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] with loss:</p><disp-formula id="equ11">
<label>(11)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0047" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
L_{c}= \mathrm{TD}^{2} = [(R_{t} + Q_{\phi }(s_{t+1},a_{t+1})) - Q_{\phi }(s_{t},a_{t})]^{2}.
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>Since the goal of the actor network is to achieve the largest expected reward by learning an optimal actor policy, we optimize the actor network by maximizing <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0048" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$J({\theta }) = \mathbb {E}_{a \sim {\pi }_{\theta }}[Q_{\phi }(s_{t},a)]$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>. We use the REINFORCE algorithm [<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] to optimize the parameters. To encourage more diverse exploration in finding paths, we use the entropy of &#x003c0;<sub>&#x003b8;</sub> as a regularization term and optimize the actor network with the following stochastic gradient of the loss function <italic toggle="yes">L<sub>a</sub></italic>:</p><disp-formula id="update1c23e-11613">
<label>(12)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0049" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
{\nabla }_{\theta }L_{a} = - {\nabla }_{\theta }J({\theta })= - \mathbb {E}_{{\pi }_{\theta }}[{\nabla }_{\theta }\mathrm{TD} \log {\pi }_{\theta }(a_{t}|s_{t})] - {\alpha }{\nabla }_{\theta }\mathrm{entropy}({\pi }_{\theta })
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>where &#x003c0;<sub>&#x003b8;</sub> is the action probability distribution based on the actor policy, and &#x003b1; is the entropy weight.</p><p>We follow Zhao et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] to train the adversarial actor&#x02013;critic RL model in a multistage way. First, we initialized the actor network using the behavior cloning method [<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] in which the training set of demonstration paths is used to guide the sampling of the agent with mean square error (MSE) loss. Then, in the first <italic toggle="yes">z</italic> epochs, we freeze the parameters of the actor network and the critic network and respectively train the path discriminator network and meta-path discriminator network by minimizing <italic toggle="yes">L<sub>p</sub></italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L<sub>m</sub></italic>. After <italic toggle="yes">z</italic> epochs, we unfreeze the actor network and the critic network and optimize them together by minimizing a joint loss <italic toggle="yes">L<sub>joint</sub></italic> = <italic toggle="yes">L<sub>a</sub></italic> + <italic toggle="yes">L<sub>c</sub></italic>.</p></sec></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3-1"><title>Evaluation settings</title><sec id="sec3-1-1"><title>Data split</title><p>The post-processed drug&#x02013;disease pairs (described in &#x0201c;Data sources for model training&#x0201d; section) are split into training, validation, and test sets where the drug&#x02013;disease pairs of each unique drug are randomly split according to a ratio of 8/1/1. For example, let&#x02019;s say drugA has 10 known diseases that it treats (e.g., drugA&#x02013;disease1, &#x02026;, drugA&#x02013;disease10), 8 pairs are randomly split into the training set, 1 pair is to the validation set, and 1 pair to the test set. With this data split method, the model can be exposed to every drug in the training set, which complies with our goal of predicting new indications of known drugs and their potential MOAs based on the MOA of known target diseases.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-1-2"><title>Evaluation metrics</title><p>The proposed framework <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> is evaluated on 2 types of tasks: <italic toggle="yes"><bold>predicting drug&#x02013;disease &#x0201c;treat&#x0201d; probability</bold></italic> (i.e., drug repurposing prediction) as well as <italic toggle="yes"><bold>identifying biologically reasonable MOA paths from all BKG-based path candidates</bold></italic> (i.e., MOA prediction). These 2 tasks are evaluated based on classification accuracy-based metrics (e.g., accuracy, macro F1 score) and ranking-based metrics (e.g., mean percentile rank, mean reciprocal rank, and proportion of ranks smaller than K) defined as follows:</p><p>
<bold>Accuracy (ACC)</bold> is the fraction of the model classification is correct, computed as</p><disp-formula id="equ13">
<label>(13)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0050" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
\mbox{ACC} = \frac{\mbox{Number of correct classifications}}{\mbox{Total number of drug-disease pair classifications}}.
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>
<bold>Macro F1 score (Macro-F1)</bold> is the unweighted mean of all the per-class F1 scores:</p><disp-formula id="update163ea-16860">
<label>(14)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0051" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
F1^{c} = 2*\frac{precision^{c} \times recall^{c}}{precision^{c} + recall^{c}} , \mbox{Macro-F1} = \frac{1}{|C|} \sum _{c \in C}{F1^{c}}
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>where <italic toggle="yes">C</italic> presents classification classes (e.g., &#x0201c;treat,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;not treat,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;unknown&#x0201d;).</p><p>
<bold>Mean percentile rank (MPR)</bold> is the average percentile rank of the 3-hop DrugMechDB-matched BKG-based path (described in &#x0201c;DrugMechDB&#x0201d; section) of true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pairs:</p><disp-formula id="update1d126-1f1e6">
<label>(15)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0052" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
\mbox{MPR} = \frac{1}{|PR|} \sum _{pr \in PR}{pr}
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>where <italic toggle="yes">PR</italic> is a list of percentile ranks of DrugMechDB-matched BKG-based paths of true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pairs (&#x0201c;treat&#x0201d; category).</p><p>
<bold>Mean reciprocal rank (MRR)</bold> is the average inverse rank of true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pairs (&#x0201c;treat&#x0201d; category) or their 3-hop DrugMechDB-matched BKG-based paths:</p><disp-formula id="update149d6-1a869">
<label>(16)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0053" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
\mbox{MRR} = \frac{1}{|R|} \sum _{r \in R}{\frac{1}{r}}
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>where <italic toggle="yes">R</italic> is a list of ranks of true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pairs (for DRP task) or DrugMechDB-matched BKG-based paths (for MOA prediction task).</p><p>
<bold>Hit@K</bold> is the proportion of ranks not larger than K for true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pairs (&#x0201c;treat&#x0201d; category) or their 3-hop DrugMechDB-matched BKG-based paths:</p><disp-formula id="update1423b-1bc92">
<label>(17)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0054" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
\mbox{Hit@K} = \frac{1}{|R|} \sum _{r \in R}{|r \le K|}
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>where <italic toggle="yes">R</italic> is a list of ranks of true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pairs (for DRP task) or DrugMechDB-matched BKG-based paths (for MOA prediction task).</p></sec><sec id="sec3-1-3"><title>Drug repurposing prediction evaluation method</title><p>We utilize the metrics <italic toggle="yes">ACC</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Macro-F1</italic> to measure the accuracy of drug repurposing prediction of our <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> framework while using ranking-based metrics <italic toggle="yes">MRR</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Hit@K</italic> to show its capability in reducing false positives (i.e., the false drug&#x02013;disease pairs ranking higher among possible drug&#x02013;disease candidates). We use the following 3 methods to generate non-true-positive drug&#x02013;disease candidates for each true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pair to calculate the ranks that are employed in the <italic toggle="yes">MRR</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Hit@K</italic> calculation:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>
<bold>Drug rank&#x02013;based replacement</bold>: For each true positive drug&#x02013;disease pair, the drug rank&#x02013;based replacement pairs are generated by replacing the drug entity with each of all 274,676 other drugs in the customized BKG while excluding all known true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pairs.</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>Disease rank&#x02013;based replacement</bold>: For each true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pair, the disease rank&#x02013;based replacement pairs are generated by replacing the disease entity with each of all 124,638 other diseases in the BKG while excluding all known true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pairs.</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>Combined replacement:</bold> For each true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pair, the combined replacement pairs are the combination of all replacement pairs of the above 2 methods. All known true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pairs are excluded from these replacement pairs.</p></list-item></list><p>Due to the massive size of possible drug&#x02013;disease candidates, some baseline models (e.g., GAT and GraphSAGE+SVM) are not applicable in this setting within a reasonable time (e.g., a week). Thus, we also employ a small subset of drug&#x02013;disease replacements to calculate the <italic toggle="yes">MRR</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Hit@K</italic>, allowing for comparison between <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> with all baselines. Specifically, we utilize 1,000 random drug&#x02013;disease pairs from the combined replacement set above: 500 with drug ID replacement and 500 with disease ID replacement. To enhance the robustness of results obtained through this random replacement method, we use this method to generate 10 sets of random drug&#x02013;disease pairs (each with 1,000 pairs) independently and calculate the mean and standard deviation of the ranking-based metrics outcomes. In addition, since the drug repurposing prediction module of <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> framework does 3-class classification while other baselines do 2-class classification, for a fair comparison, we recalculate <italic toggle="yes">ACC</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Macro-F1</italic> for <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> by excluding the &#x0201c;unknown&#x0201d; class.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-1-4"><title>MOA prediction evaluation method</title><p>For the evaluation of MOA prediction, we use the DrugMechDB [<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] to obtain the expert-verified MOA paths as ground-truth data, and match each biological concept in these verified MOA paths to the biological entities used in the customized BKG, and then generate the BKG-based matched paths of DrugMechDB drug&#x02013;disease pairs (described in &#x0201c;DrugMechDB&#x0201d; section), which are considered biologically meaningful MOA paths. We first calculate the path scores for all 3-hop KG paths between drug and disease with the path-finding policy learned from adversarial actor&#x02013;critic RL model using the following equation:</p><disp-formula id="update15cef-1511c">
<label>(18)</label>
<tex-math id="TM0055" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}
\mbox{path score} = \sum _{i=1}^{k}{{\delta }^{i-1} \times \log (P_{i} \times N_{i})}
\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>where <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> is the number of hops in this path, &#x003b4; is a decay coefficient (we set it to 0.9 in this study), <italic toggle="yes">P<sub>i</sub></italic> represents the probability of choosing action <italic toggle="yes">a<sub>i</sub></italic> in the <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0056" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$i^{th}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> hop following this path based on the trained RL model, and <italic toggle="yes">N<sub>i</sub></italic> is the number of possible actions in the <inline-formula><tex-math id="TM0057" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$i^{th}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> hop.</p><p>With the path scores, we obtain the ranks of the DrugMechDB-matched BKG-based paths and calculate their ranking-based metrics (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">MPR, MRR</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Hit@K</italic>). For those drug&#x02013;disease pairs with multiple matched paths, we use the highest ranks of the matched paths as their ranks in the metrics calculation. We compare <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> with the baseline models based on these metrics to show the capability of the MOA prediction module of <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> in identifying biologically reasonable MOA paths from a massive and complex BKG with a comparably low false positive. In addition, we further perform 2 case studies to evaluate the effectiveness of <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> in identifying the biologically reasonable MOA paths.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>Drug repurposing prediction evaluation</title><p>For drug repurposing prediction evaluation, we compare the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model framework against several state-of-the-art (SOTA) KG-based models and variants of <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> for drug repurposing prediction based on the method described in &#x0201c;Drug repurposing prediction evaluation method&#x0201d; section.</p><p>We use 8 different SOTA KG-based models as baseline models that are commonly used for BKG-based drug repurposing [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. <monospace>TransE</monospace> [<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], <monospace>TransR</monospace> [<xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>], and <monospace>RotatE</monospace> [<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] are the translation distance&#x02013;based models that regard a relation (e.g., &#x0201c;treats&#x0201d;) as a &#x0201c;translation&#x0201d;/&#x0201d;rotation&#x0201d; (e.g., a kind of spatial transformation) from a head entity (e.g., a drug node) to a tail entity (e.g., a disease node). <monospace>DistMult</monospace> [<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] is a bilinear model that measures the latent semantic similarity of a knowledge graph triple (head entity, relation/predicate, tail entity) with a trilinear dot product. <monospace>ComplEx</monospace> [<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] and <monospace>ANALOGY</monospace> [<xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>] are the extensions of <monospace>DistMult</monospace> that consider more complex relations (e.g., asymmetric relations). <monospace>SimpLE</monospace> [<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] is a tensor factorization&#x02013;based model to learn the semantic relation of a knowledge graph triple. <monospace>GAT</monospace> [<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] is a popular graph neural model that leverages the important graph topology structure based on self-attention mechanism for graph-associated tasks (e.g., link prediction). Implementation details of these baselines are presented in <xref rid="sup11" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Section&#x000a0;S5</xref>.</p><p>Besides these SOTA baseline models, we also compare the drug repurposing prediction module in <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> with its several variants to show the effectiveness of model components. For example, to show efficacy of the combination of GraphSage and random forest (RF), we use a pure GraphSAGE model for link prediction (<monospace>GraphSAGE-link</monospace>), the combination of GraphSage and logistic model (<monospace>GraphSAGE-logistic</monospace>), and the combination of GraphSage and support vector machine (SVM) model (<monospace>GraphSAGE-SVM</monospace>). To demonstrate the effectiveness of node attribute embeddings (described in &#x0201c;DRP module&#x0201d; section) in improving repurposing prediction, we conduct an ablation experiment that replaces node attribute embeddings (NAEs) with random embeddings (initialized with the Xavier method [<xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]) as GraphSage initialized embeddings (<monospace>KGML-xDTD w/o NAE</monospace>); to support rationality of setting &#x0201c;unknown&#x0201d; class through negative sampling (described in &#x0201c;DRP module&#x0201d; section), we modify the drug repurposing prediction module for 2-class classification (i.e., true positive and true negative) (<monospace>2-class KGML-xDTD</monospace>) as a baseline comparison model.</p><p>Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows the performance of the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model and all other baseline models in the task of drug repurposing prediction based on test set (described in &#x0201c;Data split&#x0201d; section). For the calculation of the <italic toggle="yes">MRR</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Hit@K</italic> used in this table, we utilize the random subset replacement method described in the&#x000a0;&#x0201c;Drug repurposing prediction evaluation method&#x0201d; section. As shown in the table, on the one hand, the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> outperforms most of the baseline models and achieves comparable performance as <monospace>GAT</monospace> in classification-based metrics (e.g., accuracy, macro F1 score), indicating its effectiveness in classifying known &#x0201c;treat&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;not treat&#x0201d; drug&#x02013;disease pairs with both attribute and neighborhood information on the knowledge graph. On the other hand, <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace>&#x02019;s exceptional performance in ranking-based metrics shows its superiority over baselines in identifying new indications of existing drugs out of a large number of possible drug&#x02013;disease pairs with relatively low false positives, which is of great importance for guiding clinical research. Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> displays the comparison results where we calculate the <italic toggle="yes">MRR</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Hit@K</italic> with 3 different &#x0201c;complete&#x0201d; replacement methods (described in &#x0201c;Drug repurposing prediction evaluation method&#x0201d; section). Although <monospace>GAT</monospace> and <monospace>GraphSAGE+SVM</monospace> are excluded in this comparison due to computation time constraints, we can see that the results presented in both Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> are consistent to demonstrate <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace>&#x02019;s ability in reducing false positives. Therefore, excluding the <monospace>GAT</monospace> and <monospace>GraphSAGE+SVM</monospace> from the comparison with &#x0201c;complete&#x0201d; replacement methods does not affect the conclusion. Besides, by comparing <monospace>2-class KGML-xDTD</monospace> with the vanilla GraphSAGE model (e.g., <monospace>GraphSAGE-link</monospace>), we demonstrate the effectiveness of the random forest model over a neural network classifier in this task. The comparison between <monospace>KGML-xDTD w/o NAE</monospace> and <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> shows that the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> benefits from the use of node attribute embeddings for drug repurposing prediction while the comparison with <monospace>2-class KGML-xDTD</monospace> indicates the effectiveness of using negative sampling to generate &#x0201c;unknown&#x0201d; drug&#x02013;disease pairs for model training. With the &#x0201c;unknown&#x0201d; drug&#x02013;disease pairs, the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model achieves significant improvement in ranking-based metrics, which is essential when applying to real-world drug repurposing because it can reduce the false positives.</p><fig position="float" id="fig3"><label>Figure 3:</label><caption><p>The performance comparison of DRP between <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> and different baseline models (<monospace>GAT</monospace> and <monospace>GraphSAGE+SVM</monospace> are excluded due to computation time constraints) based on test set using 3 &#x0201c;complete&#x0201d; replacement methods (i.e., &#x0201c;drug rank&#x02013;based replacement,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;disease rank&#x02013;based replacement,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;combined replacement&#x0201d; described in &#x0201c;Drug repurposing prediction evaluation method&#x0201d; section) to generate non-true-positive drug&#x02013;disease candidates for each true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pair for MRR and Hit@K calculation. &#x0201c;Drug rank&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;disease rank,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;combined rank&#x0201d; respectively correspond to the methods of &#x0201c;drug rank&#x02013;based replacement,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;disease rank&#x02013;based replacement,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;combined replacement.&#x0201d;</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="giad057fig3" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2:</label><caption><p>The performance comparison of drug repurposing prediction (DRP) between <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> and different baseline models based on test set (described in &#x0201c;Data split&#x0201d; section). The top panel shows the performance of state-of-the-art (SOTA) baseline models; the middle panel shows the performance of variants of the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model framework; the bottom panel shows the performance of <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model framework</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accuracy</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Macro F1 score</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MRR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hit@1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hit@3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hit@5</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TransE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.708</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.708</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.301 (&#x000b1;0.005)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.134 (&#x000b1;0.007)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.327 (&#x000b1;0.009)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.482 (&#x000b1;0.007)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TransR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.858</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.855</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.329 (&#x000b1;0.006)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.150 (&#x000b1;0.009)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.378 (&#x000b1;0.008)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.542 (&#x000b1;0.005)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RotatE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.704</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.704</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.281 (&#x000b1;0.007)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098 (&#x000b1;0.008)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.314 (&#x000b1;0.007)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.497 (&#x000b1;0.009)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DistMult</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.555</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.495</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.182 (&#x000b1;0.004)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042 (&#x000b1;0.002)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.157 (&#x000b1;0.010)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.292 (&#x000b1;0.010)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ComplEx</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.624</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.460</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.138 (&#x000b1;0.004)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026 (&#x000b1;0.004)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.106 (&#x000b1;0.007)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.205 (&#x000b1;0.008)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANALOGY</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.594</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.465</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.188 (&#x000b1;0.004)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044 (&#x000b1;0.004)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.165 (&#x000b1;0.009)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.301 (&#x000b1;0.008)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SimplE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.599</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.472</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167 (&#x000b1;0.006)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036 (&#x000b1;0.006)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.140 (&#x000b1;0.008)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.259 (&#x000b1;0.011)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.936</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.934</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002 (&#x000b1;0.000)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (&#x000b1;0.000)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (&#x000b1;0.000)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (&#x000b1;0.000)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GraphSAGE-link</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.919</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.915</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002 (&#x000b1;0.000)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (&#x000b1;0.000)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (&#x000b1;0.000)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (&#x000b1;0.000)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GraphSAGE+logistic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.791</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.784</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002 (&#x000b1;0.000)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (&#x000b1;0.000)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (&#x000b1;0.000)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (&#x000b1;0.000)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GraphSAGE+SVM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.807</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.793</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002 (&#x000b1;0.000)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (&#x000b1;0.000)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (&#x000b1;0.000)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (&#x000b1;0.000)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">KGML-xDTD w/o NAEs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.909 (0.898*)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.891 (0.892*)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.159 (&#x000b1;0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035 (&#x000b1;0.002)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.143 (&#x000b1;0.006)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.262 (&#x000b1;0.008)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-class KGML-xDTD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.929</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.925</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.278 (&#x000b1;0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.183 (&#x000b1;0.006)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.321 (&#x000b1;0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.389 (&#x000b1;0.006)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">KGML-xDTD (ours)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.935 (0.930*)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.923 (0.926*)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.382 (&#x000b1;0.004)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.238 (&#x000b1;0.007)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.425 (&#x000b1;0.006)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.543 (&#x000b1;0.006)</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fn1"><p>The values with * inside the parentheses are the adjusted results by excluding the &#x0201c;unknown&#x0201d; category for a fair comparison.</p></fn><fn id="tbl2fn2"><p>The ranking metrics (e.g., &#x0201c;MRR&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Hit@K&#x0201d;) are calculated as the mean along with standard deviation based on 10 independent sets of non-true-positive drug&#x02013;disease candidates generated by the random drug&#x02013;disease replacement method (i.e., for each true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pair in test set, we use 1,000 random drug&#x02013;disease pairs as non-true-positive drug&#x02013;disease candidates to calculate the rank). See more details in &#x0201c;Drug repurposing prediction evaluation method&#x0201d; section.</p></fn><fn id="tbl2fn3"><p>The abbreviation &#x0201c;w/o NAEs&#x0201d; in the name of model &#x0201c;KGML-xDTD w/o NAEs&#x0201d; represents without using node attribute embeddings.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-3"><title>MOA prediction evaluation</title><p>For MOA prediction, we evaluate how well the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> can identify the DrugMechDB-matched BKG-based MOA paths (described in &#x0201c;MOA prediction evaluation method&#x0201d; section) from a large number of possible paths in the customized BKG by utilizing ranking-based metrics (e.g., MPR, MRR, and Hit@K) and 2 specific case studies.</p><p>There are few machine learning models designed for the task of identifying biologically meaningful paths from biomedical knowledge graphs for explaining drug repurposing. Although the UKGE [<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], GrEDeL [<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], and Polo [<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] models (all mentioned in&#x000a0;&#x0201c;Introduction&#x0201d;) were proposed and can be used for this goal, they all have certain constraints and cannot be used as baseline models for comparison. The UKGE model cannot be applied to BKGs without weighted edge information (e.g., frequency of relation appeared in literature). The authors of the GrEDeL model do not provide the code to implement this model. The Polo model cannot be trained within a reasonable time (e.g., within 2 weeks) on a massive and complex BKG (e.g., RTX-KG2) due to its dependence on a computationally inefficient method &#x0201c;DWPC&#x0201d; [<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Therefore, we choose the <monospace>MultiHop</monospace> reinforcement learning model [<xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] as a baseline model since it uses a similar LSTM model framework as the GrEDel model and allows using a self-defined reward-shaping strategy in its reward function as what we do in the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model (i.e., we can use the same reward strategy described in &#x0201c;Adversarial actor&#x02013;critic reinforcement learning&#x0201d; section). Furthermore, we also compare with an ablated version of <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> (i.e., <monospace>KGML-xDTD w/o DP</monospace>, which does not take advantage of the demonstration paths by setting &#x003b1;<sub><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></sub> and &#x003b1;<sub><italic toggle="yes">m</italic></sub> in Function <xref rid="equ9" ref-type="disp-formula">9</xref> as 0) as another baseline model to show the importance of proposed demonstration paths.</p><p>We compare the MOA prediction performance between the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model framework and different baseline models in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. Although all the models use the same terminal reward function from the environment (i.e., the drug repurposing prediction module of <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace>), the MOA prediction module of <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> achieves significantly better performance in identifying DrugMechDB-matched BKG-based MOA paths than the other 2 baselines across all ranking-based metrics. Comparison between the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> with and without demonstration paths (i.e., <monospace>KGML-xDTD w/o DP</monospace>) further illustrates the great effectiveness of using proposed demonstration paths to guide the path-finding process. Due to the massive searching space and sparse rewards, the RL agent often fails to find biologically reasonable BKG-based MOA paths out of many possible choices, while our model <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace>, with the intermediate guidance provided by the demonstration path, is able to identify those biologically reasonable choices with a much higher probability. Moreover, comparing <monospace>KGML-xDTD w/o DP</monospace> and <monospace>MultiHop</monospace> reveals that the actor&#x02013;critic model structure performs similarly to LSTM. However, incorporating the proposed demonstration paths can significantly enhance the effectiveness of the actor&#x02013;critic model structure over LSTM for this task.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table 3:</label><caption><p>The performance comparison of MOA prediction between <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> and different baseline models (e.g., <monospace>MultiHop</monospace> and <monospace>KGML-xDTD w/o DP</monospace>) based on the test set (described in &#x0201c;Data split&#x0201d; section). The metrics in this table are calculated using path scores and all non-DrugMechDB-matched 3-hop paths between drug and disease as &#x0201c;negative&#x0201d; paths for each true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pair (see more details in &#x0201c;MOA prediction evaluation method&#x0201d; section)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MRR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hit@1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hit@10</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hit@50</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hit@100</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hit@500</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MultiHop</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.400%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.118</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.345</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">KGML-xDTD w/o DP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.965%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.160</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.403</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">KGML-xDTD (ours)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>94.696%</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.109</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.059</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.193</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.496</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.613</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.849</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl3fn1"><p>The abbreviation &#x0201c;w/o DP&#x0201d; in the name of model &#x0201c;KKGML-xDTD w/o DP&#x0201d; represents &#x0201c;without using demonstration paths.&#x0201d;</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To further evaluate the performance of <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model framework in identifying biologically relevant MOA paths for drug repurposing, we present 2 different case studies to explore the potential repurposed drugs and their potential mechanism for 2 rare genetic diseases: hemophilia B and Huntington&#x02019;s disease.</p><sec id="sec3-3-1"><title>Case 1: Hemophilia B</title><p>Hemophilia B, also known as factor IX deficiency or Christmas disease, is a rare genetic disorder that results in prolonged bleeding in patients. It is caused by mutations in the factor IX (F9) gene, which is located on the X chromosome. Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">4</xref> displays the top 10 drugs/treatments predicted by the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model framework, including both those that are used in the training set (red bolded) and those that are not. Besides those known drugs/treatments used in the training set, the majority of the remaining 7 drugs/treatments on the list are supported by published research and have the potential to treat hemophilia B. For example, the activated human-derived coagulation factor VII (i.e., factor VIIa) or the recombinant activated factor VII (i.e., rFVIIa) is one of the proteins that can cause blood clots as an important part of the blood coagulation regulatory network (as shown in the Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). This protein is used as an effective inhibitor in the treatment of patients with hemophilia B [<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>, <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Thrombin is a key enzyme in the maintenance of normal hemostatic function. It has been reported that using thrombin as a therapeutic strategy can help prevent bleeding in patients with hemophilia [<xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. The use of recombinant factor IX therapy is a recommended treatment option for individuals with hemophilia B [<xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Some examples of recombinant factor IX products include BeneFIX, Rixubis, Ixinity, Alprolix Idelvion, and Rebinyn. These examples demonstrate the potential capability of <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> for drug repurposing in real-world applications.</p><fig position="float" id="fig4"><label>Figure 4:</label><caption><p>Blood coagulation regulatory network with arrows for molecular reactions (black), positive feedback (green), and negative feedback (red).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="giad057fig4" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4"><label>Table 4:</label><caption><p>Top 10 predicted drugs/treatments for hemophilia B (note that the red bolded drugs are used in the training set)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug/Treatment</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prob.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Publications</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Eptacog Alfa (rFVIIa)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.833</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>, <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Nonacog Alfa (rFIX)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.803</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Viral vector</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.780</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factor VIIa</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.748</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>, <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recombinant FVIIa (rFVIIa)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.724</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>, <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thrombin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.709</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factor IX</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.708</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epicriptine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.702</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperbaric oxygen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.660</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triamcinolone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.649</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>To further assess the biological explanations of the predicted 3-hop BKG-based MOA paths for the treatment of hemophilia B, we have used the curated DrugMechDB-based MOA paths, which are not used in the model training process. DrugMechDB contains relevant MOA paths of hemophilia B treatment only for Eptacog Alfa and Nonacog Alfa. We use the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model to predict the top 10 potential 3-hop BKG-based MOA paths for these 2 drugs and compare them with the curated DugMechDB-based MOA paths in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> (for visualization purpose, we only display the top 5 predicted paths along with any available DrugMechDB-matched BKG-based paths in the top 10 predicted paths). The corresponding biological entities between the predicted paths and the curated DrugMechDB-based paths are highlighted in red. Although the predicted paths cannot exactly match the DrugMechDB-based MOA paths due to the limited path length and some missing semantic relationships in the customized biomedical knowledge graph, key biological entities (such as coagulation factor VII, coagulation factor X, and coagulation factor IX) that are important for the treatment of hemophilia B are present in the predicted paths. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, the treatment of hemophilia B involves a complex molecular network of blood coagulation, and many of the coagulation factors (such as factor VII, factor III, factor II, factor VIII, factor IX, and factor X) present in the predicted paths are also part of this molecular network. In <xref rid="sup11" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Section&#x000a0;S6</xref>, we also utilize the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model framework to predict the top 10 three-hop BKG-based paths, which can serve as biological explanations of the predicted &#x0201c;treats&#x0201d; relationship between factor VIIa and hemophilia B (shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). This particular drug/treatment&#x02013;disease pair is not included in the training set and thus can be used to indicate how <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace>&#x02019;s MOA path predictions can contribute to the explanation of the predicted drug repurposing results. The predicted paths show molecular details akin to those in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> for treating hemophilia B. As a result, the predicted paths by <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model framework can help identify key molecules in the real drug action regulatory network, thereby aiding in explaining drug repurposing to some extent.</p><fig position="float" id="fig5"><label>Figure 5:</label><caption><p>Comparison between the top 5 predicted 3-hop paths (including any available DrugMechDB-matched BKG-based paths in the top 10 predicted paths, highlighted in red) and the curated DrugMechDB-based MOA paths for Eptacog Alfa and Nonacog Alfa. Note that the RTX-KG2 paths and DrugMechDB paths might use different synonyms for the same biological concept. For better visualization and illustration, we utilize consistent entity synonyms between the predicted paths and the curated paths as well as present the predicted paths in a graph structure. (A, C) Graph representation of predicted paths generated by <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> respectively for Eptacog Alfa and Nonacog Alfa. (B, D) Human-curated DrugMechDB MOA paths.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="giad057fig5" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-3-2"><title>Case 2: Huntington&#x02019;s disease</title><p>Huntington&#x02019;s disease (HD) is a rare neurogenetic disorder that typically occurs in midlife with symptoms of depression, uncontrolled movements, and cognitive decline. While there is currently no drug/treatment that can alter the course of HD, some drugs/treatments can be useful for the treatment of its symptoms in abnormal movements (e.g., chorea) and psychiatric phenotypes. We show 10 drugs/treatments with the highest predicted probability by the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model framework after manual processing in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">5</xref>. This processing involves excluding the chemotherapeutic drugs from the predicted drug candidate list due to their potential risk of cytotoxicity to normal cells (which could lead to false positives for drug repurposing of noncancer diseases [<xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>, <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]), and only presenting the top 5 results in the training set and top 5 from the test or validation set. From this table, it can be observed that many of the top-ranked predicted drugs have been supported by publications as potential treatments for the symptoms of HD. Since there is currently no effective treatment for HD, DrugMechDB does not have a corresponding MOA path for comparison. To analyze the predicted paths by the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model framework for the predicted nonchemotherapeutic drugs/treatments that are not included in the training set (shown in regular text in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">5</xref>), we present their top 5 predicted paths in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>. From these predicted paths, we can see that most of them are biologically relevant. For example, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6A</xref> shows that risperidone is predicted to be useful for the treatment of HD by decreasing the activity of the genes associated with the 5-hydroxytryptamine receptor (e.g., HTR1A, HTR2A, HTR2C, HTR7) and dopamine receptor (e.g., DRD2), which have been proven to be involved in the pathogenesis of depressive disorders [<xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>, <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. The presence of depressive symptoms is a significant characteristic of HD [<xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Entinostat is predicted to have the potential to alleviate the symptoms of HD by inhibiting the functions of histone deacetylase genes such as HDAC1 and HDAC6 (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6B</xref>), and one of the predicted 3-hop BKG-based MOA paths (&#x0201c;Entinostat&#x0201d; &#x02192; &#x0201c;decreases activity of&#x0201d; &#x02192; &#x0201c;HDAC1 gene&#x0201d; &#x02192; &#x0201c;interacts with&#x0201d; &#x02192; &#x0201c;Histone H4&#x0201d; &#x02192; &#x0201c;gene associated with condition&#x0201d; &#x02192; &#x0201c;Huntington&#x02019;s disease&#x0201d;) is supported by the previous research [<xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>, <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Primaquine is predicted to act on the IKBKG gene to potentially play a therapeutic role in neurodegenerative disease (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6C</xref>), reported in [<xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. According to the predicted BKG-based MOA paths (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6D</xref>), isradipine may have a potential therapeutic effect for HD by mainly regulating the genes of the calcium voltage-gated channel, including CACNA1C and CACNB2. These genes may be associated with the symptoms of HD, such as depression and dementia [<xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. Lastly, amifampridine is predicted to regulate the genes of the potassium voltage-gated channel (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6E</xref>), which are potentially associated with HD [<xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. All these examples indicate that the predicted BKG-based MOA paths can explain the mechanism of repurposed drugs to some extent.</p><fig position="float" id="fig6"><label>Figure 6:</label><caption><p>Top 5 predicted 3-hop BKG-based MOA paths (integrated into a graph for better visualization) for top 5 nonchemotherapeutic predicted drugs/treatments that are not included in the training set for Huntington&#x02019;s disease.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="giad057fig6" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl5"><label>Table 5:</label><caption><p>Top 5 predicted drugs/treatments used in the training set (highlighted in red bold) and the top 5 nonchemotherapeutic predicted drugs/treatments that are not in the training set for Huntington&#x02019;s disease</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug/Treatment</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prob.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Publications</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Pimozide</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.939</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>, <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Therapeutic agent</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.939</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Olanzapine</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.938</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>, <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Riluzole</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.935</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Antipsychotic agent</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.932</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risperidone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.893</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>, <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Entinostat</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.888</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primaquine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.887</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isradipine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.884</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amifampridine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.882</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Drug Class Analysis</title><p>The drug repurposing prediction of the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model does not leverage any information regarding drug similarity such as drug classes, SMILES, drug side effects, and drug-related gene profiles/sequences, and we find that the distribution of drug classes in true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pairs is similar between the training and test sets (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). In this section, we examine whether our model can only predict the drugs with the drug classes that it has seen in the training set.</p><fig position="float" id="fig7"><label>Figure 7:</label><caption><p>Comparison of the drug class distribution in true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pairs between the training set and test set. The drug class of each drug/chemical in these pairs is determined based on the FDA &#x0201c;Established Pharmacologic Class&#x0201d; (EPC) accessed via <ext-link xlink:href="https://mychem.info/" ext-link-type="uri">MyChem.info</ext-link> APIs. There are 2,238 drug classes represented in the true-positive drug&#x02013;disease pairs in the training set and 718 drug classes in the test set. For visualization purposes, we only show the top 10 drug classes in each set and the rest is classified into the &#x0201c;Others&#x0201d; class.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="giad057fig7" position="float"/></fig><p>To do this, we use the <ext-link xlink:href="https://mychem.info/" ext-link-type="uri">MyChem.info</ext-link> APIs [<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] to retrieve the FDA&#x02019;s &#x0201c;Established Pharmacologic Class&#x0201d; (EPC) information for chemicals/drugs using their synonym identifiers. For the FDA-unapproved chemical/drug without such EPC information, we consider it as as a single class. We first utilize the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model to predict the top 100 chemicals/drugs for each of the 1,140 diseases in the test set (described in &#x0201c;Data split&#x0201d; section) after excluding the drug&#x02013;disease pairs presented in the training set. Then we count the number of drug classes among these 100 predicted drugs that are not seen in the training set for each disease. Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref> shows the distribution of unseen drug classes in the top 100 predicted nontrain drugs across the 1,140 diseases in the test set. We can see that each disease has at least 70 different drug classes among the top 100 predicted drugs, indicating that the predictive power of the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model is derived from the node attribute information and knowledge graph topology structure rather than any drug class information.</p><fig position="float" id="fig8"><label>Figure 8:</label><caption><p>Distribution of unseen drug classes in the top 100 predicted nontrain drugs across the 1,140 diseases in the test set.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="giad057fig8" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec5"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this work, we propose <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace>, a 2-module, knowledge graph&#x02013;based machine learning framework that not only predicts the treatment probabilities between drugs/compounds and diseases but also provides biological explanations for these predictions through the predicted paths in a massive biomedical knowledge graph with comprehensive biomedical data sources as potential mechanisms of action. This framework can assist medical researchers in quickly identifying the potential drug/compound&#x02013;disease pairs that might have a treatment relationship, which can accelerate the process of drug discovery for emerging diseases. Additionally, by leveraging the KG-based MOA paths predicted by the framework, medical professionals (e.g., doctors and licensed medical practitioners) can straightforwardly assess the accuracy of the predictions, which can help to reduce false positives that may be produced by the &#x0201c;black-box&#x0201d; operation of traditional machine learning models.</p><p>Although previous research [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] has applied a variety of models to the task of drug repurposing using BKGs, these approaches are implemented in the small-scale BKGs, and many do not scale to larger and more complex graphs as biotechnology advances and the volume of data in biomedical databases increases. In our comparison with state-of-the-art KG-based models for drug repurposing, we find that the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model had higher accuracy with lower false positives when applied to a massive and complex biomedical knowledge graph <italic toggle="yes">RTX-KG2c</italic>. By evaluating the predicted paths with DrugMechDB and 2 case studies, we show that the model can capture some key biological entities involved in real drug action regulatory networks.</p><p>It is widely acknowledged that drug repurposing is one of the most challenging problems in biomedicine, and current artificial intelligence (AI) techniques are still in the early stages of addressing it. Many other AI models, such as those based on chemical structure, drug&#x02013;target interactions, and drug perturbations of gene expression, are developed for solving this goal. They may offer more accurate predictions but also have limitations in terms of cost and the availability of samples for specific diseases. BKG-based machine learning models, such as the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model, offer a cost- and time-efficient alternative due to the large volume of biomedical knowledge stored in public databases and publications. The <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model framework is not intended to replace or beat these models but rather provides a complementary approach that leverages emerging knowledge graphs for drug repurposing.</p><p>Future work to further enhance the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model framework might include extending the predicted paths for more specific explanations and considering the negative drug&#x02013;disease pairs so that the model can explain why certain drugs are harmful to diseases.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Availability of Source Code and Requirements</title><p>Project name: KGML-xDTD</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Project homepage: <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/chunyuma/KGML-xDTD" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/chunyuma/KGML-xDTD</ext-link></p></list-item><list-item><p>Operating system(s): Linux (Ubuntu)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Resource usage in training step: A Linux (Ubuntu) system with at least 8 CPU cores, 800 GB of VRAM, and a 48 GB GPU card (48 GB Quadro RTX 8000 GPU card used in our training)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Resource usage in inference step: A Linux (Ubuntu) system with at least 8 CPU cores and 50 GB of VRAM. The GPU card is not necessary, but if used, the GPU card needs at least 24 GB VRAM (48 GB Quadro RTX 8000 GPU card used in our inference)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Time requirement: Based on our hardware performance and parameter settings (please see the scripts on GitHub), the training step takes approximately 2 weeks while the inference step takes approximately 25.42 seconds for 1 drug&#x02013;disease pair with 3,320 potential paths. These time estimates may vary depending on the hardware performance, parameter settings, and the number of potential paths of a given drug&#x02013;disease pair.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Programming language: Shell Script (Bash) with Python 3.8.12</p></list-item><list-item><p>Other requirements: Python 3.8.12 with GPU/CPU support (GraphSAGE training needs Python 2.7), neo4j-community 3.5.26, miniconda 4.8.2 (please see more requirements in the yaml files under &#x0201c;envs&#x0201d; folder on Github repository)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Licenses: MIT license, DrugBank academic license, Apache 2.0 license, UMLS Metathesaurus license, CC-BY 4.0 license</p></list-item><list-item><p>Research Resource Identifier (#RRID): SCR_023678</p></list-item></list></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>giad057_GIGA-D-23-00026_Original_Submission</label><media xlink:href="giad057_giga-d-23-00026_original_submission.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup2" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>giad057_GIGA-D-23-00026_Revision_1</label><media xlink:href="giad057_giga-d-23-00026_revision_1.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup3" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>giad057_GIGA-D-23-00026_Revision_2</label><media xlink:href="giad057_giga-d-23-00026_revision_2.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup4" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>giad057_GIGA-D-23-00026_Revision_3</label><media xlink:href="giad057_giga-d-23-00026_revision_3.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup5" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>giad057_Response_to_Reviewer_Comments_Original_Submission</label><media xlink:href="giad057_response_to_reviewer_comments_original_submission.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup6" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>giad057_Response_to_Reviewer_Comments_Revision_1</label><media xlink:href="giad057_response_to_reviewer_comments_revision_1.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup7" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>giad057_Response_to_Reviewer_Comments_Revision_2</label><media xlink:href="giad057_response_to_reviewer_comments_revision_2.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup8" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>giad057_Reviewer_1_Report_Original_Submission</label><caption><p>Yuansheng Liu -- 3/3/2023 Reviewed</p></caption><media xlink:href="giad057_reviewer_1_report_original_submission.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup9" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>giad057_Reviewer_1_Report_Revision_1</label><caption><p>Yuansheng Liu -- 5/18/2023 Reviewed</p></caption><media xlink:href="giad057_reviewer_1_report_revision_1.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup10" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>giad057_Reviewer_2_Report_Original_Submission</label><caption><p>Michel Dumontier -- 4/2/2023 Reviewed</p></caption><media xlink:href="giad057_reviewer_2_report_original_submission.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup11" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>giad057_Supplemental_Files</label><media xlink:href="giad057_supplemental_files.zip"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="ack1"><title>Acknowledgement</title><p>The authors thank Dr. Jared Roach from the Institute for Systems Biology for his assistance in manually evaluating the biological realism of the model-predicted paths in a double-blind manner, and also the RTX-KG2 team (Stephen Ramsey, Amy Glen, E. C. Wood, Lili Acevedo) for their guidance in building RTX-KG2 and in resolving any issues that arose.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec7"><title>Data Availability</title><p>The data sets supporting the results of this article are publicly available in the Zenodo repository [<xref rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. All supporting data and materials are available in the <italic toggle="yes">GigaScience</italic> GigaDB database [<xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>].</p><p>
<bold>Molecular data provider</bold>: A knowledge-centric data provider for systems chemical biology, as part of the NCATS Biomedical Data Translator (&#x0201c;Translator&#x0201d;). See more in <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/NCATSTranslator/Translator-All/wiki/Molecular-Data-Provider" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/NCATSTranslator/Translator-All/wiki/Molecular-Data-Provider</ext-link> [<xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="h1content1690371597368"><title>Additional Files</title><p>
<bold>Supplementary Section&#x000a0;S1</bold>. Biomedical Knowledge Graph RTX-KG2c Preprocessing.</p><p>
<bold>Supplementary Section&#x000a0;S2</bold>. Summary of Data Resources Used by MyChem Data.</p><p>
<bold>Supplementary Section&#x000a0;S3</bold>. Implementation Details of <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> Model Framework.</p><p>
<bold>Supplementary Section&#x000a0;S4</bold>. Implementation Details of Demonstration Path Extraction.</p><p>
<bold>Supplementary Section&#x000a0;S5</bold>. Implementation Details of Baseline Models.</p><p>
<bold>Supplementary Section&#x000a0;S6</bold>. Top 10 KGML-xDTD&#x02019;s Predicted Paths Serving as Biological Explanations for the Predicted &#x0201c;Treats&#x0201d; Relationship between Factor VIIa and Hemophilia B.</p><p>
<bold>Supplementary Table S1</bold>. Eleven data resources used by MyChem data.</p><p>
<bold>Supplementary Table S2</bold>. Hyperparameters used for baseline models.</p><p>
<bold>Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;S1</bold>. Top 10 predicted 3-hop paths (integrated into a graph for better visualization) generated by the <monospace>KGML-xDTD</monospace> model framework serve as biological explanations of the predicted &#x0201c;treats&#x0201d; relationship between factor VIIa and hemophilia B. The path highlighted with red is the one in which all nodes can align with the key molecules in the real drug action regulatory network shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> in the main text.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Abbreviations</title><p>ACC: accuracy; ADAC: adversarial actor&#x02013;critic; BKG: biomedical knowledge graph; DWPC: degree-weighted path count; EHR: electronic health record; FDA: Food and Drug Administration; GRL: graph reinforcement learning; GWAS: Genome-wide association studies; KG: knowledge graph; LSTM: long short-term memory; Macro-F1: macro F1 score; MDP: Markov decision process; MeSH: Medical Subject Heading; MOA: mechanism of action; MPR: mean percentile rank; MSE: mean square error; NAE: node attribute embedding; NGD: normalized Google distance; NLP: Natural Language Processing; PCA: principal components analysis; RF: random forest; RL: reinforcement learning; RNN: recurrent neural network; RTX-KG2: Reasoning Tool X Knowledge Graph 2; RTX-KG2c: canonicalized version of the Reasoning Tool X Knowledge Graph 2; SemMedDB: Semantic MEDLINE Database; SMILES: Simplified Molecular Input Line Entry System; SVM: support vector machine; VHA: Veterans Health Administration.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="h1content1690371637684"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="h1content1690371643883"><title>Funding</title><p>Research reported in this publication was supported by the National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences (NCATS) of the National Institutes of Health (NIH) under award numbers OT2-TR003428-01S3, OT2-TR003428-01S2, and OT2-TR003428-01; National Library of Medicine of the NIH under award number R01LM01372201; and the National Science Foundation under award number CAREER-1841569.</p></sec><sec id="h1content1690371691119"><title>Authors&#x02019; Contributions</title><p>D.K. and C.M. conceived the project and supervised the study. C.M. processed the raw data and designed model framework. C.M. and Z.Z. wrote code and trained models. C.M., Z.Z., and D.K. drafted the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Berdigaliyev</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aljofan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>An overview of drug discovery and development</article-title>. <source>Future Med Chem</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>939</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32270704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>MT.</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Thalidomide embryopathy: a model for the study of congenital incomitant horizontal strabismus</article-title>. <source>Trans Am Ophthalmol Soc</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>623</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1808819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Verheul</surname>
<given-names>HMW</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Panigrahy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Combination oral antiangiogenic therapy with thalidomide and sulindac inhibits tumour growth in rabbits</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>114</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10408702</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Singhal</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Desikan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Antitumor activity of thalidomide in refractory multiple myeloma</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>341</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>1565</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10564685</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kairys</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baranauskiene</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kazlauskiene</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Binding affinity in drug design: experimental and computational techniques</article-title>. <source>Expert Opin Drug Discov</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>755</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31146609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Aulner</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Danckaert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ihm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Next-generation phenotypic screening in early drug discovery for infectious diseases</article-title>. <source>Trends Parasitol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>559</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31176583</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Rusz</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>&#x00150;sz</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>J&#x000ee;tc&#x001ce;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Off-label medication: from a simple concept to complex practical aspects</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>10447</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34639747</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Swamidass</surname>
<given-names>SJ.</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mining small-molecule screens to repurpose drugs</article-title>. <source>Brief Bioinform</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21715466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sanseau</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Use of genome-wide association studies for drug repositioning</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22491277</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Bonner</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>A review of biomedical datasets relating to drug discovery: a knowledge graph perspective</article-title>. <source>Brief Bioinform</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>bbac404</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36151740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wishart</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feunang</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>DrugBank 5.0: a major update to the DrugBank database for 2018</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>):<fpage>gkx1037</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Gaulton</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bellis</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bento</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>ChEMBL: a large-scale bioactivity database for drug discovery</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>):<fpage>D1100</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21948594</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wishart</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feunang</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marcu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>HMDB 4.0: the human metabolome database for 2018</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>):<fpage>gkx1089</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kanza</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Graham&#x000a0;Frey</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Semantic technologies in drug discovery</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Wolkenhauer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name></person-group>, ed. <source>Systems Medicine</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>; <year>2021</year>:<fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Himmelstein</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lizee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hessler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Systematic integration of biomedical knowledge prioritizes drugs for repurposing</article-title>. <source>eLife</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e26726</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28936969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Walsh</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nov&#x000e1;&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>BioKG: a knowledge graph for relational learning on biological data</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of the 29th ACM International Conference on Information &#x00026; Knowledge Management,&#x000a0;Virtual Event, Ireland</source>. <fpage>p. 3173</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3180</lpage>.. <publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ACM</publisher-name>, <year>2020</year>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/3340531.3412776</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Biomedical discovery through the integrative biomed-ical knowledge hub (iBKH)</article-title>. <source>iScience</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>106460</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37020958</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Percha</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>RB.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>A global network of biomedical relationships derived from text</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>2614</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2624</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29490008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hristovski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schutte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Drug repurposing for COVID-19 via knowledge graph completion</article-title>. <source>J Biomed Inform</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>103696</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33571675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>COVID-19 literature knowledge graph construction and drug repurposing report generation</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of the 2021 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics: Human Language Technologies: Demonstrations</source>. <fpage>p.&#x000a0;66</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>.. <publisher-name>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher-name>, <year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>KGHC: a knowledge graph for hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Inform Decis</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>suppl 3</issue>):<fpage>135</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Santos</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cola&#x000e7;o</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>A knowledge graph to interpret clinical proteomics data</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>692</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>702</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35102292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wood</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Glen</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kvarfordt</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>RTX-KG2: a system for building a semantically standardized knowledge graph for translational biomedicine</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinform</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>400</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Ioannidis</surname>
<given-names>VN</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karypis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Few-shot link prediction via graph neural networks for Covid-19 drug-repurposing</article-title>. <year>2020</year>. &#x0200b;&#x0200b;<comment>arXiv:2007.10261. </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2007.10261</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Bordes</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Usunier</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia-Duran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>, <article-title>Translating embeddings for modeling multi-relational data</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Burges</surname><given-names>CJC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bottou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Welling</surname>&#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>, eds. <source>Proceedings of the 26th International Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems</source>. <fpage>p. 2787</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2795</lpage>.. <publisher-name>Curran Associates, Inc</publisher-name>, <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<source>RotatE: knowledge graph embedding by relational rotation in complex space</source>. <year>2019</year>. <comment>arXiv:1902.10197. </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.48550/arXiv.1902.10197</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yih</surname><given-names>Wt</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<source>Embedding entities and relations for learning and inference in knowledge bases</source>. <year>2014</year>. <comment>arXiv:1412.6575. </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.48550/arXiv.1412.6575</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Trouillon</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Welbl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riedel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<source>Complex embeddings for simple link prediction</source>. <year>2016</year>. <comment>arXiv:1606.06357. </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.48550/arXiv.1606.06357</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Structure-augmented text representation learning for efficient knowledge graph completion</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of the Web Conference 2021</source>. <fpage>p. 1737</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1748</lpage>.. <publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Association for Computing Machinery</publisher-name>, <year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sosa</surname>
<given-names>DN</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Derry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>A literature-based knowledge graph embedding method for identifying drug repurposing opportunities in rare diseases. Pacific Symp Biocomputing</article-title>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>463</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Embedding uncertain knowledge graphs</article-title>. <source>Proc AAAI Conf Artif Intell</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>3363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>GrEDeL: a knowledge graph embedding based method for drug discovery from biomedical literatures</article-title>. <source>IEEE Access</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>8404</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kilicoglu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosemblat</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fiszman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Broad-coverage biomedical relation extraction with SemRep</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinform</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>188</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>
<source>Reinforcement learning applications</source>. <year>2019</year>. <comment>arXiv:1908.06973. </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.48550/arXiv.1908.06973</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>RLPath: a knowledge graph link prediction method using reinforcement learning based attentive relation path searching and representation learning</article-title>. <source>Appl Intell</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>4715</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Adversarial attacks on graph neural networks via node injections: a hierarchical reinforcement learning approach</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of The Web Conference 2020</source>. <fpage>p.&#x000a0;673</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>683</lpage>.. <publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Association for Computing Machinery</publisher-name>, <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Multi-hop knowledge graph reasoning based on hyperbolic knowledge graph embedding and reinforcement learning</article-title>. In: <source>The 10th International Joint Conference on Knowledge Graphs</source>. <fpage>p. 1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.. <publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Association for Computing Machinery</publisher-name>, <year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hildebrandt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Joblin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Neural multi-hop reasoning with logical rules on biomedical knowledge graphs</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Verborgh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hose</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paulheim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>eds. <source>The Semantic Web</source>. <publisher-loc>Cham,&#x000a0;Switzerland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>; <year>2021</year>:<fpage>375</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Womack</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>McClelland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koslicki</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Leveraging distributed biomedical knowledge sources to discover novel uses for known drugs</article-title>. <source>bioRxiv</source>. <year>2019</year>:<fpage>765305</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/765305</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Hamilton</surname>
<given-names>WL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leskovec</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Inductive representation learning on large graphs</article-title>. <year>2017</year>. <comment>arXiv:1706.02216. </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.48550/arXiv.1706.02216</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Leveraging demonstrations for reinforcement recommendation reasoning over knowledge graphs</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of the 43rd International ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval</source>. <fpage>p.&#x000a0;239</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>248</lpage>.. <publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Association for Computing Machinery</publisher-name>, <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Mayers</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steinecke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>AI.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Database of mechanism of action paths for selected drug-disease indications</article-title>. <source>Zenodo</source>. <year>2020</year>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.3708278</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Mayers</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steinecke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Design and application of a knowledge network for automatic prioritization of drug mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>btac205</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Degtyarenko</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matos</surname><given-names>Pd</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ennis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>ChEBI: a database and ontology for chemical entities of biological interest</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>Database issue</issue>):<fpage>D344</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17932057</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Consortium</surname>
<given-names>TBDT.</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Toward a universal biomedical data translator</article-title>. <source>Clin Transl Sci</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>86</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30412337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Translator Consortium</collab>
</person-group>. <article-title>The Biomedical Data Translator Program: conception, culture, and community</article-title>. <source>Clin Transl Sci</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30412340</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Unni</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moxon</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Biolink model: a universal schema for knowledge graphs in clinical, biomedical, and translational science</article-title>. <source>Clin Transl Sci</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1848</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1855</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36125173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Xin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Afrasiabi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lelong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Cross-linking BioThings APIs through JSON-LD to facilitate knowledge exploration</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinform</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>30</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Xin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Afrasiabi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>High-performance web services for querying gene and variant annotation</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>91</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27154141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kilicoglu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fiszman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>SemMedDB: a PubMed-scale repository of biomedical semantic predications</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>3158</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23044550</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elkin</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenbloom</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>VA National Drug File Reference Terminology: a cross-institutional content coverage study</article-title>. <source>Stud Heal Tech Inform</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>107</volume>(<issue>Pt 1</issue>):<fpage>477</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>CJ.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>A standard database for drug repositioning</article-title>. <source>Sci Data</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>170029</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28291243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Cilibrasi</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vitanyi</surname><given-names>PMB.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>The Google similarity distance</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans Knowl Data Eng</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>370</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Gu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tinn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Domain-specific language model pretraining for biomedical natural language processing</article-title>. <source>ACM Trans Comput Healthc</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Mikolov</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sutskever</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>, <article-title>Distributed representations of words and phrases and their compositionality</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of the 26th International Conference on Neural Information Processing System, vol. 2</source>, p. <fpage>3111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3119</lpage>.. <publisher-loc>Red Hook, NY, United States</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Curran Associates Inc</publisher-name>, <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Lillicrap</surname>
<given-names>TP</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pritzel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Continuous control with deep reinforcement learning</article-title>. <year>2015</year>. <comment>arXiv:1509.02971. </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.48550/arXiv.1509.02971</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sutton</surname>
<given-names>RS.</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Learning to predict by the methods of temporal differences</article-title>. <source>Mach Learn 19</source>. <year>88</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>RJ.</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Simple statistical gradient-following algorithms for connectionist reinforcement learning</article-title>. <source>Mach Learn</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3&#x02013;4</issue>):<fpage>229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Pomerleau</surname>
<given-names>DA.</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Efficient training of artificial neural networks for autonomous navigation</article-title>. <source>Neural Comput</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>88</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31141866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Hsieh</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Drug repurposing for COVID-19 using graph neural network and harmonizing multiple evidence</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>23179</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34848761</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Learning entity and relation embeddings for knowledge graph completion</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence, vol. 29(1)</source>. <year>2015</year>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1609/aaai.v29i1.9491</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Analogical inference for multi-relational embeddings</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of the 34th International Conference on Machine Learning, vol. 70</source>. <fpage>p.&#x000a0;2168</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2178</lpage>.. <publisher-loc>Sydney, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>PMLR</publisher-name>, <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kazemi</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>SimplE embedding for link prediction in knowledge graphs</article-title>. <source>Adv Neural Inform Process Syst</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>4284</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Veli&#x0010d;kovi&#x00107;</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cucurull</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Casanova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Graph attention networks</article-title>. <year>2017</year>. <comment>arXiv:1710.10903. </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.48550/arXiv.1710.10903</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Glorot</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bengio</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Understanding the difficulty of training deep feedforward neural networks</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Teh</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Titterington</surname><given-names>DM.</given-names></string-name></person-group>eds. <source>AISTATS, vol. 9 of JMLR Proceedings.</source><year>2010</year>:<fpage>249</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>256</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>XV</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Socher</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Multi-hop knowledge graph reasoning with reward shaping</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of the 2018 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing</source>. <fpage>p.&#x000a0;3243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3253</lpage>.. <publisher-loc>Brussels, Belgium</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher-name>, <year>2018</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Croom</surname>
<given-names>KF</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>PL.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Recombinant factor VIIa (eptacog alfa): a review of its use in congenital hemophilia with inhibitors, acquired hemophilia, and other congenital bleeding disorders</article-title>. <source>BioDrugs</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18345709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Minno</surname>
<given-names>GD.</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Eptacog alfa activated: a recombinant product to treat rare congenital bleeding disorders</article-title>. <source>Blood Rev</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>S26</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26073366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Rendo</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Nonacog alfa: an analysis of safety data from six prospective clinical studies in different patient populations with haemophilia B treated with different therapeutic modalities</article-title>. <source>Blood Coagul Fibrinolysis</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>912</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26196195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Driessche</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Collen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chuah</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Viral vector-mediated gene therapy for hemophilia</article-title>. <source>Curr Gene Ther</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>301</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12109144</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monroe</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>White</surname><given-names>GC.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>The use of recombinant factor VIIa in the treatment of bleeding disorders</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>3858</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15328151</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Negrier</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>The central role of thrombin in bleeding disorders</article-title>. <source>Blood Rev</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>100582</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31164248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Goodeve</surname>
<given-names>AC.</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Hemophilia B: molecular pathogenesis and mutation analysis</article-title>. <source>J Thromb Haemost</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1184</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25851415</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sourimant</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Plemper</surname><given-names>RK.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Progress and pitfalls of a year of drug repurposing screens against COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Virol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34218010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Gysi</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>do&#x000a0;Valle</surname><given-names>&#x000cd;</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zitnik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Network medicine framework for identifying drug-repurposing opportunities for COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>118</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>e2025581118</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33906951</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Yohn</surname>
<given-names>CN</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gergues</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Samuels</surname><given-names>BA.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>The role of 5-HT receptors in depression</article-title>. <source>Mol Brain</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>28</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28646910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Delva</surname>
<given-names>NC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stanwood</surname><given-names>GD.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Dysregulation of brain dopamine systems in major depressive disorder</article-title>. <source>Exp Biol Med</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>246</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1084</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Coppen</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>RAC.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Current pharmacological approaches to reduce chorea in huntington&#x02019;s disease</article-title>. <source>Drugs</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>77</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27988871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><label>79.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Shukla</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tekwani</surname><given-names>BL.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Histone deacetylases inhibitors in neurodegenerative diseases, neuroprotection and neuronal differentiation</article-title>. <source>Front Pharmacol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>537</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32390854</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><label>80.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>IT</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Valproic acid promotes neuronal differentiation by induction of proneural factors in association with H4 acetylation</article-title>. <source>Neuropharmacology</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>473</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19007798</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><label>81.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>TG.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Role of nuclear factor kappa B (NF-KB) signalling in neurodegenerative diseases: an mechanistic approach</article-title>. <source>Curr Neuropharmacol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>918</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32031074</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><label>82.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Yagami</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kohma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>L-type voltage-dependent calcium channels as therapeutic targets for neurodegenerative diseases</article-title>. <source>Curr Med Chem</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>28</issue>):<fpage>4816</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22834820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><label>83.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Noh</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Transient potassium channels: therapeutic targets for brain disorders</article-title>. <source>Front Cell Neurosci</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>265</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31263403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib84"><label>84.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Arena</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iudice</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Virgili</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Huntington&#x02019;s disease: clinical effects of a short-term treatment with pimozide</article-title>. <source>Adv Biochem Psychopharmacol</source>. <year>1980</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>573</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6447434</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib85"><label>85.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Videnovic</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Treatment of Huntington disease</article-title>. <source>Curr Treat Options Neurol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>424</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23417276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib86"><label>86.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Paleacu</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anca</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Giladi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Olanzapine in Huntington&#x02019;s disease: olanzapine in Huntington&#x02019;s disease</article-title>. <source>Acta Neurol Scand</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>105</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>441</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12027832</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib87"><label>87.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Squitieri</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cannella</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Porcellini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Short-term effects of olanzapine in Huntington disease</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychiatry Neuropsychol Behav Neurol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11234911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib88"><label>88.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Group</surname>
<given-names>HS.</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Dosage effects of riluzole in Huntington&#x02019;s disease: a multicenter placebo-controlled study</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1551</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14663041</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib89"><label>89.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Unti</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mazzucchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palermo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Antipsychotic drugs in Huntington&#x02019;s disease</article-title>. <source>Exp Rev Neurother</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>227</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib90"><label>90.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Duff</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beglinger</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O&#x02019;Rourke</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Risperidone and the treatment of psychiatric, motor, and cognitive symptoms in Huntington&#x02019;s disease</article-title>. <source>Ann Clin Psychiatry</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18297579</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib91"><label>91.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Miranda</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cardozo</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Alterations of calcium channels in a mouse model of Huntington&#x02019;s disease and neuroprotection by blockage of CaV1 channels</article-title>. <source>ASN NEURO</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1759091419856811</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31216184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib92"><label>92.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<source>Relevant datasets and software used for paper &#x0201c;KGML-xDTD: a knowledge graph-based machine learning framework for drug treatment prediction and mechanism description (1.0.0) [Data set]</source>. <source>Zenodo</source>. <year>2023</year>. <comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://zenodo.org/record/7582233" ext-link-type="uri">https://zenodo.org/record/7582233</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib93"><label>93.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Supporting data for &#x0201c;KGML-xDTD: A Knowledge Graph&#x02013;Based Machine Learning Framework for Drug Treatment Prediction and Mechanism Description</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>GigaScience Database</source>. <year>2023</year>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5524/102404</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib94"><label>94.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Molecular Data Provider Team.</collab>
</person-group>
<comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/NCATSTranslator/Translator-All/wiki/Molecular-Data-Provider" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/NCATSTranslator/Translator-All/wiki/Molecular-Data-Provider</ext-link>. Accessed 9 November 2021</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>