<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Gigascience</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Gigascience</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">gigascience</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>GigaScience</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2047-217X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11299106</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39101782</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gigascience/giae047</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">giae047</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Technical Note</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI00960</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI02254</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>MOBFinder: a tool for mobilization typing of plasmid metagenomic fragments based on a language model</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1984-4265</contrib-id><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Tao</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Microbiome Medicine Center, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Zhujiang Hospital, Southern Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou 510280</addr-line>, <country country="CN">China</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7793-2509</contrib-id><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Shufang</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Microbiome Medicine Center, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Zhujiang Hospital, Southern Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou 510280</addr-line>, <country country="CN">China</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2472-8541</contrib-id><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Hongwei</given-names></name><!--hzhou@smu.edu.cn--><aff>
<institution>Microbiome Medicine Center, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Zhujiang Hospital, Southern Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou 510280</addr-line>, <country country="CN">China</country></aff><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0137-4683</contrib-id><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Zhencheng</given-names></name><!--fangzc@smu.edu.cn--><aff>
<institution>Microbiome Medicine Center, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Zhujiang Hospital, Southern Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou 510280</addr-line>, <country country="CN">China</country></aff><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence address. Hongwei Zhou, Microbiome Medicine Center, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Zhujiang Hospital, Southern Medical University, 253 Gongye Middle Avenue, Haizhu District, Guangzhou, Guangdong 510280, China. E-mail: <email>hzhou@smu.edu.cn</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2">Correspondence address. Zhencheng Fang, Microbiome Medicine Center, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Zhujiang Hospital, Southern Medical University, 253 Gongye Middle Avenue, Haizhu District, Guangzhou, Guangdong 510280, China. E-mail: <email>fangzc@smu.edu.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2024-08-05"><day>05</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>05</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>giae047</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of GigaScience.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="giae047.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="abs1"><title>Background</title><p>Mobilization typing (MOB) is a classification scheme for plasmid genomes based on their relaxase gene. The host ranges of plasmids of different MOB categories are diverse, and MOB is crucial for investigating plasmid mobilization, especially the transmission of resistance genes and virulence factors. However, MOB typing of plasmid metagenomic data is challenging due to the highly fragmented characteristics of metagenomic contigs.</p></sec><sec id="abs2"><title>Results</title><p>We developed MOBFinder, an 11-class classifier, for categorizing plasmid fragments into 10 MOB types and a nonmobilizable category. We first performed MOB typing to classify complete plasmid genomes according to relaxase information and then constructed an artificial benchmark dataset of plasmid metagenomic fragments (PMFs) from those complete plasmid genomes whose MOB types are well annotated. Next, based on natural language models, we used word vectors to characterize the PMFs. Several random forest classification models were trained and integrated to predict fragments of different lengths. Evaluating the tool using the benchmark dataset, we found that MOBFinder outperforms previous tools such as MOBscan and MOB-suite, with an overall <italic toggle="yes">accuracy</italic> approximately 59% higher than that of MOB-suite. Moreover, the <italic toggle="yes">balanced accuracy, harmonic mean</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">F1-score</italic> reached up to 99% for some MOB types. When applied to a cohort of patients with type 2 diabetes (T2D), MOBFinder offered insights suggesting that the MOBF type plasmid, which is widely present in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella</italic>, and the MOBQ type plasmid might accelerate antibiotic resistance transmission in patients with T2D.</p></sec><sec id="abs3"><title>Conclusions</title><p>To the best of our knowledge, MOBFinder is the first tool for MOB typing of PMFs. The tool is freely available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/FengTaoSMU/MOBFinder" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/FengTaoSMU/MOBFinder</ext-link>.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>MOB typing</kwd><kwd>language model</kwd><kwd>metagenomic sequencing</kwd><kwd>plasmid</kwd><kwd>random forest</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Key Research and Development Program of China</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100012166</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>2022YFA0806400</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>82102508</award-id><award-id>81925026</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Plasmids are usually small, double-stranded, and circular DNA molecules found within bacterial cells [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Being separate from the bacterial chromosome, plasmids have the ability to replicate independently and can be transferred between bacteria through conjugation [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Bacteria, specifically pathogenic strains, can acquire antibiotic resistance genes or virulence factors via plasmid-mediated horizontal gene transfer, aiding their ability to adapt to various environments [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>Plasmid classification is important for investigating multiple properties of plasmids, such as host range, replication patterns, and mobilization mechanisms [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Many classification schemes have been developed according to the distinct characteristics of plasmids, including taxonomic classification, replicon typing (Rep), incompatibility typing (Inc), mate&#x02013;pair formation typing (MPF), and mobilization typing (MOB). In taxonomic classification, plasmids are categorized based on their host bacteria [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Rep typing classifies plasmids according to genes controlling their replication, known as replication initiation genes [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Inc typing takes advantage of the fact that plasmids with similar replication or partition systems are incompatible within the same cell, categorizing plasmids based on compatibility [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. MPF typing is based on genes encoding the MPF system, which consists of proteins that mediate contact and DNA exchange between donor and recipient cells during conjugation [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Finally, MOB typing classifies plasmids based on the relaxase gene, which is present in all transmissible plasmids [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Plasmids with different relaxase types are categorized as different MOB types, with each possessing a distinct transmission mechanism that determines its taxonomic host range [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. This variation among different MOB types is critical in researching the spread of virulence traits, the emergence of antibiotic resistance, and the adaptation and evolution of bacteria. Moreover, MOB typing has been found to be effective for identifying novel mobilizable plasmids that were previously unassigned to any Rep or Inc types and for investigating the mobilization characteristics of plasmids with similar mobilization systems [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>Recently, many experimental and computational schemes have been devised for plasmid typing, as well as to explore the diversity and functionality of plasmids (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). For example, plasmid taxonomic PCR (PlasTax-PCR) [<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], PCR-based replicon typing (PBRT) [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], and degenerate primer MOB typing (DPMT) [<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] are multiplex PCR methods for identifying plasmids with analogous replication or mobilization systems. PlasTrans, based on deep learning, identifies mobilizable metagenomic plasmid fragments [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Web servers such as PlasmidFinder [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], pMLST, and oriTfinder [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] were established based on collected maker gene databases and alignment-based methods to facilitate Rep, Inc, and MOB typing. COPLA [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], based on average nucleotide identity, performs taxonomic classifications of complete plasmid genomes with an overall accuracy of 41%. For the MOB typing, MOBscan [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] uses the HMMER model to annotate relaxase genes and classify plasmids accordingly. MOB-suite [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] performs plasmid typing for plasmid assemblies. First, it uses Mash distance to cluster plasmid assemblies into clusters; then, it uses marker gene databases to annotate them.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1:</label><caption><p>Experimental and computational schemes developed for plasmid classification</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Technology category</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Method</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Classification scheme</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Material</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DPMT [<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOB typing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmid DNA from clinical isolates</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used degenerate primers to hybridize relaxase-coding genes to identify and classify plasmids isolated from clinical isolates</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PlasTax-PCR [<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taxonomic typing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmid DNA from clinical isolates</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Utilized PCR primers that target conserved segments of the relaxase gene of plasmid taxonomic units (PTUs) to identify specific PTUs of transmissible plasmids</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PBRT [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rep typing or Inc typing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmid DNA from clinical isolates</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used multiplex PCR to amplify DNA fragments of replicons and detect known replicon types of plasmids</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Computational</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOBscan [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOB typing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmid protein sequences</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used the HMMER model to annotate the relaxases and further perform MOB typing</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOB-suite [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOB typing, MPF typing, and Rep typing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complete plasmid genomes or plasmid assembly clusters (Linux)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Utilized collected relaxase, oriT, replicon, and T4SS sequences to construct the database, then classified plasmid assembly clusters with BLAST</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PlasTans [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transmissible plasmid identification</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmid assembly contigs (Linux)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used the convolutional neural network deep learning algorithm to classify plasmid DNA fragments</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PlasmidFinder [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rep typing or Inc typing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Raw reads or complete plasmid genomes or plasmid assembly contigs (web server)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Utilized collected replicon sequences and BLASTn to perform Rep typing and Inc typing</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pMLST [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rep typing or Inc typing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Raw reads or complete plasmid genomes or plasmid assembly contigs (web server)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used collected plasmid multilocus sequence typing (pMLST) allele sequences, known sequence type profiles, and BLAST to perform Rep typing and Inc typing</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">oriTfinder [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOB typing, MPF typing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complete plasmid genomes (web server)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Utilized collected oriT, relaxase, T4CP, and T4SS sequences to annotate plasmids with BLAST</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">COPLA [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taxonomic typing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complete plasmid genomes or plasmid assembly sets (Linux)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used average nucleotide identity (ANI) metrics and hierarchical stochastic block modeling (HSBM) to create plasmid taxonomic units (PTUs) and predict taxonomic hosts</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Metagenomic sequencing makes it possible to obtain all plasmid DNA from microbial communities at once, and a number of computational tools for identifying plasmid fragments from metagenomic data have been developed, such as PlasFlow [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], PlasmidSeeker [<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], PlasClass [<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], PPR-Meta [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and PlasForest [<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. As DNA fragments of plasmids and bacteria are intermingled in metagenomic data [<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], recognizing the transmission mechanisms and host ranges of plasmids can be challenging. To this end, it is crucial to annotate MOB types of metagenomic plasmid fragments. However, this is difficult when plasmid assembly fragments are incomplete and essential genes for annotation are lacking. Therefore, it is worthwhile to consider alternative methods. Given that plasmids of the same MOB type have similar transmission mechanisms and host ranges, their genomic signatures (e.g., GC content and codon usage) tend to also be alike, not only relaxase [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In this context, neural networks, which have demonstrated strong performance in the classification and identification of biological sequences [<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], could be useful. Furthermore, language models [<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] derived from such neural networks have also showcased their impressive ability to characterize sequence features [<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In this methodology, short sequences of nucleotides (referred to as <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers) or amino acids are analogous to &#x0201c;words,&#x0201d; and the longer sequences of DNA or proteins are analogous to &#x0201c;sentences.&#x0201d; Through the application of unsupervised learning on large datasets, each &#x0201c;word&#x0201d; is linked to a feature vector that captures its context, offering a more sophisticated analysis than the traditional <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer frequency method, which simply counts the occurrence of nucleotide sequences without acknowledging their biochemical characteristics. Unlike the conventional method, this language model-based approach assesses sequences based on their contextual importance across different genetic environments, positioning contextually similar sequences close together in a multidimensional space. This technique provides deeper insights into the biochemical complexities of nucleotide sequences, thereby furnishing a more comprehensive understanding of an organism&#x02019;s functional biology [<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. To characterize the features of plasmids within the same MOB type, we employed language models to perform the MOB annotation. In addition to the relaxase-coding gene, language models exhibit the ability to capture more biological features and associations within comparable mobilization systems, making it possible to perform MOB annotation for metagenomic plasmid assemblies.</p><p>Thus, we presented MOBFinder, a tool for annotating MOB types from plasmid metagenomic fragments (PMFs). MOBFinder can process single or multiple plasmid DNA sequences, and it provides predicted MOB types for each input fragment, including MOBB, MOBC, MOBF, MOBH, MOBL, MOBM, MOBP, MOBQ, MOBT, MOBV, and non-MOB. Moreover, it provides the option to annotate plasmid bins from metagenomics data.</p><p>An overview of this work is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>, and the development of MOBFinder involved the following steps: (i) Benchmark dataset construction. Plasmid complete genomes obtained from the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) were classified into different MOB types based on relaxase databases. Then, to simulate plasmid fragments in metagenomic data, an artificial benchmark dataset of varying lengths was generated. (ii) Word embeddings. Numerical word vectors were generated using skip-gram to characterize the sequence features of different MOB categories. (iii) Classification model ensemble and optimization. Several classification models, specifically designed for different lengths, were trained and integrated to predict fragments of different lengths. Evaluations against a test dataset demonstrated that MOBFinder is a powerful tool for MOB typing of plasmid fragments and bins. Its application to a cohort of patients with type 2 diabetes (T2D) revealed a potential correlation between some MOB types and the spread of antibiotic resistance genes among T2D patients. This suggests that MOBFinder is an effective data analysis approach for investigating plasmid-mediated horizontal gene transfer within microbial communities.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1"><label>Figure 1:</label><caption><p>Flowchart of the technical approach utilized in this study. (A) General workflow of the development and testing of MOBFinder. (B) Using plasmid relaxases with known MOB types as reference sequences, we developed a database of relaxases from the nonredundant (NR) database representing different MOB types. (C) Utilizing the relaxase database, complete plasmid genomes from the NCBI were subjected to MOB typing. (D) Those complete genomes were also used to train a 4-mer language model using the skip-gram algorithm, allowing each 4-mer to be represented by a 100-dimensional word vector. For a DNA fragment, the average word vector of all 4-mers on its sequence serves as the feature vector for that DNA. (E) We constructed simulated metagenomic contigs from the complete genomes that had been MOB typed as a benchmark and encoded these contigs into word vectors. Then these word vectors were used to train a random forest algorithm. Then the trained model, with metagenomic DNA fragments as input, was used to predict the MOB typing of the corresponding DNA fragment based on its word vectors.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="giae047fig1" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>The workflow of MOBFinder</title><p>To annotate the MOB type of plasmid fragments in metagenomics, we designed MOBFinder (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). As MOB-suite [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] did not offer a quantitative likelihood score for the outcomes and some plasmids would be classified into multiple MOB types (<xref rid="sup6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>), we constructed a benchmark dataset using a high-resolution MOB typing strategy for categorizing complete plasmid genomes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>, <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">C</xref>). Then, based on a language model and random forest, we designed an algorithm to perform MOB typing for PMFs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1D</xref>, <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">E</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>MOB typing of complete plasmid genomes</title><p>Traditionally, plasmid MOB typing of complete plasmid genomes has been a bioinformatics task based on the analysis of relaxase sequence similarity. The practice of annotating MOB types through BLAST similarity searches using representative sequences of different MOB type relaxases has gradually evolved into the standard method for MOB typing [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In this work, we constructed a benchmark dataset of simulated metagenomic contigs based on complete plasmid genomes with known MOB types. Previous studies have included a relatively small number of plasmids in their analyses. To further expand the MOB typing training dataset, we annotated the newly collected plasmid complete genome data for MOB typing according to relaxase information.</p><p>Ten validated MOB relaxase protein families were collected, including MOBB, MOBC, MOBF, MOBH, MOBL, MOBM, MOBP, MOBQ, MOBT, and MOBV [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7&#x02013;9</xref>, <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>). For each MOB category, blastp (<ext-link xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/RRID:SCR_001010" ext-link-type="uri">RRID:SCR_001010</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] was used to search homologous protein sequences against the NCBI nonredundant protein sequence database, with an <italic toggle="yes">e-value</italic> threshold of 1e-10, a <italic toggle="yes">query coverage</italic> threshold of 70%, and an <italic toggle="yes">identity</italic> threshold of 70%. A previous study applied an <italic toggle="yes">e-value</italic> threshold of 1e-5 and minimum requirements for <italic toggle="yes">query coverage</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">identity</italic> set at 50% [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. However, employing these criteria, we observed that some relaxases were annotated as belonging to multiple MOB types. To eliminate ambiguous annotations and construct a more reliable dataset for the training of MOBFinder, we imposed the stricter criteria mentioned above. After the expansion of protein sequences, local relaxase databases were built using the &#x0201c;makeblastdb&#x0201d; command for MOB typing of plasmid genomes.</p><p>Plasmid genomes were retrieved from the NCBI nucleotide database using the keywords &#x0201c;complete&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;plasmid,&#x0201d; and incomplete fragments were removed manually for further analysis. The accession list of these plasmids is provided in <xref rid="sup6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>. For each plasmid genome, coding sequences were extracted from the genebank file, and blastp [<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] was employed to search for the best alignment of local relaxase databases. Here, we defined the <italic toggle="yes">mob_score</italic> to measure the likelihood of homology:</p><disp-formula>
<tex-math id="TM0001" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
\begin{eqnarray*}
mob\_score = \sqrt {0.01{\mathrm{*}}\textit{qcov}\_max{\mathrm{*}}\left( {1 - 1/{\mathrm{log}}_{10}\left( {\textit{bitscore}\_max} \right)} \right)}
\end{eqnarray*}\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>where <italic toggle="yes">qcov_max</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">bitscore_max</italic> represent the <italic toggle="yes">query coverage</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">bitscore</italic> corresponding to the match with the highest bit score, respectively. To identify plasmid genomes encoding known relaxase families, we set a <italic toggle="yes">mob_score</italic> threshold of 0.5, which was established in conjunction with a minimum <italic toggle="yes">query coverage</italic> of 50% and a minimum <italic toggle="yes">bitscore</italic> of 100. To further enhance the reliability of our classification, we introduced an <italic toggle="yes">e-value</italic> cutoff, conservatively set at 1e-10, to complete the plasmid genome classification (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1C</xref>). In instances where plasmid genomes yielded no blast results or exhibited an <italic toggle="yes">e-value</italic> exceeding 0.01, we categorized them as non-MOB.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Word embeddings using a language model</title><p>To characterize the features and patterns within each MOB category and use numerical word vectors to represent them, we utilized a skip-gram language model [<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] to learn from plasmid genomes. Using a sliding window, the model calculated the likelihood between segmented words and outputted a probability distribution over the context words. The training steps were as follows (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1D</xref>):</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Word generation. Since DNA sequences are composed of different nucleotide characters, we used a <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer sliding window to generate overlapping input words. For example, with <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> = 4, &#x0201c;ATCGCTGA&#x0201d; would be segmented into &#x0201c;ATCG,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;TCGC,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;CGCT,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;GCTG,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;CTGA.&#x0201d; In this step, unique words were generated.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Word encoding initialization. Each word was initially assigned a random vector.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Skip-gram model. We employed a standard skip-gram model as described in previous studies [<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] to generate word vectors through the dna2vec module [<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. A 2-layer neural network was used to construct the skip-gram model. The initialized vectors were used as input, and the output was a probability distribution over the input words. Layer 1 was a hidden layer to convert the initialized vectors into a 100-dimensional word vector representation as predefined by Ng [<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Layer 2 was used to compute and maximize the probability of the correct context words using the negative sampling function, with the size of context words set to 20 (10 words for upstream and downstream, respectively) as preset by Ng [<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p>Model training. For each input plasmid genome, we used an optimization algorithm to minimize the loss function. Then, using the default settings, we used backpropagation to update the neural network parameters (word vectors) for 10 epochs.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Word vector extraction. After the training process, the word vectors in the hidden layer were extracted to characterize the plasmid fragments.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Benchmark dataset construction</title><p>Because there are no real metagenomic data to serve as a benchmark, using simulated data as a benchmark dataset is a common approach when developing bioinformatics tools [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Therefore, in the development of MOBFinder, we artificially generated simulated datasets through the following steps:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>For classified plasmid genomes in each MOB category, we randomly split them at a proportion of 70% and 30% to construct the training and test datasets.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Training dataset. To predict plasmid fragments with different lengths, we generated contigs of different length ranges: 100&#x02013;400&#x000a0;bp, 401&#x02013;800&#x000a0;bp, 801&#x02013;1,200&#x000a0;bp, and 1,201&#x02013;1,600&#x000a0;bp. For each MOB class in each length range, we randomly generated 90,000 artificial contigs. Plasmid fragments longer than 1,600&#x000a0;bp were segmented into shorter contigs and predicted using models designed for the corresponding lengths.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Test dataset. Because some plasmid fragments in real metagenomics datasets were much longer, we generated 4 length groups to assess the performance of MOBFinder: group A with a length range of 801&#x02013;1,200&#x000a0;bp, group B with a length range of 1,201&#x02013;1,600&#x000a0;bp, group C with a length range of 3,000&#x02013;4,000&#x000a0;bp, and group D with a length range of 5,000&#x02013;10,000&#x000a0;bp. For each MOB class in these 4 groups, 500 fragments were randomly extracted.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Classification algorithm</title><p>To efficiently handle the training dataset and improve the robustness of MOBFinder, we employed random forest to train 4 predictive models using the training dataset. The detailed steps are as follows (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1E</xref>):</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Word representation calculation. For each contig in the training dataset, we used a 4-mer sliding window to generate overlapping words and transformed them into numerical word vectors using trained word embeddings. To characterize the underlying features and patterns of the input contigs, we summed all the word vectors to compute their average as input of random forest.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Classification model training. To improve the performance of MOBFinder, we trained 4 classification models on different lengths in the training dataset: 100&#x02013;400&#x000a0;bp, 401&#x02013;800&#x000a0;bp, 801&#x02013;1,200&#x000a0;bp, and 1,201&#x02013;1,600&#x000a0;bp. The number of trees was set to 500 to generate predictive models.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Model ensemble. The 4 trained models were ensembled into MOBFinder to make more accurate predictions. For fragments shorter than 100&#x000a0;bp, we used a model designed for 100&#x02013;400&#x000a0;bp to predict the MOB type. For those longer than 1,600&#x000a0;bp, we segmented them into short contigs and made predictions using the corresponding model. For example, a fragment with a length of 4,000&#x000a0;bp would be segmented into 3 contigs: 2 with a length of 1,600&#x000a0;bp and 1 of 800&#x000a0;bp. After predicting fragments with the corresponding models, we aggregated and calculated the weighted average scores for each MOB class, and the MOB type with the highest score was selected as the final prediction result for the input fragment.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Plasmid bin classification. Metagenomic binning is an essential step in the reconstruction of genomes from individual microorganisms. Thus, we designed MOBFinder to perform MOB typing on both plasmid contigs and plasmid bins. If the input is a plasmid bin, MOBFinder predicts the likelihood of each MOB class for fragments within the bin. For each MOB category, MOBFinder aggregates the scores of each sequence within the bin and calculates the weighted average scores based on the sequence length. The MOB category with the maximum score is selected as the prediction result.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Performance validation</title><p>A test dataset was used to assess the performance of MOBFinder and compare it to MOB-suite and MOBscan. Because MOBscan can only predict MOB type using plasmid protein sequences rather than DNA sequences, we first annotated the proteins in the plasmid fragments of the test set using Prokka (<ext-link xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/RRID:SCR_014732" ext-link-type="uri">RRID:SCR_014732</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and then used MOBscan to predict the MOB type based on the annotated proteins. We calculated overall <italic toggle="yes">accuracy, kappa</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">run time</italic> by comparing the predicted classes and true classes. We used the online server of MOBscan to perform the MOB annotation, and the calculation of <italic toggle="yes">run time</italic> for MOBScan was confined to the duration spent on preprocessing with Prokka locally. The overall <italic toggle="yes">accuracy</italic> was the proportion of accurate predictions. The <italic toggle="yes">kappa</italic> (a) was calculated to assess the overall consistency between the predictions and true classes, which took into account the possibility of random prediction. <italic toggle="yes">Po</italic> represented observed accuracy [<italic toggle="yes">Po</italic> = (<italic toggle="yes">A<sub>11</sub></italic> + <italic toggle="yes">A<sub>22</sub></italic> + &#x02026; + <italic toggle="yes">Ann</italic>)/<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>], where <italic toggle="yes">A<sub>11</sub>, A<sub>22</sub></italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Ann</italic> represented the values on the diagonal of the confusion matrix and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> represented the number of MOB categories. <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> represented the total number of samples. <italic toggle="yes">Pe</italic> represented the expected accuracy [<italic toggle="yes">Pe</italic> = (<italic toggle="yes">E<sub>11</sub></italic> + <italic toggle="yes">E<sub>22</sub></italic> + &#x02026; + <italic toggle="yes">Enn</italic>)/<italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sup>2</sup>], where <italic toggle="yes">E<sub>11</sub>, E<sub>22</sub></italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Enn</italic> were the expected values in each cell of the confusion matrix; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> was the number of MOB classes; and <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> was the total number of samples. The <italic toggle="yes">run time</italic> was recorded using the command &#x0201c;time&#x0201d; in Linux.</p><disp-formula>
<tex-math id="TM0002" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
\begin{eqnarray*} \begin{array}{@{}*{2}{l}@{}} {\textit{kappa} = \left( {Po - Pe} \right)/\left( {1 - Pe} \right)}&#x00026;{\left( a \right)}\\ {\textit{balanced}\,\,\textit{accuracy} = \left( {TPR + TNR} \right)/2}&#x00026;{\left( b \right)}\\ {\textit{harmonic}\,\,\textit{mean} = 2*Sn*Sp/\left( {Sn + Sp} \right)}&#x00026;{\left( c \right)}\\ {F1 - \textit{score} = 2*\textit{precision}*\textit{recall}/\left( {\textit{precision} + \textit{recall}} \right)}&#x00026;{\left( d \right)} \end{array}
\end{eqnarray*}\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>For each MOB category, we also calculated the <italic toggle="yes">balanced accuracy</italic> (b), <italic toggle="yes">harmonic mean</italic> (c), and <italic toggle="yes">F1-score</italic> (d). Considering the class imbalance within the training dataset, <italic toggle="yes">balanced accuracy</italic> was used to measure the average accuracy of each MOB category, where <italic toggle="yes">TPR</italic> was the true-positive rate [<italic toggle="yes">TRP</italic> = true positives/(true positives + false negatives)] and <italic toggle="yes">TNR</italic> was the true-negative rate [<italic toggle="yes">TNR</italic> = true negatives/(true negatives + false positives)]. The <italic toggle="yes">harmonic mean</italic> provided an overall evaluation of the model&#x02019;s performance, where <italic toggle="yes">Sn</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Sp</italic> represented sensitivity [<italic toggle="yes">Sn</italic> = true positives/(true positives + false negatives)] and specificity [<italic toggle="yes">Sp</italic> = true negatives/(true negatives + false positives)], respectively. The <italic toggle="yes">F1-score</italic> combined <italic toggle="yes">precision</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">recall</italic>, providing a balanced measure of the model&#x02019;s performance, where <italic toggle="yes">precision</italic> was the number of correct positive predictions out of all positive predictions [<italic toggle="yes">precision</italic> = true positives/(true positives + false positives)] and <italic toggle="yes">recall</italic> was the number of correct positive predictions out of all actual positive predictions. [<italic toggle="yes">recall</italic> = true positives/(true positives + false negatives)].</p><p>A receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve was used to visualize the performance of MOBFinder in predicting each MOB category, where the x-axis and y-axis were the false-positive rate (<italic toggle="yes">FPR</italic>) and true-positive rate (<italic toggle="yes">TPR</italic>). Plots closer to the left and top indicate higher <italic toggle="yes">TPR</italic> and lower <italic toggle="yes">FPR</italic>, which means better performance. For each MOB class, the area under the curve (AUC) value was calculated to quantify the performance of MOBFinder. An AUC value between 0.5 and 1 indicates that the model performs better than random chance, and a higher AUC value indicates better prediction capability.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Annotation and analysis of T2D metagenomic data</title><p>Metagenomic sequencing data (SRA045646 and SRA050230) were retrieved from the NCBI Short Read Archive (SRA) database to investigate whether the plasmids within different MOB classes were associated with antibiotic resistance enrichment in T2D patients, as suggested by previous studies [<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. All metagenomic data were preprocessed using the same protocols. PRINSEQ (<ext-link xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/RRID:SCR_005454" ext-link-type="uri">RRID:SCR_005454</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] was used to remove low-quality reads and bowtie2 (<ext-link xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/RRID:SCR_016368" ext-link-type="uri">RRID:SCR_016368</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] was used to remove host reads by aligning them to the human GRCH38 reference genome downloaded from the ENSEMBL database. We excluded metagenomic samples that did not pass quality control. Because the abundance of plasmids in metagenomes was much lower than that of bacteria, we only retained samples with more than 10,000,000 paired-end reads for downstream analysis (<xref rid="sup6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S2</xref>).</p><p>To improve the efficiency and accuracy of assembly, we used MEGAHIT (<ext-link xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/RRID:SCR_018551" ext-link-type="uri">RRID:SCR_018551</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] to generate metagenomic contigs. PPR-Meta (<ext-link xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/RRID:SCR_016915" ext-link-type="uri">RRID:SCR_016915</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] was utilized to identify and extract plasmid fragments from the assembled fragments while filtering out bacteria and phage sequences. COCACOLA [<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] was employed to cluster plasmid fragments into bins based on sequence similarity and composition. This allowed us to investigate the plasmid fragments from same originate and enabled better annotation and analysis of their functions.</p><p>MOBFinder was applied to annotate the MOB types in each plasmid bin. The average fragments per kilobase per million of each plasmid bin was calculated using bowtie2 to represent its abundance. Next, we analyzed the significance of differences in plasmid bins and various MOB types between healthy and T2D groups using the Wilcoxon rank-sum test. The calculation of <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values was adjusted for multiple comparisons using the Benjamini&#x02013;Hochberg method (denoted as <italic toggle="yes">p.adjust</italic>). ABRicate (<ext-link xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/RRID:SCR_021093" ext-link-type="uri">RRID:SCR_021093</ext-link>) [<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] was utilized to annotate antibiotic resistance genes (<italic toggle="yes">identity</italic> &#x0003e;50% and <italic toggle="yes">qcov</italic> &#x0003e;50%) in each plasmid bin, based on 4 antibiotic resistance gene databases [<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44&#x02013;47</xref>]. The Tukey honest significant difference test was performed to compare the identified resistance genes among different MOB classes. All statistical analyses were conducted using R.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3-1"><title>MOB typing of plasmid genomes</title><p>To construct the benchmark datasets, we obtained 90,395 complete plasmid genomes and categorized them into 11 MOB categories using blast (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). We removed 22,470 of them potentially classified into more than 1 MOB class, leaving 67,925 classified genomes for the training and optimization of MOBFinder (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2A</xref>). Our analysis results revealed significant differences in the number, average length, and GC content of plasmid genomes among MOB types. Notably, non-MOB types included the genomes with the most and longest average length, whereas MOBB and MOBM had the fewest plasmid genomes and shortest average length, respectively. In terms of GC content, MOBL had the lowest and MOBQ had the highest amounts. Moreover, plasmids of different MOB types exhibited diverse host ranges at the genus level (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2B</xref>). MOBB was predominantly found in <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroides, Hymenobacter, Parabacteroides, Phocaeicola</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Spirosoma</italic>. Particularly, <italic toggle="yes">Phocaeicola</italic> has been detected in the human gut and possessed the gene for porphyran degradation through horizontal gene transfer [<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. MOBC, MOBF, MOBH, and MOBP were all found in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella. Klebsiella</italic> also is a multidrug-resistant bacterium that has demonstrated resistance to multiple antibiotics [<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. MOBL, MOBT, and MOBV were mainly discovered in <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>. Almost all MOBM-type plasmid genomes were present in <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Enterocloster</italic>, and some species in <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium</italic> could cause various diseases [<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. MOBQ demonstrated a broader host range, including <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter, Agrobacterium, Escherichia, Rhizobium, Lactiplantibacillus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic>. Non-MOB plasmids were detected in the majority of bacteria. These results illustrate the relationship between different MOB types and their host ranges, as well as demonstrate that MOB typing of plasmid fragments is feasible in the absence of relaxases.</p><fig position="float" id="fig2"><label>Figure 2:</label><caption><p>Benchmark dataset construction using a high-resolution strategy. (A) Proportion of classified plasmid genomes. A confidence level of &#x0201c;sure&#x0201d; means that the classified plasmid genomes had a <italic toggle="yes">mob_score</italic> of more than 0.5 and an <italic toggle="yes">e-value</italic> of less than 1e-10, while &#x0201c;possible&#x0201d; did not. Plasmid genomes identified as &#x0201c;sure&#x0201d; were used to generate benchmark datasets. Non-MOB, nonmobilizable plasmid. (B) Host range of the classified plasmid genomes at the genus level. Different colors represent different genera, and genera accounting for less than 5% of the total abundance are grouped under the category &#x0201c;other.&#x0201d;</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="giae047fig2" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2:</label><caption><p>Number, average length, and GC content of plasmid genomes for each MOB type</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Class</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average length</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOBB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">623</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,921.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.27</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOBC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,218</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,965.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOBF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21,268</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103,802.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOBH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,880</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">151,108.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.37</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOBL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,446</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51,430.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.57</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOBM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,761</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,684.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOBP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,617</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32,237.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.70</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOBQ</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,347</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89,357.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.77</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOBT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,181</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,643.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOBV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,405</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,595.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.75</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-MOB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,649</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37,581.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.84</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>Overall performance of MOBFinder</title><p>We evaluated the overall performance of MOBFinder in terms of <italic toggle="yes">accuracy, kappa</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">run time</italic> and compared the tool to MOBscan and MOB-suite. MOBscan did not perform well, achieving low <italic toggle="yes">accuracy</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">kappa</italic> values across sequences of varying lengths, while MOB-suite exhibited marginally better performance than MOBscan when handling sequences of greater length (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3A</xref>, <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">B</xref>). In comparison, the <italic toggle="yes">accuracy</italic> of MOBFinder ranged from 70% to 77%, a significant improvement of at least 59% over MOB-suite (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3A</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">kappa</italic> of MOBFinder ranged between 67% and 75% and was approximately 65% higher than that of MOB-suite (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3B</xref>). Moreover, MOBFinder exhibited a shorter <italic toggle="yes">run time</italic> in the test dataset, with a more gradual increase trend (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3C</xref>). In general, these results indicate that MOBFinder greatly outperformed the other tools and consistently improved in accuracy and consistency as the sequence length increased.</p><fig position="float" id="fig3"><label>Figure 3:</label><caption><p>Overall performance of MOBFinder and comparison to MOB-suite and MOBScan. Evaluation and comparison in terms of (A) <italic toggle="yes">accuracy</italic>, (B) <italic toggle="yes">kappa</italic>, and (C) <italic toggle="yes">run time</italic> (C). The 4 fragment length groups in the test dataset were group A (801&#x02013;1,200&#x000a0;bp), group B (1,201&#x02013;1,600&#x000a0;bp), group C (3,000&#x02013;4,000&#x000a0;bp), and group D (5,000&#x02013;10,000bp). (D) For each MOB type, the <italic toggle="yes">balanced accuracy, harmonic mean</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">F1-score</italic> were used to assess the performance of MOBFinder and compared to MOB-suite and MOBscan. Since MOB-suite and MOBscan do not include the prediction of MOBL, only the results of MOBL from MOBFinder are provided. MOBFinder, MOB-suite, and MOBscan are represented by blue lines, orange lines, and gray lines, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="giae047fig3" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-3"><title>Evaluation by MOB category</title><p>Next, to evaluate the discrimination ability of MOBFinder for each MOB type, we calculated the <italic toggle="yes">balanced accuracy, harmonic mean</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">F1-score</italic> using the test dataset (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3D</xref>). It demonstrated the highest performance for MOBB and MOBM, while its ability to identify non-MOB types was comparatively low. For MOBM, the <italic toggle="yes">balanced accuracy</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">harmonic mean</italic> reached up to 99% and the <italic toggle="yes">F1-score</italic> exceeded 96% for all length groups. For non-MOB, the <italic toggle="yes">balanced accuracy</italic> was 65%, the <italic toggle="yes">harmonic mean</italic> was 49%, and the <italic toggle="yes">F1-score</italic> was 40%. Compared to MOB-suite, MOBFinder exhibited much better performance in predicting all MOB classes. Even for non-MOB, it showed an approximate 13% improvement over the other tools in terms of <italic toggle="yes">balanced accuracy</italic>, 34% in terms of <italic toggle="yes">harmonic mean</italic>, and 24% in terms of <italic toggle="yes">F1-score</italic>.</p><p>In AUC analyses (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), all values were greater than 0.8, indicating that the tool effectively distinguished between positive and negative samples in each MOB class. In fact, most values were higher than 0.9, except for MOBT and non-MOB. The performance differences by MOB type might be attributable to the differences in host ranges and sequence features among types. Additionally, the imbalance in the training dataset for each MOB type may also be a primary factor contributing to the performance disparities.</p><fig position="float" id="fig4"><label>Figure 4:</label><caption><p>ROC curves and AUC values for MOBFinder. The curves were plotted using the output scores of MOBFinder, and the AUC values were calculated to quantify the performance of the tool for each MOB class.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="giae047fig4" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-4"><title>Application to T2D metagenomic data</title><p>In a previous study, enrichment analysis of fecal samples identified antibiotic resistance pathways in patients with T2D [<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The precise mechanism of this enrichment, however, remained elusive. We used MOBFinder to analyze real T2D metagenomic data [<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. After preprocessing and assembly, 2,217,064 metagenomic fragments were generated, and plasmid assemblies were identified using PPR-Meta. Subsequently, the plasmid fragments were clustered into 55 bins and annotated using MOBFinder. By employing MOBFinder, we assigned 2 bins to the MOBF class, 8 bins to MOBL, and 17 bins to MOBQ and identified 28 bins as non-MOB (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). Furthermore, we detected 15 bins that exhibited significant differences between the T2D group and a control group. Among them, 1 bin was classified as MOBF, 2 as MOBL, 5 as MOBQ, and 7 as non-MOB (<xref rid="sup6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S2</xref>). Among above MOB types, MOBQ contains the highest number of bins enriched in T2D, while MOBF is widely present in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2B</xref>); some strains of <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella</italic> are resistant to multiple antibiotics, including carbapenems [<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], and these 2 MOB types might contribute to antibiotic resistance in T2D patients. Indeed, when we compared the average abundance of each MOB type between the T2D group and the control group (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5B</xref>), the abundances of MOBF and MOBQ were significantly greater in the T2D group.</p><fig position="float" id="fig5"><label>Figure 5:</label><caption><p>Annotation of T2D-related plasmid bins using MOBFinder. (A) Heatmap of plasmid bins between T2D patients and controls. Each column represents a sample, and each row represents a plasmid bin. (B) Comparison of the abundance of the 4 identified MOB types between T2D patients and controls. The <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value was calculated using the Wilcoxon rank-sum test, adjusted using the Benjamini&#x02013;Hochberg method for multiple comparisons (*<italic toggle="yes">P-adjust</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P-adjust</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, and ***<italic toggle="yes">P-adjust</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="giae047fig5" position="float"/></fig><p>In addition, these 2 MOB types can be transferred among multiple bacterial species. This suggests that an increase in these 2 MOB types could potentially raise the risk of bacterial infection among individuals with T2D. Subsequently, we used 4 databases [<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44&#x02013;47</xref>] to detect drug resistance genes in 4 MOB types (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The number of such genes was significantly higher in MOBF than in the other 3 MOB types. This suggests that MOBF plasmids may carry more drug resistance genes than the other MOB types. Furthermore, the increase in MOBF and MOBQ plasmids could result in more bacteria acquiring drug resistance genes, thereby leading to more antibiotic resistance pathways in T2D patients. In summary, our results demonstrate the utility of MOBFinder for annotating plasmid fragments in metagenomes, uncovering the potential mechanisms underlying the antibiotic resistance enrichment in metagenomic analysis.</p><fig position="float" id="fig6"><label>Figure 6:</label><caption><p>Comparison of resistance genes among different MOB types. Four databases were used to identify antibiotic resistance gene within each MOB type, and the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value was calculated using the Tukey honest significant difference test. The 2 groups without significance markings indicate no statistical difference (*<italic toggle="yes">P-adjust</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P-adjust</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, and ***<italic toggle="yes">P-adjust</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="giae047fig6" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-5"><title>Use of MOBFinder</title><p>MOBFinder can predict the MOB type of plasmid fragments and bins in metagenomics. For PMFs, it takes a FASTA file as input. The output file consists of 13 columns. The first column represents the fragment ID, the second column displays the predicted MOB type, and columns 3 to 13 represent the scores for each MOB class, namely, MOBB, MOBC, MOBF, MOBH, MOBL, MOBM, MOBP, MOBQ, MOBT, MOBV, and non-MOB.</p><p>For plasmid metagenomic bins, MOBFinder requires 2 input files: a FASTA file containing the plasmid fragments and a metatable that records the mapping between plasmid fragment IDs and bin IDs. The output results are similar to those of plasmid fragments. The first column is the plasmid bin ID. The second is the predicted MOB class of the plasmid bins. The other columns present the MOB scores of the different MOB types.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p>We developed MOBFinder based on a language model and the random forest algorithm to classify plasmid fragments and bins from metagenomics data into MOB types. First, using the relaxase-alignment method, plasmid genomes were classified into distinct MOB categories. Analyses revealed substantial differences in parameters such as the number, average length, and GC content of plasmid genomes across MOB types. Additionally, there were noteworthy differences in the host ranges among different MOB classes. These results suggest the potential of utilizing sequence features from different MOB types for PMF MOB typing. To characterize the plasmids within each MOB type, we used the skip-gram model to generate word vectors. Our tool demonstrated superior overall performance compared to other tools. Specifically, for each MOB category, MOBFinder exhibited significant improvements in <italic toggle="yes">balanced accuracy, harmonic mean</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">F1-score</italic>, with values reaching up to 99% for the first 2 measures in the MOBM category.</p><p>Traditionally, <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer frequency models and one-hot encoding have commonly been employed to digitize biological sequences, extensively applied across various machine learning algorithms [<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. However, both models simply mark or count the frequency of various characters in sequences, failing to reflect the biological significance underlying each character. These models may also encounter dimensionality issues [<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. For instance, in the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer model, if <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> is set to 8, the dimensionality of the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer vector of each DNA sequence becomes 4<sup>8</sup>, which is problematic in metagenomics where most fragment lengths do not reach this magnitude. This would result in significant noise in the feature vector and cause overfitting. Similarly, in the one-hot model, for a sequence of length <italic toggle="yes">L</italic> using 4-mers as the base unit, it would require <italic toggle="yes">L</italic> one-hot vectors each with a dimensionality of 4<sup>4</sup>. In such instances, if the dataset for training is not sufficiently large, this representation method could also lead to overfitting due to high dimensionality. In contrast, word vector models offer a superior solution to these problems. Such models initially perform a random initialization of vectors for each &#x0201c;word.&#x0201d; Taking the skip-gram algorithm utilized in this study as an example, the dimension of a random vector can be 1-of-<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>, where <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> represents the size of the vocabulary [<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Following unsupervised pretraining on large datasets, the algorithm maps characters with similar contexts to similar feature spaces. The dimensions of the coordinates (i.e., the word vectors) of these feature spaces will be lower than those of the initial random vectors. Thus, through unsupervised pretraining on large datasets, language models can compress high-dimensional initial vectors into lower-dimensional word vectors (e.g., MOBFinder&#x02019;s word vectors have a dimensionality of 100), enabling the feature vectors to contain more character information while effectively avoiding dimensionality issues during supervised training.</p><p>In a metagenomic sequences classification task, 4-mer is widely used as the basic unit in various bioinformatics tools [<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], and thus MOBFinder takes this as a &#x0201c;word.&#x0201d; To assess the impact of training word vectors with different <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer lengths on performance, we compared models with <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer lengths of 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, and 8 (<xref rid="sup6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>). We observed lower overall <italic toggle="yes">accuracy</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">kappa</italic> values for <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> = 2. At <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> = 4, the <italic toggle="yes">balanced accuracy, harmonic mean, F1-score</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">AUC</italic> values stabilized across different MOB types. Subsequently, as the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer length increased, there was no significant improvement in <italic toggle="yes">accuracy</italic> or other metrics, while the <italic toggle="yes">run time</italic> gradually increased. Therefore, we chose a <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer length of 4 for training word vectors and developing MOBFinder.</p><p>Interestingly, in an analysis of T2D metagenomic sequencing data [<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], we noted a significant increase in MOBF and MOBQ type plasmids in T2D patients. Moreover, we found more drug resistance genes in the MOBF class, whose dominant hosts are <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia</italic>, which are associated with the spread of multidrug resistance. Although previous analyses of gut metagenomic data from patients with T2D have reported enrichment of drug resistance pathways [<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], our results suggest a potential reason for it: the increased abundance of MOBF- and MOBQ-type plasmids in the guts of individuals with T2D may disseminate more antibiotic resistance genes, resulting in such enrichment.</p><p>At present, databases contain a large amount of human metagenomic data derived from second-generation sequencing. However, understanding of the functions of numerous disease-linked microbial sequences remains limited, attributable to the incomplete nature of metagenomic fragments. The development of MOBFinder enables MOB annotation for plasmid fragments from metagenomics data and provides a powerful tool for investigating the transmission mechanisms of plasmid-mediated antibiotic resistance genes and virulence factors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In summary, MOBFinder is a tool for MOB typing of plasmid fragments and bins from metagenomic data. Analyses of classified plasmid genomes unveiled notable differences in sequence characteristics and host ranges across MOB types. Hence, we employed a language model to extract the sequence features specific to each MOB type and represented them using word vectors. Additionally, we boosted prediction accuracy by training and integrating several random forest classification models. MOBFinder surpassed other tools in performance tests and successfully detected an increase in certain MOB-type plasmids in T2D patients. Importantly, these MOB-type plasmids harbor potential drug resistance genes, thus offering an explanation for the observed antibiotic resistance in T2D individuals. This suggests that MOBFinder could potentially aid the formulation of specific medications to curb drug resistance transmission. We anticipate that MOBFinder will be a powerful tool for the analysis of plasmid-mediated transmission.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Availability of Source Code and Requirements</title><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Project name: MOBFinder</p></list-item><list-item><p>Project homepage: <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/FengTaoSMU/MOBFinder" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/FengTaoSMU/MOBFinder</ext-link></p></list-item><list-item><p>Operating system(s): Linux</p></list-item><list-item><p>Programming language: Python, R script</p></list-item><list-item><p>Other requirements: BLAST, biopython</p></list-item><list-item><p>License: GPL-3.0</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://scicrunch.org/resolver/RRID:SCR_024451" ext-link-type="uri">RRID:SCR_024451</ext-link>
</p></list-item><list-item><p>biotoolsID: MOBFinder</p></list-item></list></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>giae047_GIGA-D-24-00070_Original_Submission</label><media xlink:href="giae047_giga-d-24-00070_original_submission.pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup2" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>giae047_GIGA-D-24-00070_Revision_1</label><media xlink:href="giae047_giga-d-24-00070_revision_1.pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup3" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>giae047_Response_to_Reviewer_Comments_Original_Submission</label><media xlink:href="giae047_response_to_reviewer_comments_original_submission.pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup4" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>giae047_Reviewer_1_Report_Original_Submission</label><caption><p>Haruo Suzuki -- 3/23/2024 Reviewed</p></caption><media xlink:href="giae047_reviewer_1_report_original_submission.pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup5" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>giae047_Reviewer_2_Report_Original_Submission</label><caption><p>Dan Wang -- 5/16/2024 Reviewed</p></caption><media xlink:href="giae047_reviewer_2_report_original_submission.pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup6" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>giae047_Supplemental_Files</label><media xlink:href="giae047_supplemental_files.zip"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec id="sec7"><title>Additional Files</title><p>
<bold>Supplementary Table S1</bold>. Accessions list of classified plasmid genomes.</p><p>
<bold>Supplementary Table S2</bold>. List of metagenomic samples used in our analysis.</p><p>
<bold>Supplementary Fig. S1</bold>. MOB typing using MOB-suite. Single-class, plasmid genomes classified into 1 MOB type; multiclass, plasmid genomes classified into more than 1 MOB category; non-MOB, nonmobilizable plasmids.</p><p>
<bold>Supplementary Fig. S2</bold>. Abundance of each significantly different plasmid bin from various MOB types between patients with type 2 diabetes and controls.</p><p>
<bold>Supplementary Fig. S3</bold>. Comparison results for the development of MOBFinder using word vectors trained with different <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer lengths. (A&#x02013;C) Overall <italic toggle="yes">accuracy, kappa</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">run time</italic> of the MOB classification model trained with word vectors trained using different lengths of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers. (D) <italic toggle="yes">Balanced accuracy, harmonic mean, F1-score</italic>, and AUC of word vectors trained with different <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer lengths across different MOB types.</p></sec><sec sec-type="abbreviations" id="sec8"><title>Abbreviations</title><p>AUC: the area under the curve; BLAST: Basic Local Alignment Search Tool; DPMT: degenerate primer MOB typing; Inc: incompatibility typing; MOB: mobilization typing; MPF: mate&#x02013;pair formation typing; NCBI: National Center for Biotechnology Information; non-MOB: nonmobilizable; PBRT: PCR-based replicon typing; PlasTax-PCR: plasmid taxonomic PCR; Rep: replicon typing; ROC: receiver operating characteristic; Sn: sensitivity; Sp: specificity; SRA: Short Read Archive; T2D: type 2 diabetes; TNR: true-negative rate; TPR: true-positive rate.</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>T.F., Z.C.F., and H.W.Z. proposed and designed this work. T.F. and Z.C.F. developed and optimized the software. T.F., Z.C.F., S.F.W., and H.W.Z. wrote and revised the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec10"><title>Funding</title><p>This investigation was financially supported by the National Key R&#x00026;D Program of China(2022YFA0806400) and the National Natural Science Foundation of China (82102508, 81925026).</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec11"><title>Data Availability</title><p>Snapshots of our code and other data further supporting this work are openly available in the <italic toggle="yes">GigaScience</italic> repository, GigaDB [<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec12"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Helinski</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A brief history of plasmids</article-title>. <source>EcoSal Plus</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>eESP00282021</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/ecosalplus.esp-0028-2021</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35373578</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Garcill&#x000e1;n-Barcia</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Francia</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de&#x000a0;la&#x000a0;Cruz</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The diversity of conjugative relaxases and its application in plasmid classification</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>657</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6976.2009.00168.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19396961</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Beltr&#x000e1;n</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DelaFuente</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Le&#x000f3;n-Sampedro</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Beyond horizontal gene transfer: the role of plasmids in bacterial evolution</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Micro</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>347</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-020-00497-1</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Shintani</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanchez</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>ZK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kimbara</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Genomics of microbial plasmids: classification and identification based on replication and transfer systems and host taxonomy</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>242</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2015.00242</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25873913</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Redondo-Salvo</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bartomeus-Pe&#x000f1;alver</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vielva</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>COPLA, a taxonomic classifier of plasmids</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinf</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>390</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-021-04299-x</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Carattoli</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hasman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>PlasmidFinder and In Silico pMLST: identification and typing of plasmid replicons in whole-genome sequencing (WGS)</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>2075</volume>:<fpage>285</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4939-9877-7_20</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31584170</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Smillie</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcill&#x000e1;n-Barcia</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Francia</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Mobility of plasmids</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>434</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MMBR.00020-10</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20805406</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Francia</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Varsaki</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcill&#x000e1;n-Barcia</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>A classification scheme for mobilization regions of bacterial plasmids</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>100</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.femsre.2003.09.001</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14975531</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Garcill&#x000e1;n-Barcia</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alvarado</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de&#x000a0;la&#x000a0;Cruz</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of bacterial plasmids based on mobility and plasmid population biology</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>936</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6976.2011.00291.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21711366</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Bradley</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>den&#x000a0;Bakker</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rocha</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>EPC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Ultrafast search of all deposited bacterial and viral genomic data</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>152</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41587-018-0010-1</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30718882</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Alvarado</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcill&#x000e1;n-Barcia</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de&#x000a0;la&#x000a0;Cruz</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A degenerate primer MOB typing (DPMT) method to classify gamma-proteobacterial plasmids in clinical and environmental settings</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e40438</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0040438</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22792321</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Cuartas</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coque</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de&#x000a0;la&#x000a0;Cruz</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>PLASmid TAXonomic PCR (PlasTax-PCR), a multiplex relaxase MOB typing to assort plasmids into taxonomic units</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>2392</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-0716-1799-1_10</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34773620</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Carattoli</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bertini</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Villa</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Identification of plasmids by PCR-based replicon typing</article-title>. <source>J Microbiol Methods</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>219</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mimet.2005.03.018</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15935499</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Fang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of the conjugative and mobilizable plasmid fragments in the plasmidome using sequence signatures</article-title>. <source>Microb Genom</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>mgen000459</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.000459</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33074084</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Li</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>oriTfinder: a web-based tool for the identification of origin of transfers in DNA sequences of bacterial mobile genetic elements</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>W1</issue>):<fpage>W229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky352</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29733379</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Garcill&#x000e1;n-Barcia</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redondo-Salvo</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vielva</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>MOBscan: automated annotation of MOB relaxases</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>2075</volume>:<fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>308</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4939-9877-7_21</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31584171</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Robertson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nash</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JHE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>MOB-suite: software tools for clustering, reconstruction and typing of plasmids from draft assemblies</article-title>. <source>Microb Genom</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e000206</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.000206</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30052170</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Robertson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bessonov</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schonfeld</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Universal whole-sequence-based plasmid typing and its utility to prediction of host range and epidemiological surveillance</article-title>. <source>Microb Genom</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>mgen000435</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.000435</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32969786</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Krawczyk</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lipinski</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dziembowski</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>PlasFlow: predicting plasmid sequences in metagenomic data using genome signatures</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e35</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkx1321</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29346586</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Roosaare</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Puustusmaa</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>M&#x000f6;ls</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>PlasmidSeeker: identification of known plasmids from bacterial whole genome sequencing reads</article-title>. <source>PeerJ</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e4588</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.4588</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29629246</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Pellow</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mizrahi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shamir</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>PlasClass improves plasmid sequence classification</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>e1007781</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007781</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32243433</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Fang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>PPR-Meta: a tool for identifying phages and plasmids from metagenomic fragments using deep learning</article-title>. <source>Gigascience</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gigascience/giz066</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Pradier</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tissot</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fiston-Lavier</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>PlasForest: a homology-based random forest classifier for plasmid detection in genomic datasets</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinf</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>349</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-021-04270-w</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sobecky</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hazen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Horizontal gene transfer and mobile genetic elements in marine systems</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>532</volume>:<fpage>435</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-60327-853-9_25</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19271200</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Suzuki</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yano</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Predicting plasmid promiscuity based on genomic signature</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>192</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>6045</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00277-10</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20851899</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>DeePhage: distinguishing virulent and temperate phage-derived sequences in metavirome data with a deep learning approach</article-title>. <source>Gigascience</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>giab056</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gigascience/giab056</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34498685</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Fang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feng</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>DeePVP: identification and classification of phage virion proteins using deep learning</article-title>. <source>Gigascience</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>giac076</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gigascience/giac076</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35950840</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Mikolov</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Corrado</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Efficient estimation of word representations in vector space</article-title>. <source>arXiv preprint</source>. <year>2013</year>. <comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/arXiv:1301.3781" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/arXiv:1301.3781</ext-link>. Accessed 16 November 2021</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Ng</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>dna2vec: consistent vector representations of variable-length k-mers</article-title>. <source>arXiv</source>. <year>2017</year>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.48550/arXiv.1701.06279</pub-id><comment>. Accessed 18 November 2021</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Tsukiyama</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hasan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fujii</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>LSTM-PHV: prediction of human-virus protein-protein interactions by LSTM with word2vec</article-title>. <source>Brief Bioinform</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>bbab228</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bib/bbab228</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34160596</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sharma</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shrivastava</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kumar&#x000a0;Singh</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Deep-ABPpred: identifying antibacterial peptides in protein sequences using bidirectional LSTM with word2vec</article-title>. <source>Brief Bioinform</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>bbab065</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bib/bbab065</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33784381</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Asgari</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mofrad</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Continuous distributed representation of biological sequences for deep proteomics and genomics</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e0141287</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0141287</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26555596</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wisniewski</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Traore</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bannam</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>TcpM: a novel relaxase that mediates transfer of large conjugative plasmids from Clostridium perfringens</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>884</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mmi.13270</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26560080</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Ramachandran</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miguel-Arribas</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abia</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Discovery of a new family of relaxases in Firmicutes bacteria</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e1006586</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1006586</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28207825</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Camacho</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coulouris</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Avagyan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>BLAST+: architecture and applications</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinf</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>421</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-10-421</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Seemann</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prokka: rapid prokaryotic genome annotation</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>2068</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu153</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24642063</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Qin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cai</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>A metagenome-wide association study of gut microbiota in type 2 diabetes</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>490</volume>(<issue>7418</issue>):<fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11450</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23023125</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tremaroli</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schmidt</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>The gut microbiota in prediabetes and diabetes: a population-based cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>379</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>..<comment>e3. </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2020.06.011</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32652044</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Schmieder</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Edwards</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Quality control and preprocessing of metagenomic datasets</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>863</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr026</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21278185</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Langmead</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salzberg</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1923</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Li</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luo</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>MEGAHIT: an ultra-fast single-node solution for large and complex metagenomics assembly via succinct de Bruijn graph</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1674</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv033</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25609793</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Lu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>YY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fuhrman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>COCACOLA: binning metagenomic contigs using sequence COmposition, read CoverAge, CO-alignment and paired-end read LinkAge</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>791</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw290</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27256312</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Seemann</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Abricate</article-title>. <source>GitHub</source>. <year>2020</year>. <comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/tseemann/abricate" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/tseemann/abricate</ext-link>. Accessed 20 June 2022</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Gupta</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Padmanabhan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>BR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diene</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>ARG-ANNOT, a new bioinformatic tool to discover antibiotic resistance genes in bacterial genomes</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>212</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.01310-13</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24145532</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Jia</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raphenya</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alcock</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>2017: expansion and model-centric curation of the comprehensive antibiotic resistance database</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>):<fpage>D566</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw1004</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27789705</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Doster</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lakin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dean</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>MEGARes 2.0: a database for classification of antimicrobial drug, biocide and metal resistance determinants in metagenomic sequence data</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>):<fpage>D561</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkz1010</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31722416</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Feldgarden</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brover</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haft</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Validating the AMRFinder tool and resistance gene database by using antimicrobial resistance genotype-phenotype correlations in a collection of isolates</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e00483</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00483-19</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31427293</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Hehemann</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Correc</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barbeyron</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Transfer of carbohydrate-active enzymes from marine bacteria to Japanese gut microbiota</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>464</volume>(<issue>7290</issue>):<fpage>908</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08937</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20376150</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Fu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Metagenomic sequencing combined with flow cytometry facilitated a novel microbial risk assessment framework for bacterial pathogens in municipal wastewater without cultivation</article-title>. <source>iMeta</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>e77</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/imt2.77</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38868349</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Dieterle</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rao</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>VB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Novel therapies and preventative strategies for primary and recurrent Clostridium difficile infections</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>1435</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>110</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nyas.13958</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30238983</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Yang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dong</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Carbapenem resistance-encoding and virulence-encoding conjugative plasmids in Klebsiella pneumoniae</article-title>. <source>Trends Microbiol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2020.04.012</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32448764</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Jaillard</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palmieri</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van&#x000a0;Belkum</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Interpreting k-mer-based signatures for antibiotic resistance prediction</article-title>. <source>Gigascience</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>giaa110</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gigascience/giaa110</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33068113</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sedlar</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupkova</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Provaznik</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>I</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Bioinformatics strategies for taxonomy independent binning and visualization of sequences in shotgun metagenomics</article-title>. <source>Comput Struct Biotechnol J</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>48</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.csbj.2016.11.005</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27980708</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="data">
<person-group person-group-type="curator">
<string-name>
<surname>Feng</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<data-title>Supporting data for &#x0201c;MOBFinder: A Tool for Mobilization Typing of Plasmid Metagenomic Fragments Based on a Language Model.&#x0201d;</data-title>. <source>GigaScience Database</source>. <year>2024</year>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5524/102559</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>