<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4589233</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-28334</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0139571</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>PATBox: A Toolbox for Classification and Analysis of P-Type ATPases</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">PATBox: A Toolbox for Classification and Analysis of P-Type ATPases</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>S&#x000f8;ndergaard</surname><given-names>Dan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="currentaff001">
<sup>&#x000a4;</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>Christian N&#x000f8;rgaard Storm</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Bioinformatics Research Centre, Aarhus University, Aarhus, Denmark</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Centre for Membrane Pumps in Cells and Disease, Aarhus University, Aarhus, Denmark</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>Dinesh</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>International Centre for Genetic Engineering and Biotechnology (ICGEB), INDIA</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: DS CNSP. Performed the experiments: DS. Analyzed the data: DS. Wrote the paper: DS CNSP.</p></fn><fn fn-type="current-aff" id="currentaff001"><p>&#x000a4; Current address: Bioinformatics Research Centre, Aarhus University, Aarhus, Denmark</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>das@birc.au.dk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e0139571</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2015 S&#x000f8;ndergaard, Pedersen</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>S&#x000f8;ndergaard, Pedersen</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0139571.pdf"/><abstract><p>P-Type ATPases are part of the regulatory system of the cell where they are responsible for transporting ions and lipids through the cell membrane. These pumps are found in all eukaryotes and their malfunction has been found to cause several severe diseases. Knowing which substrate is pumped by a certain P-Type ATPase is therefore vital. The P-Type ATPases can be divided into 11 subtypes based on their specificity, that is, the substrate that they pump. Determining the subtype experimentally is time-consuming. Thus it is of great interest to be able to accurately predict the subtype based on the amino acid sequence only. We present an approach to P-Type ATPase sequence classification based on the <italic>k</italic>-nearest neighbors, similar to a homology search, and show that this method provides performs very well and, to the best of our knowledge, better than any existing method despite its simplicity. The classifier is made available as a web service at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://services.birc.au.dk/patbox/">http://services.birc.au.dk/patbox/</ext-link> which also provides access to a database of potential P-Type ATPases and their predicted subtypes.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The authors have no support or funding to report.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="0"/><page-count count="5"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>P-Type ATPases are a large group of transmembrane transporters which pump ions and lipids as part of the regulatory system of the cell. It has been found that the malfunction of some P-Type ATPases cause several severe diseases in humans such as dystonia parkinsonism and Wilson disease [<xref rid="pone.0139571.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>The first P-Type ATPase, the sodium-potassium pump, was discovered in the 1950s and since then over 500 P-Type ATPases have been sequenced, their specificity experimentally verified, and several structures determined [<xref rid="pone.0139571.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Phylogenetic analysis has shown that the P-Type ATPases can be divided into 5 major and 11 minor subtypes (1A, 1B, 2A, 2B, 2C, 2D, 3A, 3B, 4, 5A and 5B) based on the substrate transported by the pump [<xref rid="pone.0139571.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>Experimentally determining the subtype of a P-Type ATPase is a slow and expensive process, but computational methods for predicting the subtype can aid this analysis significantly. After evaluating several methods for subtype prediction we found that the method presented in this paper provides surprisingly good results and in fact, to the best of our knowledge, performs better than all existing methods despite its simplicity.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>We present a machine learning approach for accurately predicting the subtype of a P-Type ATPase from the amino acid sequence by applying the <italic>k</italic>-nearest neighbors (<italic>k</italic>-NN) method [<xref rid="pone.0139571.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] to a curated dataset of 515 P-Type ATPase sequences annotated with experimentally verified subtypes. The dataset (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0139571.s001">S1 Dataset</xref>) has been gathered from [<xref rid="pone.0139571.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139571.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The sequences were obtained by mapping the accession identifiers to UniProtKB [<xref rid="pone.0139571.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Sequences with invalid characters and duplicates were removed. This resulted in 515 sequences with known subtype.</p><p>The classifier is made available as a web service. Sequences in FASTA format can be uploaded and the results are available as a web page or can be downloaded in comma-separated values (CSV) format. The web service also provides access to an automatically constructed database of all sequences from UniProtKB containing PROSITE motif D-K-T-G-T-[LIVM]-[TI] (PS00154) characteristic for P-Type ATPases annotated with their classification obtained by our <italic>k</italic>-NN method and a classifier based on the Sequence Learner (SeqL) method [<xref rid="pone.0139571.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139571.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], which is also made available through the web service. The latter method has previously been applied to P-Type ATPase classification in [<xref rid="pone.0139571.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. This database is thus a valuable resource for exploring P-Type ATPases.</p><p>The PATBox web service is implemented in Python using Flask as a web framework, Celery as a job queue, and SQLite as the database. The service is packaged using Docker for reproducability and maintainability.</p><sec id="sec003"><title>Method</title><p>The prediction method presented here is based on the <italic>k</italic>-NN method. Given a labeled dataset with data points (<italic>x</italic>
<sub>1</sub>, <italic>y</italic>
<sub>1</sub>), &#x02026;, (<italic>x</italic>
<sub><italic>n</italic></sub>, <italic>y</italic>
<sub><italic>n</italic></sub>) and a query with unknown label <italic>x</italic>, the <italic>k</italic>-NN method looks at the <italic>k</italic> nearest neighbors to <italic>x</italic> by applying some distance function <italic>d</italic> to each data point in the labeled dataset. The label <italic>y</italic> of <italic>x</italic> is then decided by majority vote. The distance function used in our approach is that of a BLAST [<xref rid="pone.0139571.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] search. Thus, for some sequence <italic>x</italic> a search is performed via BLAST and the top <italic>k</italic> results are then used to perform a majority vote. For <italic>k</italic> = 1 this corresponds to a homology search on the curated dataset. Formulating the method in terms of nearest neighbor classification enables us to evaluate it using well-known machine learning evaluation methods.</p><p>Additionally we have implemented weighed majority vote such that the weight of a class is given by the sum of the E-values of results belonging to that class divided by the number of results belonging to that class. The class with the minimum weight is chosen as the predicted subtype.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec004"><title>Results</title><p>The overall performance of the <italic>k</italic>-NN classifier has been evaluated by non-stratified 5-fold cross-validation. The dataset is shuffled and split into five parts. A fold is then carried out by training on four parts and predicting on the remaining part. This is repeated five times. We denote this as a run. To obtain an estimate of the variance of the accuracy the run is repeated 20 times, shuffling the sequences every time, for a total of 100 parts per <italic>k</italic> and the standard deviation and average accuracy is reported.</p><p>We evaluated both unweighed and weighed <italic>k</italic>-NN for 1 &#x02264; <italic>k</italic> &#x02264; 50 to determine the best <italic>k</italic> for each method.</p><p>The results are summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0139571.g001">Fig 1</xref> as a box plot. The average accuracy of the shuffled and repeated folds for each majority vote method is shown on the vertical axis with error bars showing the standard deviation. As we expect the accuracy of the two methods for <italic>k</italic> = 1 is the same. For both weighed and unweighed majority vote we see that as <italic>k</italic> increases as the accuracy decreases and the standard deviation increases. We obtain the best result when <italic>k</italic> = 1 for which the accuracy is 100%. Similar results are obtained for 2-fold cross-validation, where only half of the data is available for training, suggesting that the classifier is not prone to over-fitting (data not shown).</p><fig id="pone.0139571.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0139571.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>The results of 20 runs of 5-fold cross-validation for 1 &#x02264; <italic>k</italic> &#x02264; 50.</title><p>The weighed and unweighed approaches both perform well for small <italic>k</italic>. For <italic>k</italic> = 1 we obtain an accuracy of 100%. Dots are outliers. Lines show accuracy for reduced datasets.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0139571.g001"/></fig><p>The high accuracy is not a surprise. The average area-under-curve (AUC) over all classes of the Structured Logistic Regression (SLR) classifier in [<xref rid="pone.0139571.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] is 97.7%. An advanced prediction method presented in [<xref rid="pone.0139571.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] based on neural networks also yields a very high accuracy of 99.1% based on a 10-fold cross-validation on 5/6 of the dataset.</p><p>The consistently good results obtained through a variety of independent methods also suggests that the methods are not over-fitting and should generalize well.</p><p>To further investigate the predictive power of the <italic>k</italic>-NN method we used the CD-HIT [<xref rid="pone.0139571.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] web server to cluster the dataset at similarity thresholds of 30%, 50%, 75% and 90%, and extracted the representative sequences of each cluster. The cross-validation was repeated with weighed <italic>k</italic>-NN on the four reduced datasets and the results are shown as lines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0139571.g001">Fig 1</xref> (error bars omitted to reduce complexity of the plot). We find that the method is very robust, obtaining 100% accuracy for k = 1 for similarity thresholds as low as 50%.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec005"><title>Discussion</title><p>We present a method for accurate classification of P-Type ATPases into 11 subtypes based on the <italic>k</italic>-NN method using BLAST as a distance measure. We show experimentally that the optimal <italic>k</italic> = 1 for which we obtain an accuracy of 100%. More advanced methods have previously provided similar results which leads us to believe that the representative sequences for each subtype in the dataset cluster well based on sequence similarity. The results obtained by the <italic>k</italic>-NN method confirms this observation.</p><p>The contribution of this paper is twofold. Firstly, we show that <italic>k</italic>-NN performs extremely well on P-Type ATPases, despite the simplicity of the method, and that homology searches therefore can be used to determine the subtype of P-Type ATPase sequence. Secondly, the method presented here performs better than a multitude of more complicated methods, emphasising that simple methods should not be forgotten, even in the presence of more complicated methods.</p><p>The classifier is made available through a new web service for researchers in the field of P-Type ATPases, the P-Type ATPase Toolbox (PATBox), which also gives access to a database of predicted P-Type ATPases and their predicted subtype, based on UniProtKB [<xref rid="pone.0139571.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec006"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0139571.s001"><label>S1 Dataset</label><caption><title>Dataset of annotated P-Type ATPase sequences.</title><p>The dataset used for cross-validation and final training of the classifier described in this manuscript.</p><p>(FASTA)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0139571.s001.fasta"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We wish to thank Michael Knudsen and the reviewers for comments and corrections to the initial manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0139571.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bublitz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morth</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nissen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>P-type ATPases at a glance</article-title>. <source>Journal of Cell Science</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>124</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>2515</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2519</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 21768325?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21768325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139571.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Axelsen</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palmgren</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolution of Substrate Specificities in the P-Type ATPase Superfamily</article-title>. <source>Journal of molecular evolution</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>84</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/PL00006286</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 9419228?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9419228</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139571.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Cover</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nearest neighbor pattern classification</article-title>. <source>IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</source>. <year>1967</year>;<volume>13</volume>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TIT.1967.1053964</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139571.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>M&#x000f8;ller</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Asp</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palmgren</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Phylogenetic analysis of P5 P-type ATPases, a eukaryotic lineage of secretory pathway pumps</article-title>. <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>619</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>634</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2007.10.023</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18155930?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18155930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139571.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Magrane</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Consortium</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name>. <article-title>UniProt Knowledgebase: A hub of integrated protein data</article-title>. <source>Database</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>2011</volume>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/database/bar009</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21447597?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21447597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139571.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ifrim G, Bakir G, Weikum G. Fast logistic regression for text categorization with variable-length n-grams. In: the 14th ACM SIGKDD international conference. New York, New York, USA: ACM, Association for Computing Machinery; 2008. p. 354&#x02013;362.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139571.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ifrim G, Wiuf C. Bounded coordinate-descent for biological sequence classification in high dimensional predictor space. In: KDD&#x02019;11: Proceedings of the 17th ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery and data mining. ACM Request Permissions; 2011. p. 708&#x02013;716.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139571.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ifrim</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liboriussen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Axelsen</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palmgren</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nissen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Large Scale Identification and Categorization of Protein Sequences Using Structured Logistic Regression</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e85139</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085139</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24465495?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24465495</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139571.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coulouris</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Avagyan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bealer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>BLAST plus: architecture and applications</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>:&#x02013;. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-10-421</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20003500?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20003500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139571.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Espeholt L. Neural Networks for Classification of Protein Sequences. M.Sc. Thesis, Aarhus University. 2014.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139571.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>CD-HIT Suite: A web server for clustering and comparing biological sequences</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>680</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>682</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq003</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20053844?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20053844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>