<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biomed Res Int</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biomed Res Int</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BMRI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BioMed Research International</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2314-6133</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2314-6141</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6732622</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2019/2426958</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Predicting Drug-Disease Associations via Using Gaussian Interaction Profile and Kernel-Based Autoencoder</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4208-2027</contrib-id><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Han-Jing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5346-2394</contrib-id><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Yu-An</given-names></name><email>yahuang1991@gmail.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7373-7922</contrib-id><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>Zhu-Hong</given-names></name><email>zhuhongyou@gmail.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1">
<sup>1</sup>Xinjiang Technical Institute of Physics and Chemistry, Chinese Academy of Science, Urumqi 830011, China</aff><aff id="I2">
<sup>2</sup>University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100049, China</aff><aff id="I3">
<sup>3</sup>Department of Computing, Hong Kong Polytechnic University, Hung Hom, Hong Kong</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="other"><p>Academic Editor: Gerald J. Wyckoff</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>2019</volume><elocation-id>2426958</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>5</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2019 Han-Jing Jiang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Computational drug repositioning, designed to identify new indications for existing drugs, significantly reduced the cost and time involved in drug development. Prediction of drug-disease associations is promising for drug repositioning. Recent years have witnessed an increasing number of machine learning-based methods for calculating drug repositioning. In this paper, a novel feature learning method based on Gaussian interaction profile kernel and autoencoder (GIPAE) is proposed for drug-disease association. In order to further reduce the computation cost, both batch normalization layer and the full-connected layer are introduced to reduce training complexity. The experimental results of 10-fold cross validation indicate that the proposed method achieves superior performance on Fdataset and Cdataset with the AUCs of 93.30% and 96.03%, respectively, which were higher than many previous computational models. To further assess the accuracy of GIPAE, we conducted case studies on two complex human diseases. The top 20 drugs predicted, 14 obesity-related drugs, and 11 drugs related to Alzheimer's disease were validated in the CTD database. The results of cross validation and case studies indicated that GIPAE is a reliable model for predicting drug-disease associations.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>National Natural Science Foundation of China</funding-source><award-id>61702424</award-id><award-id>61572506</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source>Natural Science Basic Research Plan in Shaanxi Province</funding-source><award-id>2018JQ6015</award-id></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>For the past few decades, development of new drugs has been a time-consuming and costly process. The cost of developing new drugs has been rising in recent years, but the profits of new drugs are declining. Drug development is divided into three phases: the discovery phase, the clinical phase, and the clinical development phase. The first step in drug discovery phase is to identify potential drug-disease associations. Computational approaches for predicting drug-disease associations are drawing increasing attention in recent decades. Some redirected drugs have been successfully identified by rational observations. In view of the advantages of drug repositioning, it is an urgent need to utilize a more efficient approach for computational repositioning methods systematically.</p><p>In the past few years, a large number of computational methods have been proposed to predict drug-disease associations. For instance, Wang<italic> et al.</italic> proposed the TL-HGBI method, which is a computational framework based on a heterogeneous network model [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Mart&#x000ed;nez<italic> et al.</italic> built a network of interconnected drugs, proteins, and diseases and applied DrugNet to different types of tests for drug repositioning [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Lu<italic> et al.</italic> proposed a computational tool, DR2DI, to apply high-dimensional and heterogeneous omics data as information source to accurately reveal the potential associations between drugs and diseases [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Wu<italic> et al. </italic>developed a semisupervised graph cut algorithm, SSGC, to find the optimal graph cut [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Chen et al. used the recommendation system model to predict the relationship between drugs and diseases and put forward two different recommendation system models: ProbS and HeatS [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. However, the data integration adopted by these methods only simply considers the linear combination between different types of features. Developing extensible and interpretive models by fusing multiple data sources remains challenging.</p><p>The drug repositioning problem is basically a prediction problem, which is usually defined as a classification task to solve. Classification tasks normally include two processes, feature extraction and classification. In the feature extraction process, the features of the drug and the features of the disease are, respectively, extracted, and then the drug and the disease feature are spliced into a drug-disease pair feature. In the process of classification, the extracted drug-disease features are classified by a classifier to obtain the classification results. For the approach of calculating features, the raw dataset as the materials of prediction problem has large noise information, which is the main challenge for the prediction task. Choosing a method for extracting the most meaningful features in each sample plays an important role in the subsequent prediction tasks. For example, Wang<italic> et al.</italic> used the fingerprints of the drug to generate Tanimoto score as the feature of the drug. But the features which they used only contained the structural information of the drug. Liang<italic> et al.</italic> combined the drug fingerprints to extract the characteristics of LRSSL and extracted important drug characteristics from multiple drug characteristic spectra under the constraint of L1-norm [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>In recent years, in addition to the traditional feature extraction methods, feature extraction methods based on deep learning have been widely used. Autoencoder can learn features by reducing the dimension of the feature. For instance, Vishnubhotla<italic> et al.</italic> applied autoencoder to the modeling of low-dimensional coefficient model [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Badino<italic> et al.</italic> apply autoencoder for the unsupervised identification of subword units [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. With the development of autoencoder and deep learning techniques, applications based on autoencoder have received more and more research attention. Using Autoencoder to map raw features to low-dimensional spaces can more effectively measure the relationship between drugs and disease. Along this promising direction, this work proposes a novel feature extraction method based on autoencoder for learning a meaningful feature representation of drug fingerprints. By doing so we can set objective function with respect to recovering new links on known drug-disease association network, considering the nonlinear combination of different features.</p><p>Computational methods based on statistical rules and machine learning can be used to supplement clinical trials to determine the relationship between drugs and disease at low cost. In addition, they can integrate different types of data resources related to diseases and drugs to generate experimental validation candidates. Much has been done in this promising direction. For example, SCMFDD applies similarity constrained matrix factorization to identify potential indications for a given drug [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. LRSSL associates drugs with diseases through L1 regularized regression model, which improves the interpretability of the model [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. SSGC is a semisupervised graph cut algorithm to find the optimal graph cut [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Inspired by the success of the recent machine learning approach, we have proposed a machine learning-based method to predict new drugs that are most likely to treat a particular disease.</p><p>Public databases store all drug-disease associations that have been confirmed by clinical studies, but a large number of unknown relationships remain to be studied. In this study, we propose a drug repositioning computational method combining Gaussian interaction profile kernel and autoencoder (GIPAE). GIPAE combines data information from multiple data sources, including drug Gaussian interaction profile kernel similarity, drug fingerprints, disease semantic similarity, and diseases Gaussian interaction profile. Secondly, a module based on autoencoder technology is built to extract the useful information of drug fingerprints and integrated the drug Gaussian interaction profile as the final drug feature descriptor. Similarly, disease Gaussian interaction profile similarity and semantic similarity are integrated into the final disease feature descriptor. Finally, the feature descriptor is used as the inputs of the random forest classifier to predict the association of each type of drug with all diseases. The purpose of our study is to establish an effective prediction model to look for new drug-disease association and to provide deeper understanding for the study of drug-disease association by looking for the influence factors.</p><p>To evaluate the performance of GIPAE, 10-fold cross validation was implemented on the Fdataset. GIPAE was compared with several state-of-the-art methods which were previously proposed for drug repositioning. The results show that the proposed method has better performance than the state-of-art methods. In addition, we validated the proposed model against two human disease including Obesity and Alzheimer disease. As a result, more than 10 of the top-20 drug candidates (14/20 for Obesity and 11/20 for Alzheimer disease) predicted by GIPAE were successfully confirmed by CTD database [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. These experimental results indicated that GIPAE is effective to predict drug-disease associations on a large scale.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>2. Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>2.1. Datasets</title><p>In this work, we use two drug-disease association datasets following Gottlieb<italic> et al.</italic> and Luo<italic> et al. </italic>[<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. As shown in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, Gottlieb<italic> et al.</italic> collected 593 drugs, 313 diseases, and 1933 validated drug-disease associations from multiple data sources, which we here abbreviate as Fdataset. Luo<italic> et al</italic>. collected another dataset called Cdataset which covers 663 drugs, 409 diseases, and 2532 associations between them. The information of drugs is extracted from DrugBank, a comprehensive database containing extensive information about drugs [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The drug fingerprints defined in the PubChem database were extracted to represent the chemical substructures of drugs [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Disease information comes from human phenotypes definition in the Online Mendelian Inheritance in Man (OMIM) database, which focuses on human genes and disease [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In this work, we randomly generate negative samples from the unlabeled drug-disease pairs with the same number of the positive ones.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>2.2. Feature Extraction Based on Autoencoder</title><p>Autoencoder has made remarkable progress with regard to its learning features for classification of more complex data such as image classification or voice recognition. It proves to be effective in solving different types of problems in data mining, gaining increasing attention for the application of deep learning-based applications in feature extraction for drugs. Autoencoder is a specific neural network structure, which is composed of two parts: encoder and decoder. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>, it tries to learn a function:<disp-formula id="EEq1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mtable style="T1"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000b4;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">W</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="0.0pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="0.0pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>where x is the input vector. W = (W<sub>1</sub>, W<sub>2</sub>) and b = (b<sub>1</sub>, b<sub>2</sub>) represent the variables for weights and the biases. Given a training sample set x, the autoencoder first encodes the input x into the hidden representation through a deterministic mapping as<disp-formula id="EEq2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mtable style="T17"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Y</mml:mi><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="7.04pt" depth="2.4pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace height="7.04pt" depth="2.4pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="EEq3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="EEq3EAAAGADDCA"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="0.0pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="0.0pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">exp</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02061;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><italic>&#x003c3;</italic>(x) denotes an elementwise application of the logistic sigmoid. The resulting hidden representation, Y, is then mapped back to a reconstructed vector, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>x</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000b4;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, with a similar mapping function: <disp-formula id="EEq4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mtable style="T1"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000b4;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="7.04pt" depth="2.4pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace height="7.04pt" depth="2.4pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>In this paper, the drug fingerprint is encoded and decoded by an autoencoder to obtain a matrix FG representing structural features.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>2.3. Similarity for Drugs and Disease</title><p>The use of Gaussian interaction profile kernel can allow us to consider the nonlinear relationship of known drug-disease associations when we construct the feature representation. The method of Gaussian interaction profile kernel has been widely used in works relevant to disease prediction. For example, Chen et al. used Gaussian interaction profile kernel to calculate the similarity between MiRNA and disease when predicting Mirna-disease association [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Chen et al. used heterogeneous graphs to infer the association of Mirna-disease and used Gaussian interaction profile kernel to calculate the miRNA similarity and disease similarity [<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Lu et al. used the Gaussian interaction profile kernel to calculate the disease similarity when predicting the drug-disease association [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The Gaussian interaction profile of the disease is calculated based on the assumption that similar diseases (e.g., different subtypes of lung cancer) can often bind to the same drug molecule and vice versa. The definition binary vector Y(d(x)) represents the interaction profiles of disease d(x) whose value describe whether d(x) is associated with each disease. The binary vector Y(d(x)) is equivalent to the x-th row vector of adjacency matrix. Then Gaussian interaction profile kernel similarity between d(x) and d(y) was defined as follows:<disp-formula id="EEq5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mtable style="T3"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:malignmark/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="8.07999pt" depth="2.98001pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="0.0pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="0.0pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="2.555pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="2.555pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace height="8.07999pt" depth="2.98001pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/><mml:mspace width="10pt"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">exp</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02061;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="10.04pt" depth="2.98001pt"/><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02202;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="&#x02016;" close="&#x02016;" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="8.07999pt" depth="2.98001pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Y</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="7.04pt" depth="1.84001pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace height="7.04pt" depth="1.84001pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Y</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="8.07999pt" depth="2.98001pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace height="8.07999pt" depth="2.98001pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace height="8.07999pt" depth="2.98001pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace height="10.04pt" depth="2.98001pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>where parameter &#x02202;<sub>d</sub> was implemented to tune the kernel bandwidth with normalizing original parameter as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02202;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000b4;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as follows:<disp-formula id="EEq6"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mtable style="T1"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02202;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02202;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000b4;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="&#x02016;" close="&#x02016;" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Y</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>Similarly, the definition binary vector Y(u(x)) represents the interaction profiles with drug u(x), and Y(u(y)) represents the interaction profiles with the drug u(y). Gaussian interaction profile kernel similarity for drug GIP<sub>drug</sub> between u(x) and u(y) is calculated as follows:<disp-formula id="EEq7"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mtable style="T17"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">exp</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02061;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="10.04pt" depth="2.98001pt"/><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02202;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="&#x02016;" close="&#x02016;" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="8.07999pt" depth="2.98001pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Y</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="6.93999pt" depth="1.84001pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace height="6.93999pt" depth="1.84001pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Y</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="8.07999pt" depth="2.98001pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace height="8.07999pt" depth="2.98001pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace height="8.07999pt" depth="2.98001pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace height="10.04pt" depth="2.98001pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="EEq8"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="EEq8EAAADBCDCA"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02202;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02202;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000b4;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="&#x02016;" close="&#x02016;" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Y</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>Here, the value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02202;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000b4;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is set to 0.5 for simplicity, and the nu represents the number of the drugs.</p><p>We further calculate another type of disease similarity, that is, disease semantic similarity by using MimMiner, which measures disease similarity by calculating similarities between grid items. Specifically, we measure disease similarity using the similarity between MeSH terms and then compute similarity of correlation between drugs and diseases using known drug-disease association information. By applying the above method, the disease semantic similarity DS<sub>r</sub> was obtained. We construct a new weighted disease sharing network based on the known drug-disease associations. The disease set represents the point of the network; the shared disease of the disease pair represents the weight. Diseases in the sharing network were clustered in groups by using ClusterONE [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. ClusterONE is a method of graph clustering, which can be used to identify the cohesive modules in the weighted network. The cohesiveness of a cluster K could be defined by ClusterONE: <disp-formula id="EEq9"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mtable style="T1"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="6.39pt" depth="0.0pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="6.39pt" depth="0.0pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>where C<sub>in</sub> represents the total weight of edges in vertex set K, <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>bound</italic></sub> represents the total weight of edges connecting the set with the rest of the group, and P is the penalty term. We assume that drug u<sub>q</sub> and drug u<sub>p</sub> are located in the same cluster K; the disease semantic similarity DS between drug u<sub>q</sub> and drug u<sub>p</sub> is defined as [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]<disp-formula id="EEq10"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="M11"><mml:mtable style="T1"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="7.04pt" depth="1.84001pt"/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="6.39pt" depth="0.0pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="6.39pt" depth="0.0pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace height="7.04pt" depth="1.84001pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>In addition, for the disease semantic similarity between two diseases, if it is equal to or greater than 1, we use 0.99 instead.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>2.4. Multisource Feature Fusion</title><p>In this study, we ultimately used descriptors that fused multiple sources of data including disease similarity, drug similarity, and drug fingerprint to predict the drug-disease association. There are some unknown associations for diseases/drugs in the dataset, and the corresponding Gaussian interaction profile kernel has a value of 0. To address this challenge, we use disease semantic similarity and drug structure similarity as a complement. The advantage of this method is that it can reflect the features of disease/drug from different perspectives.</p><p>We constructed two types of disease similarity, a semantic similarity model DS and a Gaussian interaction profile kernel similarity GIP<sub>dis</sub>. Calculate the disease similarity Sim(d(x), d(y))for disease d(x) and disease d(y) as<disp-formula id="EEq11"><label>(11)</label><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mtable style="T1"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="8.07999pt" depth="2.98001pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="0.0pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="0.0pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="2.555pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="2.555pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace height="8.07999pt" depth="2.98001pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="{" close="" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>We use a Gaussian interaction profile kernel similarity of a given disease pair (d(x), d(y)) to fill the feature matrix. If the disease Gaussian interaction profile kernel for a given disease pair (d(x), d(y)) is zero, then the disease semantic similarity is used to fill.</p><p>We integrate drug structure similarity FG and drug Gaussian interaction profile kernel similarity GIP<sub>drug</sub> for the similarity of drugs. The formula calculating drug similarity RSim is<disp-formula id="EEq12"><label>(12)</label><mml:math id="M13"><mml:mtable style="T1"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="8.07999pt" depth="2.98001pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="0.0pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="0.0pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="2.555pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="2.555pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace height="8.07999pt" depth="2.98001pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="6.68pt" depth="2.48749pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">G</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="6.68pt" depth="2.48749pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>The RSim and FG feature matrices are spliced in line.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title>2.5. Feature Extraction in GIPAE</title><p>Deep learning has received extensive attention in the field of predicting drug-disease association. We introduce the batch normalization layer and the full-connected layer here to further improve the feature of drugs and disorders through deep learning. In the deep neural network training process, each batch sent to the network is usually trained in order, so that each batch has a different distribution. The Batch Normalization layer forcibly pulls the distribution of the neural network input values back to the standard normal distribution with a mean of 0 and a variance of 1. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>, we introduce a full-connected layer to map features to the sample tag space. Here, the activation function of each neuron in the full-connection layer adopts ReLU function:<disp-formula id="EEq13"><label>(13)</label><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mtable style="T1"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="0.0pt"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="4.20999pt" depth="0.0pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">max</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02061;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="6.35999pt" depth="1.16998pt"/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="6.35999pt" depth="1.16998pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>Ensemble learning algorithms have attracted increasing attention because they are more accurate than a single classifier. They are based on the premise that a group of classifiers is better than a single classifier. Random Forest (RF) has been widely applied in bioinformatics problems, including protein or peptide recognition, in vivo transcription factor binding prediction, and enhancer identification [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The RF consists of a combination of classifiers, each of which assigns the most frequent class to the input vector <italic>&#x003b5;</italic> by a single vote.<disp-formula id="EEq14"><label>(14)</label><mml:math id="M15"><mml:mtable style="T1"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">v</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="{" close="}" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="9.2pt" depth="2.48749pt"/><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace height="4.53pt" depth="0.12pt"/><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mspace height="4.53pt" depth="0.12pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace height="9.2pt" depth="2.48749pt"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></inline-formula> is the class prediction of the b-th random tree. RF increases tree diversity by growing trees from different subsets of training data. Since RF corrects the habit of overfitting a training set by a decision tree, it generally has more stable prediction performance than other single classifiers such as SVM. In the GIPAE model, we chose random forests as our classifier.</p><p>The process of feature representation consists of three steps (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>). Specifically, in the first step, the drug Gaussian interaction profile kernel is combined with drug fingerprint and disease Gaussian interaction profile kernel is combined with disease semantic similarity to obtain the drug and disease similar descriptors. The second step uses the full-connected layer to extract the features based on the combined drug and disease similarity. In its last step, a random forest classifier is introduced to yield the predicted scores using the outputs of second step as inputs.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>3. Results and Discussion</title><sec id="sec3.1"><title>3.1. Evaluation Criteria</title><p>To evaluate the performance of GIPAE, different types of evaluation criteria were used in this work to evaluate the performance of the proposed model, i.e., precision (Prec.), F1-score, Recall, and accuracy (Acc.).<disp-formula id="EEq15"><label>(15)</label><mml:math id="M17"><mml:mtable style="T17"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="EEq16"><label>(16)</label><mml:math id="EEq16ECAABACCCA"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="EEq17"><label>(17)</label><mml:math id="EEq17EBAABACCCA"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>-</mml:mtext><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="EEq18"><label>(18)</label><mml:math id="EEq18EAAABACCCA"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>where TP, FP, and FN represent the number of positive samples correctly predicted in the model, denoting the number of correctly predicted negative samples, the number of falsely predicted positive samples, and the number of false predicted negative samples, respectively. For further evaluation, we also compute the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve, sum up the ROC curve in a numerical way, and calculate the area under the ROC curve (AUC).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title>3.2. Evaluate Prediction Performance</title><p>In this study, we trained machine learning models to predict whether certain drugs are related to certain diseases. The performance of the model was evaluated by cross validation method on Fdataset and Cdataset. In this method, all data sets are randomly divided into ten roughly equal parts for cross validation. Specifically, one group of them is taken as the test set, and the remaining nine groups are taken as the training set. Each time a different subset is used as the test set and the remaining nine subsets are used as training sets to form ten models. In this process, the Gaussian interaction profile kernel similarity uses the matrix obtained above. Finally, the ten models are used to predict the classification, and the average of ten models was taken as the final result.</p><p>We implemented our proposed method by using 10-fold cross validation on the Fdataset. <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table"> Table 2</xref> shows that our proposed model yielded an average accuracy of 87.30%, precision of 86.06%, recall of 89.08%, and f1-score of 87.53% with standard deviations of 1.84%, 2.38%, 1.49%, and 1.74%, respectively. <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table"> Table 3</xref> shows that, in the experiment on the Cdataset, our method yielded the average accuracy of 90.52%, precision of 89.77%, recall of 91.47%, and f1-score of 90.60% with standard deviations of 1.57%, 1.45%, 2.31%, and 1.61%, respectively.</p><p>We further statistically discuss the prediction result of 10-fold cross validation. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>, we illustrate the distribution of predicted scores of positive and negative samples on Fdataset. As a result, for more than 85% of negative samples and 90% of positive samples, their predicted scores are lower than 0.2 and higher than 0.8, respectively. Specifically, 69% and 16% of negative samples' scores lie in the range of 0-0.1 and 0.1-0.2, respectively, while 76% and 14.3% of the positive samples achieve scores of 0.9-1.0 and 0.8-0.9, respectively.</p><p>These results indicate that the information including the Gaussian interaction profile kernel, the disease semantic similarity, and the drug fingerprint is sufficient to predict the interaction of a given drug-disease pair. The strong prediction performance of GIPAE model comes from the selection of drug-disease pair extraction method and machine learning classifier. Random forest classifier shows better performance due to ensemble model and random tree splitting strategy.</p><p>To further evaluate the performance of the proposed method, we compared it to the other five models previously proposed using the same ten-fold cross validation framework and exploring the same datasets. The five methods are MBiRW [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], DrugNet [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], HGBI [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], KBMF [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], and DRRs [<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref> and <xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, on Fdataset, our method achieves the highest AUC (Area Under the ROC Curve) which is 0.155 higher than that yielded by DrugNet, 0.104 higher than HGBI, and 0.018 higher than KBMF. MBiRW and DDRS yielded poor AUCs of 0.917 and 0.930. On Cdataset, GIPAE has an AUC of 0.960. DrugNet has an AUC of 0.804; MBiRW, HGBI, KBMF, and DRRS yielded AUC of 0.858, 0.928, 0.933, and 0.947. The results from both experiments demonstrate that the performance of GIPAE is significantly better than that of the other five models. Different from these comparison methods, our model has a wider application, using deep learning to express low-dimensional space, combined with ensemble classifier and random tree splitting strategy to achieve more significant prediction results.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title>3.3. Comparison among Different Classifiers</title><p>In this section, we try to replace random forest with Support vector machine (SVM) to compare the effectiveness of combination of the proposed feature extraction method and random forest classifier [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. SVM is a widely used supervised learning algorithm with outstanding performance in classification and regression problems. Tables <xref rid="tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref> and <xref rid="tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref> show the results yielded by combining the proposed feature descriptor with support vector machine on Fdataset and Cdataset. On Fdataset, SVM achieved accuracy, precision, recall, and f1-score being 79.31%, 79.28%, 79.36%, and 79.30%. Their standard deviations are 1.58, 1.42, 2.69, and 1.75, respectively. On Cdataset, SVM achieved accuracy, precision, recall, and f1-score being 83.83%, 83.93%, 83.69%, and 83.80%, respectively. Their standard deviations are 1.60, 1.71, 1.92, and 1.62. It can be seen from the comparison that the classification result of the random forest classifier is better than the SVM classifier on F dataset and Cdataset. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>, on Fdataset, the mean AUC is 0.8760. On Cdataset, the mean AUC was 0.9146. Among them, the average accuracy of random forests on Fdataset and Cdatasets is 7% and 6.69% higher than SVM, respectively. From the comparison we can see that, due to the ensemble model and its random tree splitting strategy, the random forest classifier can achieve better performance than the SVM classifier using the proposed feature descriptor.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>4. Case Study</title><p>To further evaluate the predictive effect of this model, we selected Obesity and Alzheimer disease for case studies. Specifically, we use Fdataset as the training set to train the model. It is worth noting that when predicting the relevance of a particular disease, all associations between a particular disease and the drug should be removed. Take remaining drug-disease associations as positive sample. Then, among all unknown associations, the same number of associations with the positive sample is randomly selected as negative samples, and the negative samples are guaranteed not to be repeated. Based on the predicted results of GIPAE, the top 20 drugs were selected and compared with the CTD database.</p><p>Obesity is defined by the world health organization as abnormal or excessive accumulation of fat that poses a threat to human health. It is a major risk factor for many chronic diseases. As shown in <xref rid="tab7" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>, after we compared the predicted results with the CTD database records, 14 of the top 20 predicted drugs were confirmed. The other disease in our case study is Alzheimer disease, which is a neurodegenerative disease. Alzheimer disease is caused by a variety of factors, including biological and psychosocial factors. <xref rid="tab8" ref-type="table"> Table 8</xref> lists the top-20 drugs predicted by GIPAE to be associated with Alzheimer disease. Checking on CTD database, we successfully confirm 11 of them. It is worth noting that high-ranked interactions that have not been reported may also exist in reality. The case studies of Obesity and Alzheimer disease suggest that GIPAE has a good performance with regard to predicting the most promising diseases.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>5. Conclusion</title><p>Drug-disease associations provide critical information for drug reposition. Biological experiments for drug repositioning are very expensive, so it is more advantageous to use computational methods to address drug repositioning problems. In this study, we proposed a novel computational method based on machine learning and deep learning called GIPAE. An underlying idea of the method that we propose is that the known drug-disease associations and drug fingerprint have a great influence on drug-disease associations. Specifically, GIPAE is a computational model based on Gaussian interaction profile kernel and autoencoder. It effectively integrates data on the association between known drugs and diseases.</p><p>We evaluated our proposed model on Fdataset and Cdataset datasets and tested them with 10-fold cross validation. On Fdataset, GIPAE obtained 86.06% prediction precision with 89.08% recall and the AUC of 93.30%. On Cdataset, GIPAE obtained 89.77% prediction precision with 91.47% recall and the AUC of 96.03%. These good experimental results show that our model can effectively predict the potential association between drugs and diseases. In addition, we conducted case studies on two complex human diseases (Obesity and Alzheimer disease) and found that more than half of the top 20 predicted results could be verified in the CTD database. These good experimental results indicate that this method can be used as a reliable application to predict potential interactions between drugs and diseases. In future work, we will consider ways to improve feature extraction to achieve higher prediction accuracy.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We are grateful to all group members in the research group led by Professor Zhu-Hong You for their valuable suggestions. This study was funded by the National Natural Science Foundation of China under Grant (Nos. 61702424 and 61572506) and the Natural Science Basic Research Plan in Shaanxi Province (No. 2018JQ6015).</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>The datasets that we collected in this work are freely available on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/HanJingJiang/GIPAE">https://github.com/HanJingJiang/GIPAE</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors certify that they have no affiliations with or involvement in any organization or entity with any financial interest or nonfinancial interest in the subject matter or materials discussed in this manuscript.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug repositioning by integrating target information through a heterogeneous network model</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source><year>2014</year><volume>30</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>2923</fpage><lpage>2930</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu403</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24974205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cano</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fajardo</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DrugNet: Network-based drug&#x02013;disease prioritization by integrating heterogeneous data</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Artificial Intelligence in Medicine</italic></source><year>2015</year><volume>63</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.artmed.2014.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25704113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DR2DI: a powerful computational tool for predicting novel drug-disease associations</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Computer-Aided Molecular Design</italic></source><year>2018</year><volume>32</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>642</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10822-018-0117-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29687309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting drug-disease interactions by semi-supervised graph cut algorithm and three-layer data integration</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Medical Genomics</italic></source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><issue>S5, article no. 79</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12920-017-0311-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W. J. C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Network-based inference methods for drug repositioning</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Computational and Mathematical Methods in Medicine</italic></source><year>2015</year><volume>2015</volume><fpage>7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">130620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2015/130620</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>LRSSL: predict and interpret drug&#x02013;disease associations based on data integration using sparse subspace learning</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source><year>2017</year><volume>33</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btw770</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vishnubhotla</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramabhadran</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An autoencoder neural-network based low-dimensionality approach to excitation modeling for HMM-based text-to-speech</article-title><conf-name>Proceedings of the 2010 IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech, and Signal Processing, ICASSP 2010</conf-name><conf-date>March 2010</conf-date><conf-loc>USA</conf-loc><fpage>4614</fpage><lpage>4617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-78049412607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Badino</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Canevari</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fadiga</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Metta</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An auto-encoder based approach to unsupervised learning of subword units</article-title><conf-name>Proceedings of the 2014 IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech, and Signal Processing, ICASSP 2014</conf-name><conf-date>May 2014</conf-date><fpage>7634</fpage><lpage>7638</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-84905227103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predicting drug-disease associations by using similarity constrained matrix factorization</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Bioinformatics</italic></source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1, article no. 233</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-018-2220-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mattingly</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenstein</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colby</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Forrest Jr</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Comparative Toxicogenomics Database (CTD): a resource for comparative toxicological studies</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Experimental Zoology. Part A, Comparative Experimental Biology</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>305A</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>689</fpage><lpage>692</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jez.a.307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>G. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruppin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PREDICT: a method for inferring novel drug indications with application to personalized medicine</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Molecular Systems Biology</italic></source><year>2014</year><volume>7, article 496</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/msb.2011.26</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-79958754253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Drug repositioning based on comprehensive similarity measures and Bi-Random walk algorithm</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source><year>2016</year><volume>32</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>2664</fpage><lpage>2671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-84990913647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27153662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wishart</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knox</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DrugBank: a knowledgebase for drugs, drug actions and drug targets</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Research</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>D901</fpage><lpage>D906</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm958</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-38549151817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18048412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolton</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiessen</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PubChem: integrated platform of small molecules and biological activities</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Annual Reports in Computational Chemistry</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1574-1400(08)00012-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamosh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amberger</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bocchini</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>McKusick</surname><given-names>V. A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Online Mendelian Inheritance in Man (OMIM), a knowledgebase of human genes and genetic disorders</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Research</italic></source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/30.1.52</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0035998736</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11752252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>WBSMDA: within and between score for MiRNA-disease association prediction</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Scientific Reports</italic></source><year>2016</year><volume>6, article 21106</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep21106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>Z.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.-A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>G.-Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HGIMDA: Heterogeneous graph inference for miRNA-disease association prediction</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Oncotarget </italic></source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><issue>40</issue><fpage>65257</fpage><lpage>65269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-84994092024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.11251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27533456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nepusz</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paccanaro</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detecting overlapping protein complexes in protein-protein interaction networks</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Nature Methods</italic></source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-84860361165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22426491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breiman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Random forests</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Machine Learning</italic></source><year>2001</year><volume>45</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0035478854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1010933404324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">Zbl1007.68152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug target predictions based on heterogeneous graph inference</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing</italic></source><year>2013</year><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23424111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000f6;nen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting drug-target interactions from chemical and genomic kernels using Bayesian matrix factorization</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source><year>2012</year><volume>28</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>2304</fpage><lpage>2310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bts360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-84866459051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22730431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Computational drug repositioning using low-rank matrix approximation and randomized algorithms</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source><year>2018</year><volume>34</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1904</fpage><lpage>1912</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bty013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29365057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cortes</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vapnik</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Support-vector networks</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Machine Learning</italic></source><year>1995</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-34249753618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00994018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">Zbl0831.68098</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Structure of autoencoder.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2019-2426958.001"/></fig><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Structure of full-connected layer.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2019-2426958.002"/></fig><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Flowchart of GIPAE model to predict potential drug-disease associations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2019-2426958.003"/></fig><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Positive and negative sample probability distribution.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2019-2426958.004"/></fig><fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>(a) and (b) Shown are the ROC curves yielded by GIPAE using 10-fold cross validation on Fdataset and Cdataset, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2019-2426958.005"/></fig><fig id="fig6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>(a) and (b) Shown are the ROC curves yielded by SVM using 10-fold cross validation on Fdataset and Cdataset, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BMRI2019-2426958.006"/></fig><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>General statistics on Fdataset and Cdataset.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Datasets</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drugs</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diseases</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interactions</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cdataset</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">663</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">409</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2532</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fdataset</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">593</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">313</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1933</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Experimental results of 10-fold cross validation yielded by GIPAE on Fdataset.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test set</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acc. (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre. (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recall (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F1-score (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.66</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.57</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.69</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.57</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.93</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.34</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.71</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.94</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.92</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.56</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.97</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.61</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.49</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.77</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.53</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>87.30&#x000b1;1.84</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>86.06&#x000b1;2.38</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>89.08&#x000b1;1.49</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>87.53&#x000b1;1.74</italic>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tab3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Experimental results of the 10-fold cross validation yielded by GIPAE on Cdataset.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test set</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acc. (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre. (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recall (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F1-score (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.91</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.70</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.97</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.93</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.70</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.91</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.72</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.70</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.49</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.87</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.47</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.91</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.66</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.49</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.54</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.84</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>90.52&#x000b1;1.57</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>89.77&#x000b1;1.45</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>91.47&#x000b1;2.31</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>90.60&#x000b1;1.61</italic>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tab4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>AUC results yielded by different methods using 10-fold cross validation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02009;</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fdataset</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cdataset</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DrugNet [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.778</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.804</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HGBI [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.829</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.858</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KBMF [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.915</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.928</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBiRW [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.917</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.933</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRRS [<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.930</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.947</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GIPAE (the proposed method)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.933</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.960</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tab5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Results yielded by SVM on Fdataset using 10-fold cross validation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test set</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acc. (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre. (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recall (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F1-score (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.87</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.79</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.53</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.83</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.93</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.91</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.50</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.27</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.66</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.87</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.90</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.83</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.76</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.57</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.37</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.46</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.76</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.61</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.79</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>79.31&#x000b1;1.58</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>79.28&#x000b1;1.42</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>79.36&#x000b1;2.69</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>79.30&#x000b1;1.75</italic>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tab6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Results yielded by SVM on Cdataset using 10-fold cross validation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test set</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acc. (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre. (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recall (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F1-score (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.68</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.61</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.99</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.77</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.79</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.34</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.62</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.41</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.77</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.58</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.58</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.58</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.98</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.82</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>83.83&#x000b1;1.60</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>83.93&#x000b1;1.71</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>83.69&#x000b1;1.92</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>83.80&#x000b1;1.62</italic>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tab7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Top-20 drugs predicted by GIPAE to be associated with Obesity based on Fdatabase.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Index</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug name</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evidence</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Index</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug name</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evidence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phendimetrazine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Almotriptan</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N.A.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ticlopidine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thioguanine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N.A.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sibutramine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terfenadine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitroglycerin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sodium tetradecyl sulfate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N.A.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesalazine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salsalate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flutamide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ramipril</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N.A.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Felodipine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Procainamide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N.A.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diethylpropion</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pravastatin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Desipramine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phentermine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Captopril</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N.A.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orlistat</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tab8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 8</label><caption><p>Top-20 drugs predicted by GIPAE to be associated with Alzheimer disease based on Fdatabase.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Index</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug name</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evidence</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Index</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug name</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evidence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dopamine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ranitidine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methylergonovine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N.A.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nizatidine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N.A.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meperidine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N.A.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nifedipine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gemcitabine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lithium</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Betamethasone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Esomeprazole</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N.A.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pioglitazone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ergocalciferol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guanethidine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dihydrocodeine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N.A.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valrubicin<break/></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N.A.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amitriptyline</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Teriparatide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N.A.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Almotriptan</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rizatriptan</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N.A.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adenosine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N.A.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>